Dedication[1]

I.

Bob Southey! You're a poet—Poet-laureate,

And representative of all the race;

Although 't is true that you turned out a Tory at

Last,—yours has lately been a common case;

And now, my Epic Renegade! what are ye at?

With all the Lakers, in and out of place?

A nest of tuneful persons, to my eye

Like "four and twenty Blackbirds in a pye;

II.

"Which pye being opened they began to sing,"

(This old song and new simile holds good),

"A dainty dish to set before the King,"

Or Regent, who admires such kind of food;—

And Coleridge, too, has lately taken wing,

But like a hawk encumbered with his hood,—

Explaining Metaphysics to the nation—

I wish he would explain his Explanation.[2]

III.

You, Bob! are rather insolent, you know,

At being disappointed in your wish

To supersede all warblers here below,

And be the only Blackbird in the dish;

And then you overstrain yourself, or so,

And tumble downward like the flying fish

Gasping on deck, because you soar too high, Bob,

And fall, for lack of moisture, quite a-dry, Bob![3]

IV.

And Wordsworth, in a rather long "Excursion,"

(I think the quarto holds five hundred pages),

Has given a sample from the vasty version

Of his new system[4] to perplex the sages;

'T is poetry-at least by his assertion,

And may appear so when the dog-star rages—

And he who understands it would be able

To add a story to the Tower of Babel.

V.

You—Gentlemen! by dint of long seclusion

From better company, have kept your own

At Keswick, and, through still continued fusion

Of one another's minds, at last have grown

To deem as a most logical conclusion,

That Poesy has wreaths for you alone:

There is a narrowness in such a notion,

Which makes me wish you'd change your lakes for Ocean.

VI.

I would not imitate the petty thought,

Nor coin my self-love to so base a vice,

For all the glory your conversion brought,

Since gold alone should not have been its price.

You have your salary; was 't for that you wrought?

And Wordsworth has his place in the Excise.[5]

You're shabby fellows—true—but poets still,

And duly seated on the Immortal Hill.

VII.

Your bays may hide the baldness of your brows—

Perhaps some virtuous blushes;—let them go—

To you I envy neither fruit nor boughs—

And for the fame you would engross below,

The field is universal, and allows

Scope to all such as feel the inherent glow:

Scott, Rogers, Campbell, Moore, and Crabbe, will try

'Gainst you the question with posterity.

VIII.

For me, who, wandering with pedestrian Muses,

Contend not with you on the wingéd steed,

I wish your fate may yield ye, when she chooses,

The fame you envy, and the skill you need;

And, recollect, a poet nothing loses

In giving to his brethren their full meed

Of merit—and complaint of present days

Is not the certain path to future praise.

IX.

He that reserves his laurels for posterity

(Who does not often claim the bright reversion)

Has generally no great crop to spare it, he

Being only injured by his own assertion;

And although here and there some glorious rarity

Arise like Titan from the sea's immersion,

The major part of such appellants go

To—God knows where—for no one else can know.

X.

If, fallen in evil days on evil tongues,[6]

Milton appealed to the Avenger, Time,

If Time, the Avenger, execrates his wrongs,

And makes the word "Miltonic" mean "Sublime,"

He deigned not to belie his soul in songs,

Nor turn his very talent to a crime;

He did not loathe the Sire to laud the Son,

But closed the tyrant-hater he begun.

XI.

Think'st thou, could he—the blind Old Man—arise

Like Samuel from the grave, to freeze once more

The blood of monarchs with his prophecies,

Or be alive again—again all hoar

With time and trials, and those helpless eyes,

And heartless daughters—worn—and pale[7]—and poor;

Would he adore a sultan? he obey

The intellectual eunuch Castlereagh?[8]

XII.

Cold-blooded, smooth-faced, placid miscreant!

Dabbling its sleek young hands in Erin's gore,

And thus for wider carnage taught to pant,

Transferred to gorge upon a sister shore,

The vulgarest tool that Tyranny could want,

With just enough of talent, and no more,

To lengthen fetters by another fixed,

And offer poison long already mixed.

XIII.

An orator of such set trash of phrase

Ineffably—legitimately vile,

That even its grossest flatterers dare not praise,

Nor foes—all nations—condescend to smile,—

Nor even a sprightly blunder's spark can blaze

From that Ixion grindstone's ceaseless toil,

That turns and turns to give the world a notion

Of endless torments and perpetual motion.

XIV.

A bungler even in its disgusting trade,

And botching, patching, leaving still behind

Something of which its masters are afraid—

States to be curbed, and thoughts to be confined,

Conspiracy or Congress to be made—

Cobbling at manacles for all mankind—

A tinkering slave-maker, who mends old chains,

With God and Man's abhorrence for its gains.

XV.

If we may judge of matter by the mind,

Emasculated to the marrow It

Hath but two objects, how to serve, and bind,

Deeming the chain it wears even men may fit,

Eutropius of its many masters,[9]—blind

To worth as freedom, wisdom as to wit,

Fearless—because no feeling dwells in ice,

Its very courage stagnates to a vice.[10]

XVI.

Where shall I turn me not to view its bonds,

For I will never feel them?—Italy!

Thy late reviving Roman soul desponds

Beneath the lie this State-thing breathed o'er thee[11]—

Thy clanking chain, and Erin's yet green wounds,

Have voices—tongues to cry aloud for me.

Europe has slaves—allies—kings—armies still—

And Southey lives to sing them very ill.

XVII.

Meantime, Sir Laureate, I proceed to dedicate,

In honest simple verse, this song to you.

And, if in flattering strains I do not predicate,

'T is that I still retain my "buff and blue;"[12]

My politics as yet are all to educate:

Apostasy's so fashionable, too,

To keep one creed's a task grown quite Herculean;

Is it not so, my Tory, ultra-Julian?[13]

Venice, Sept. 16, 1818.

FOOTNOTES:

[1] {3}["As the Poem is to be published anonymously, omit the Dedication. I won't attack the dog in the dark. Such things are for scoundrels and renegadoes like himself" [Revise]. See, too, letter to Murray, May 6, 1819 (Letters, 1900, iv. 294); and Southey's letter to Bedford, July 31, 1819 (Selections from the Letters, etc., 1856, in. 137, 138). According to the editor of the Works of Lord Byron, 1833 (xv. 101), the existence of the Dedication "became notorious" in consequence of Hobhouse's article in the Westminster Review, 1824. He adds, for Southey's consolation and encouragement, that "for several years the verses have been selling in the streets as a broadside," and that "it would serve no purpose to exclude them on the present occasion." But Southey was not appeased. He tells Allan Cunningham (June 3, 1833) that "the new edition of Byron's works is ... one of the very worst symptoms of these bad times" (Life and Correspondence, 1850, vi. 217).]

[2] {4}[In the "Critique on Bertram," which Coleridge contributed to the Courier, in 1816, and republished in the Biographia Literaria, in 1817 (chap, xxiii.), he gives a detailed analysis of "the old Spanish play, entitled Atheista Fulminato [vide ante, the 'Introduction to Don Juan'] ... which under various names (Don Juan, the Libertine, etc.) has had its day of favour in every country throughout Europe ... Rank, fortune, wit, talent, acquired knowledge, and liberal accomplishments, with beauty of person, vigorous health, and constitutional hardihood,—all these advantages, elevated by the habits and sympathies of noble birth and national character, are supposed to have combined in Don Juan, so as to give him the means of carrying into all its practical consequences the doctrine of a godless nature, as the sole ground and efficient cause not only of all things, events, and appearances, but likewise of all our thoughts, sensations, impulses, and actions. Obedience to nature is the only virtue." It is possible that Byron traced his own lineaments in this too life-like portraiture, and at the same time conceived the possibility of a new Don Juan, "made up" after his own likeness. His extreme resentment at Coleridge's just, though unwise and uncalled-for, attack on Maturin stands in need of some explanation. See letter to Murray, September 17, 1817 (Letters, 1900, iv. 172).]

[3] ["Have you heard that Don Juan came over with a dedication to me, in which Lord Castlereagh and I (being hand in glove intimates) were coupled together for abuse as 'the two Roberts'? A fear of persecution (sic) from the one Robert is supposed to be the reason why it has been suppressed" (Southey to Rev. H. Hill, August 13, 1819, Selections from the Letters, etc., 1856, iii. 142). For "Quarrel between Byron and Southey," see Introduction to The Vision of Judgment, Poetical Works, 1901, iv. 475-480; and Letters, 1901, vi. 377-399 (Appendix I.).]

[4] [The reference must be to the detailed enumeration of "the powers requisite for the production of poetry," and the subsequent antithesis of Imagination and Fancy contained in the Preface to the collected Poems of William Wordsworth, published in 1815. In the Preface to the Excursion (1814) it is expressly stated that "it is not the author's intention formally to announce a system."]

[5] {5}Wordsworth's place may be in the Customs—it is, I think, in that or the Excise—besides another at Lord Lonsdale's table, where this poetical charlatan and political parasite licks up the crumbs with a hardened alacrity; the converted Jacobin having long subsided into the clownish sycophant [despised retainer,—MS. erased] of the worst prejudices of the aristocracy.

[Wordsworth obtained his appointment as Distributor of Stamps for the county of Westmoreland in March, 1813, through Lord Lonsdale's "patronage" (see his letter, March 6, 1813). The Excursion was dedicated to Lord Lonsdale in a sonnet dated July 29, 1814—

"Oft through thy fair domains, illustrious Peer,

In youth I roamed ...

Now, by thy care befriended, I appear

Before thee, Lonsdale, and this Work present."]

[6] {6}[Paradise Lost, vii. 25, 26.]

[7] {7}"Pale, but not cadaverous:"—Milton's two elder daughters are said to have robbed him of his books, besides cheating and plaguing him in the economy of his house, etc., etc. His feelings on such an outrage, both as a parent and a scholar, must have been singularly painful. Hayley compares him to Lear. See part third, Life of Milton, by W. Hayley (or Hailey, as spelt in the edition before me).

[The Life of Milton, by William Hailey (sic), Esq., Basil, 1799, p. 186.]

[8] Or—

"Would he subside into a hackney Laureate—

A scribbling, self-sold, soul-hired, scorned Iscariot?"

I doubt if "Laureate" and "Iscariot" be good rhymes, but must say, as Ben Jonson did to Sylvester, who challenged him to rhyme with—

"I, John Sylvester,

Lay with your sister."

Jonson answered—"I, Ben Jonson, lay with your wife." Sylvester answered,—"That is not rhyme."—"No," said Ben Jonson; "but it is true."

[For Robert Stewart, Viscount Castlereagh, see The Age of Bronze, line 538, Poetical Works, 1901, v. 568, note 2; and Letters, 1900, iv. 108, note 1.]

[9] {8}For the character of Eutropius, the eunuch and minister at the court of Arcadius, see Gibbon, [Decline and Fall, 1825, ii. 307, 308].

[10] ["Mr. John Murray,—As publisher to the Admiralty and of various Government works, if the five stanzas concerning Castlereagh should risk your ears or the Navy List, you may omit them in the publication—in that case the two last lines of stanza 10 [i.e. 11] must end with the couplet (lines 7, 8) inscribed in the margin. The stanzas on Castlerighi (as the Italians call him) are 11, 12, 13, 14, 15."—MS. M.]

[11] [Commenting on a "pathetic sentiment" of Leoni, the author of the Italian translation of Childe Harold ("Sciagurata condizione di questa mia patria!"), Byron affirms that the Italians execrated Castlereagh "as the cause, by the conduct of the English at Genoa." "Surely," he exclaims, "that man will not die in his bed: there is no spot of the earth where his name is not a hissing and a curse. Imagine what must be the man's talent for Odium, who has contrived to spread his infamy like a pestilence from Ireland to Italy, and to make his name an execration in all languages."—Letter to Murray, May 8, 1820, Letters, 1901, v. 22, note 1.]

[12] {9}[Charles James Fox and the Whig Club of his time adopted a uniform of blue and buff. Hence the livery of the Edinburgh Review.]

[13] I allude not to our friend Landor's hero, the traitor Count Julian, but to Gibbon's hero, vulgarly yclept "The Apostate."

Preface to Cantos VI, VII, and VIII

The details of the siege of Ismail in two of the following cantos (i.e. the seventh and eighth) are taken from a French Work, entitled Histoire de la Nouvelle Russie.[319] Some of the incidents attributed to Don Juan really occurred, particularly the circumstance of his saving the infant, which was the actual case of the late Duc de Richelieu, then a young volunteer in the Russian service, and afterward the founder and benefactor of Odessa, where his name and memory can never cease to be regarded with reverence.

In the course of these cantos, a stanza or two will be found relative to the late Marquis of Londonderry,[320] but written some time before his decease. Had that person's oligarchy died with him, they would have been suppressed; as it is, I am aware of nothing in the manner of his death or of his life to prevent the free expression of the opinions of all whom his whole existence was consumed in endeavouring to enslave. That he was an amiable man in private life, may or may not be true: but with this the public have nothing to do; and as to lamenting his death, it will be time enough when Ireland has ceased to mourn for his birth. As a minister, I, for one of millions, looked upon him as the most despotic in intention, and the weakest in intellect, that ever tyrannised over a country. It is the first time indeed since the Normans that England has been insulted by a minister (at least) who could not speak English, and that Parliament permitted itself to be dictated to in the language of Mrs. Malaprop.

Of the manner of his death little need be said, except that if a poor radical, such as Waddington or Watson,[321] had cut his throat, he would have been buried in a cross-road, with the usual appurtenances of the stake and mallet. But the minister was an elegant lunatic—a sentimental suicide—he merely cut the "carotid artery," (blessings on their learning!) and lo! the pageant, and the Abbey! and "the syllables of dolour yelled forth"[322] by the newspapers—and the harangue of the Coroner in a eulogy over the bleeding body of the deceased—(an Anthony worthy of such a Cæsar)—and the nauseous and atrocious cant of a degraded crew of conspirators against all that is sincere and honourable. In his death he was necessarily one of two things by the law[323]—a felon or a madman—and in either case no great subject for panegyric.[324] In his life he was—what all the world knows, and half of it will feel for years to come, unless his death prove a "moral lesson" to the surviving Sejani[325] of Europe. It may at least serve as some consolation to the nations, that their oppressors are not happy, and in some instances judge so justly of their own actions as to anticipate the sentence of mankind. Let us hear no more of this man; and let Ireland remove the ashes of her Grattan from the sanctuary of Westminster. Shall the patriot of humanity repose by the Werther of politics!!!

With regard to the objections which have been made on another score to the already published cantos of this poem, I shall content myself with two quotations from Voltaire:—"La pudeur s'est enfuite des coeurs, et s'est refugiée sur les lèvres." ... "Plus les moeurs sont dépravés, plus les expressions deviennent mesurées; on croit regagner en langage ce qu'on a perdu en vertu."

This is the real fact, as applicable to the degraded and hypocritical mass which leavens the present English generation, and is the only answer they deserve. The hackneyed and lavished title of Blasphemer—which, with Radical, Liberal, Jacobin, Reformer, etc., are the changes which the hirelings are daily ringing in the ears of those who will listen—should be welcome to all who recollect on whom it was originally bestowed. Socrates and Jesus Christ were put to death publicly as blasphemers, and so have been and may be many who dare to oppose the most notorious abuses of the name of God and the mind of man. But persecution is not refutation, nor even triumph: the "wretched infidel," as he is called, is probably happier in his prison than the proudest of his assailants. With his opinions I have nothing to do—they may be right or wrong—but he has suffered for them, and that very suffering for conscience' sake will make more proselytes to deism than the example of heterodox[326] Prelates to Christianity, suicide statesmen to oppression, or overpensioned homicides to the impious alliance which insults the world with the name of "Holy!"[327] I have no wish to trample on the dishonoured or the dead; but it would be well if the adherents to the classes from whence those persons sprung should abate a little of the cant which is the crying sin of this double-dealing and false-speaking time of selfish spoilers, and——but enough for the present.

FOOTNOTES:

[319] {264}[The Marquis Gabriel de Castelnau, author of an Essai sur L'Histoire ancienne et moderne de la Nouvelle Russie (Sec. Ed. 3 tom. 1827), was, at one time, resident at Odessa, where he met and made the acquaintance of Armand Emanuel, Duc de Richelieu, who took part in the siege of Ismail. M. Léon de Crousaz-Crétet describes him as "ancien surintendant des théâtres sous l'Empereur Paul."—Le Duc de Richelieu, 1897, p. 83.]

[320] [For Robert Stewart, Viscount Castlereagh, second Marquis of Londonderry (1769-1822), see Letters, 1900, iv. 108, 109, note 1.]

[321] {266}[Samuel Ferrand Waddington, born 1759, hop-grower and radical politician, first came into notice as the chairman of public meetings in favour of making peace with the French in 1793. He was the author, inter alia, of A Key to a Delicate Investigation, 1812, and An Address to the People of the United Kingdom, 1812. He was alive in 1822. James Watson (1766-1838), a radical agitator of the following of Thomas Spence, was engaged, in the autumn of 1816, in an abortive conspiracy to blow up cavalry barracks, barricade the streets, and seize the Bank and the Tower. He was tried for high treason before Lord Ellenborough, and acquitted.]

[322] [Macbeth, act iv. sc. 3, lines 7, 8.]

[323] I say by the law of the land—the laws of humanity judge more gently; but as the legitimates have always the law in their mouths, let them here make the most of it.

[324] [Mr. Joseph Carttar, of Deptford, coroner for the County of Kent, addressed the jury at some length. The following sentences are taken from the report of the inquest, contained in The Annual Biography and Obituary for the year 1823, vol. vii. p. 57: "As a public man, it is impossible for me to weigh his character in any scales that I can hold. In private life I believe the world will admit that a more amiable man could not be found.... If it should unfortunately appear that there is not sufficient evidence to prove what is generally considered the indication of a disordered mind, I trust that the jury will pay some attention to my humble opinion, which is, that no man can be in his proper senses at the moment he commits so rash an act as self-murder. ...The Bible declares that a man clings to nothing so strongly as his own life, I therefore view it as an axiom, and an abstract principle, that a man must necessarily be out of his mind at the moment of destroying himself." Byron, probably, read the report of the inquest in Cobbett's Weekly Register (August 17, 1822, vol. 43, pp. 389-425). The "eulogy" was in perfectly good taste, but there can be little doubt that if "Waddington or Watson" had cut their "carotid arteries," the verdict would have been different.]

[325] From this number must be excepted Canning. Canning is a genius, almost a universal one, an orator, a wit, a poet, a statesman; and no man of talent can long pursue the path of his late predecessor, Lord C. If ever man saved his country, Canning can, but will he? I for one, hope so.

[The phrase, "great moral lesson," was employed by the Duke of Wellington, à propos of the restoration of pictures and statues to their "rightful owners," in a despatch addressed to Castlereagh, under date, Paris, September 19, 1815 (The Dispatches, etc. (ed. by Colonel Gurwood), 1847, viii. 270). The words, "moral lesson," as applied to the French generally, are to be found in Scott's Field of Waterloo (conclusion, stanza vi. line 3), which was written about the same time as the despatch. Byron quotes them in his "Ode from the French," stanza iv. line 8 (see Poetical Works, 1900, iii. 434, note 1). There is a satirical allusion to the Duke's "assumption of the didactic" about teaching a "great moral lesson" in the Preface to the first number of the Liberal (1822, p. xi.).]

[326] {267}When Lord Sandwich said "he did not know the difference between orthodoxy and heterodoxy," Warburton, the bishop, replied, "Orthodoxy, my lord, is my doxy, and heterodoxy is another man's doxy." A prelate of the present day has discovered, it seems, a third kind of doxy, which has not greatly exalted in the eyes of the elect that which Bentham calls "Church-of-Englandism."

[For the "prelate," see Letters, 1902, vi. 101, note 2.]

[327] [For the Duke of Wellington and the Holy Alliance, see the Introduction to The Age of Bronze, Poetical Works, 1901, v. 538, 561.]

Canto III[169]

I.

Hail, Muse! et cetera.—We left Juan sleeping,

Pillowed upon a fair and happy breast,

And watched by eyes that never yet knew weeping,

And loved by a young heart, too deeply blest

To feel the poison through her spirit creeping,

Or know who rested there, a foe to rest,

Had soiled the current of her sinless years,

And turned her pure heart's purest blood to tears!

II.

Oh, Love! what is it in this world of ours

Which makes it fatal to be loved? Ah why

With cypress branches hast thou wreathed thy bowers,

And made thy best interpreter a sigh?

As those who dote on odours pluck the flowers,

And place them on their breast—but place to die—

Thus the frail beings we would fondly cherish

Are laid within our bosoms but to perish.

III.

In her first passion Woman loves her lover,

In all the others all she loves is Love,

Which grows a habit she can ne'er get over,

And fits her loosely—like an easy glove,[CH]

As you may find, whene'er you like to prove her:

One man alone at first her heart can move;

She then prefers him in the plural number,

Not finding that the additions much encumber.

IV.

I know not if the fault be men's or theirs;

But one thing's pretty sure; a woman planted

(Unless at once she plunge for life in prayers)—

After a decent time must be gallanted;

Although, no doubt, her first of love affairs

Is that to which her heart is wholly granted;

Yet there are some, they say, who have had none,

But those who have ne'er end with only one.[170]

V.

'T is melancholy, and a fearful sign

Of human frailty, folly, also crime,

That Love and Marriage rarely can combine,

Although they both are born in the same clime;

Marriage from Love, like vinegar from wine—

A sad, sour, sober beverage—by Time

Is sharpened from its high celestial flavour

Down to a very homely household savour.

VI.

There's something of antipathy, as 't were,

Between their present and their future state;

A kind of flattery that's hardly fair

Is used until the truth arrives too late—

Yet what can people do, except despair?

The same things change their names at such a rate;

For instance—Passion in a lover's glorious,

But in a husband is pronounced uxorious.

VII.

Men grow ashamed of being so very fond;

They sometimes also get a little tired

(But that, of course, is rare), and then despond:

The same things cannot always be admired,

Yet 't is "so nominated in the bond,"[171]

That both are tied till one shall have expired.

Sad thought! to lose the spouse that was adorning

Our days, and put one's servants into mourning.

VIII.

There's doubtless something in domestic doings

Which forms, in fact, true Love's antithesis;

Romances paint at full length people's wooings,

But only give a bust of marriages;

For no one cares for matrimonial cooings,

There's nothing wrong in a connubial kiss:

Think you, if Laura had been Petrarch's wife,

He would have written sonnets all his life?[CI]

IX.

All tragedies are finished by a death,

All comedies are ended by a marriage;

The future states of both are left to faith,

For authors fear description might disparage

The worlds to come of both, or fall beneath,

And then both worlds would punish their miscarriage;

So leaving each their priest and prayer-book ready,

They say no more of Death or of the Lady.[172]

X.

The only two that in my recollection,

Have sung of Heaven and Hell, or marriage, are

Dante[173] and Milton,[174] and of both the affection

Was hapless in their nuptials, for some bar

Of fault or temper ruined the connection

(Such things, in fact, it don't ask much to mar);

But Dante's Beatrice and Milton's Eve

Were not drawn from their spouses, you conceive.

XI.

Some persons say that Dante meant Theology

By Beatrice, and not a mistress—I,

Although my opinion may require apology,

Deem this a commentator's phantasy,

Unless indeed it was from his own knowledge he

Decided thus, and showed good reason why;

I think that Dante's more abstruse ecstatics

Meant to personify the Mathematics.[175]

XII.

Haidée and Juan were not married, but

The fault was theirs, not mine: it is not fair,

Chaste reader, then, in any way to put

The blame on me, unless you wish they were;

Then if you'd have them wedded, please to shut

The book which treats of this erroneous pair,

Before the consequences grow too awful;

'T is dangerous to read of loves unlawful.

XIII.

Yet they were happy,—happy in the illicit

Indulgence of their innocent desires;

But more imprudent grown with every visit,

Haidée forgot the island was her Sire's;

When we have what we like 't is hard to miss it,

At least in the beginning, ere one tires;

Thus she came often, not a moment losing,

Whilst her piratical papa was cruising.

XIV.

Let not his mode of raising cash seem strange,

Although he fleeced the flags of every nation,

For into a Prime Minister but change

His title, and 't is nothing but taxation;

But he, more modest, took an humbler range

Of Life, and in an honester vocation

Pursued o'er the high seas his watery journey,[CJ]

And merely practised as a sea-attorney.

XV.

The good old gentleman had been detained

By winds and waves, and some important captures;

And, in the hope of more, at sea remained,

Although a squall or two had damped his raptures,

By swamping one of the prizes; he had chained

His prisoners, dividing them like chapters

In numbered lots; they all had cuffs and collars,

And averaged each from ten to a hundred dollars.

XVI.

Some he disposed of off Cape Matapan,

Among his friends the Mainots; some he sold

To his Tunis correspondents, save one man

Tossed overboard unsaleable (being old);

The rest—save here and there some richer one,

Reserved for future ransom—in the hold,

Were linked alike, as, for the common people, he

Had a large order from the Dey of Tripoli.

XVII.

The merchandise was served in the same way,

Pieced out for different marts in the Levant,

Except some certain portions of the prey,

Light classic articles of female want,

French stuffs, lace, tweezers, toothpicks, teapot, tray,[CK]

Guitars and castanets from Alicant,

All which selected from the spoil he gathers,

Robbed for his daughter by the best of fathers.

XVIII.

A monkey, a Dutch mastiff, a mackaw,[176]

Two parrots, with a Persian cat and kittens,

He chose from several animals he saw—

A terrier, too, which once had been a Briton's,

Who dying on the coast of Ithaca,

The peasants gave the poor dumb thing a pittance:

These to secure in this strong blowing weather,

He caged in one huge hamper altogether.

XIX.

Then, having settled his marine affairs,

Despatching single cruisers here and there,

His vessel having need of some repairs,

He shaped his course to where his daughter fair

Continued still her hospitable cares;

But that part of the coast being shoal and bare,

And rough with reefs which ran out many a mile,

His port lay on the other side o' the isle.

XX.

And there he went ashore without delay,

Having no custom-house nor quarantine

To ask him awkward questions on the way,

About the time and place where he had been:

He left his ship to be hove down next day,

With orders to the people to careen;

So that all hands were busy beyond measure,

In getting out goods, ballast, guns, and treasure.

XXI.

Arriving at the summit of a hill

Which overlooked the white walls of his home,

He stopped.—What singular emotions fill

Their bosoms who have been induced to roam!

With fluttering doubts if all be well or ill—

With love for many, and with fears for some;

All feelings which o'erleap the years long lost,

And bring our hearts back to their starting-post.

XXII.

The approach of home to husbands and to sires,

After long travelling by land or water,

Most naturally some small doubt inspires—

A female family's a serious matter,

(None trusts the sex more, or so much admires—

But they hate flattery, so I never flatter);

Wives in their husbands' absences grow subtler,

And daughters sometimes run off with the butler.

XXIII.

An honest gentleman at his return

May not have the good fortune of Ulysses;

Not all lone matrons for their husbands mourn,

Or show the same dislike to suitors' kisses;

The odds are that he finds a handsome urn

To his memory—and two or three young misses

Born to some friend, who holds his wife and riches—

And that his Argus[177]—bites him by the breeches.

XXIV.

If single, probably his plighted Fair

Has in his absence wedded some rich miser;

But all the better, for the happy pair

May quarrel, and, the lady growing wiser,

He may resume his amatory care

As cavalier servente, or despise her;

And that his sorrow may not be a dumb one,

Writes odes on the Inconstancy of Woman.

XXV.

And oh! ye gentlemen who have already

Some chaste liaison of the kind—I mean

An honest friendship with a married lady—

The only thing of this sort ever seen

To last—of all connections the most steady,

And the true Hymen, (the first's but a screen)—

Yet, for all that, keep not too long away—

I've known the absent wronged four times a day.[CL]

XXVI.

Lambro, our sea-solicitor, who had

Much less experience of dry land than Ocean,

On seeing his own chimney-smoke, felt glad;

But not knowing metaphysics, had no notion

Of the true reason of his not being sad,

Or that of any other strong emotion;

He loved his child, and would have wept the loss of her,

But knew the cause no more than a philosopher.

XXVII.

He saw his white walls shining in the sun,

His garden trees all shadowy and green;

He heard his rivulet's light bubbling run,

The distant dog-bark; and perceived between

The umbrage of the wood, so cool and dun,

The moving figures, and the sparkling sheen

Of arms (in the East all arm)—and various dyes

Of coloured garbs, as bright as butterflies.

XXVIII.

And as the spot where they appear he nears,

Surprised at these unwonted signs of idling,

He hears—alas! no music of the spheres,

But an unhallowed, earthly sound of fiddling!

A melody which made him doubt his ears,

The cause being past his guessing or unriddling;

A pipe, too, and a drum, and shortly after—

A most unoriental roar of laughter.

XXIX.

And still more nearly to the place advancing,

Descending rather quickly the declivity,

Through the waved branches o'er the greensward glancing,

'Midst other indications of festivity,

Seeing a troop of his domestics dancing

Like Dervises, who turn as on a pivot, he

Perceived it was the Pyrrhic dance[178] so martial,

To which the Levantines are very partial.

XXX.

And further on a troop of Grecian girls,[179]

The first and tallest her white kerchief waving,

Were strung together like a row of pearls,

Linked hand in hand, and dancing; each too having

Down her white neck long floating auburn curls—

(The least of which would set ten poets raving);[CM]

Their leader sang—and bounded to her song

With choral step and voice the virgin throng.

XXXI.

And here, assembled cross-legged round their trays,

Small social parties just begun to dine;

Pilaus and meats of all sorts met the gaze,

And flasks of Samian and of Chian wine,

And sherbet cooling in the porous vase;

Above them their dessert grew on its vine;—

The orange and pomegranate nodding o'er,

Dropped in their laps, scarce plucked, their mellow store.

XXXII.

A band of children, round a snow-white ram,[180]

There wreathe his venerable horns with flowers;

While peaceful as if still an unweaned lamb,

The patriarch of the flock all gently cowers

His sober head, majestically tame,

Or eats from out the palm, or playful lowers

His brow, as if in act to butt, and then

Yielding to their small hands, draws back again.

XXXIII.

Their classical profiles, and glittering dresses,

Their large black eyes, and soft seraphic cheeks,

Crimson as cleft pomegranates, their long tresses,

The gesture which enchants, the eye that speaks,

The innocence which happy childhood blesses,

Made quite a picture of these little Greeks;

So that the philosophical beholder

Sighed for their sakes—that they should e'er grow older.

XXXIV.

Afar, a dwarf buffoon stood telling tales

To a sedate grey circle of old smokers,

Of secret treasures found in hidden vales,

Of wonderful replies from Arab jokers,

Of charms to make good gold and cure bad ails,

Of rocks bewitched that open to the knockers,

Of magic ladies who, by one sole act,

Transformed their lords to beasts (but that's a fact).

XXXV.

Here was no lack of innocent diversion

For the imagination or the senses,

Song, dance, wine, music, stories from the Persian,

All pretty pastimes in which no offence is;

But Lambro saw all these things with aversion,

Perceiving in his absence such expenses,

Dreading that climax of all human ills,

The inflammation of his weekly bills.

XXXVI.

Ah! what is man? what perils still environ[181]

The happiest mortals even after dinner!

A day of gold from out an age of iron

Is all that Life allows the luckiest sinner;

Pleasure (whene'er she sings, at least) 's a Siren,

That lures, to flay alive, the young beginner;

Lambro's reception at his people's banquet

Was such as fire accords to a wet blanket.

XXXVII.

He—being a man who seldom used a word

Too much, and wishing gladly to surprise

(In general he surprised men with the sword)

His daughter—had not sent before to advise

Of his arrival, so that no one stirred;

And long he paused to re-assure his eyes,

In fact much more astonished than delighted,

To find so much good company invited.

XXXVIII.

He did not know (alas! how men will lie)

That a report (especially the Greeks)

Avouched his death (such people never die),

And put his house in mourning several weeks,—

But now their eyes and also lips were dry;

The bloom, too, had returned to Haidée's cheeks:

Her tears, too, being returned into their fount,

She now kept house upon her own account.

XXXIX.

Hence all this rice, meat, dancing, wine, and fiddling,

Which turned the isle into a place of pleasure;

The servants all were getting drunk or idling,

A life which made them happy beyond measure.

Her father's hospitality seemed middling,

Compared with what Haidée did with his treasure;

'T was wonderful how things went on improving,

While she had not one hour to spare from loving.[CN]

XL.

Perhaps you think, in stumbling on this feast,

He flew into a passion, and in fact

There was no mighty reason to be pleased;

Perhaps you prophesy some sudden act,

The whip, the rack, or dungeon at the least,

To teach his people to be more exact,

And that, proceeding at a very high rate,

He showed the royal penchants of a pirate.

XLI.

You're wrong.—He was the mildest mannered man

That ever scuttled ship or cut a throat;

With such true breeding of a gentleman,

You never could divine his real thought;

No courtier could, and scarcely woman can

Gird more deceit within a petticoat;

Pity he loved adventurous life's variety,

He was so great a loss to good society.

XLII.

Advancing to the nearest dinner tray,

Tapping the shoulder of the nighest guest,

With a peculiar smile, which, by the way,

Boded no good, whatever it expressed,

He asked the meaning of this holiday;

The vinous Greek to whom he had addressed

His question, much too merry to divine

The questioner, filled up a glass of wine,

XLIII.

And without turning his facetious head,

Over his shoulder, with a Bacchant air,

Presented the o'erflowing cup, and said,

"Talking's dry work, I have no time to spare."

A second hiccuped, "Our old Master's dead,

You'd better ask our Mistress who's his heir."

"Our Mistress!" quoth a third: "Our Mistress!—pooh!—

You mean our Master—not the old, but new."

XLIV.

These rascals, being new comers, knew not whom

They thus addressed—and Lambro's visage fell—

And o'er his eye a momentary gloom

Passed, but he strove quite courteously to quell

The expression, and endeavouring to resume

His smile, requested one of them to tell

The name and quality of his new patron,

Who seemed to have turned Haidée into a matron.

XLV.

"I know not," quoth the fellow, "who or what

He is, nor whence he came—and little care;

But this I know, that this roast capon's fat,

And that good wine ne'er washed down better fare;

And if you are not satisfied with that,

Direct your questions to my neighbour there;

He'll answer all for better or for worse,

For none likes more to hear himself converse."[182]

XLVI.

I said that Lambro was a man of patience,

And certainly he showed the best of breeding,

Which scarce even France, the Paragon of nations,

E'er saw her most polite of sons exceeding;

He bore these sneers against his near relations,

His own anxiety, his heart, too, bleeding,

The insults, too, of every servile glutton,

Who all the time was eating up his mutton.

XLVII.

Now in a person used to much command—

To bid men come, and go, and come again—

To see his orders done, too, out of hand—

Whether the word was death, or but the chain—

It may seem strange to find his manners bland;

Yet such things are, which I cannot explain,

Though, doubtless, he who can command himself

Is good to govern—almost as a Guelf.

XLVIII.

Not that he was not sometimes rash or so,

But never in his real and serious mood;

Then calm, concentrated, and still, and slow,

He lay coiled like the Boa in the wood;

With him it never was a word and blow,

His angry word once o'er, he shed no blood,

But in his silence there was much to rue,

And his one blow left little work for two.

XLIX.

He asked no further questions, and proceeded

On to the house, but by a private way,

So that the few who met him hardly heeded,

So little they expected him that day;

If love paternal in his bosom pleaded

For Haidée's sake, is more than I can say,

But certainly to one deemed dead returning,

This revel seemed a curious mode of mourning.

L.

If all the dead could now return to life,

(Which God forbid!) or some, or a great many,

For instance, if a husband or his wife[CO]

(Nuptial examples are as good as any),

No doubt whate'er might be their former strife,

The present weather would be much more rainy—

Tears shed into the grave of the connection

Would share most probably its resurrection.

LI.

He entered in the house no more his home,

A thing to human feelings the most trying,

And harder for the heart to overcome,

Perhaps, than even the mental pangs of dying;

To find our hearthstone turned into a tomb,

And round its once warm precincts palely lying

The ashes of our hopes, is a deep grief,

Beyond a single gentleman's belief.

LII.

He entered in the house—his home no more,

For without hearts there is no home;—and felt

The solitude of passing his own door

Without a welcome: there he long had dwelt,

There his few peaceful days Time had swept o'er,

There his worn bosom and keen eye would melt

Over the innocence of that sweet child,

His only shrine of feelings undefiled.

LIII.

He was a man of a strange temperament,

Of mild demeanour though of savage mood,

Moderate in all his habits, and content

With temperance in pleasure, as in food,

Quick to perceive, and strong to bear, and meant

For something better, if not wholly good;

His Country's wrongs and his despair to save her

Had stung him from a slave to an enslaver.

LIV.

The love of power, and rapid gain of gold,

The hardness by long habitude produced,

The dangerous life in which he had grown old,

The mercy he had granted oft abused,

The sights he was accustomed to behold,

The wild seas, and wild men with whom he cruised,

Had cost his enemies a long repentance,

And made him a good friend, but bad acquaintance.

LV.

But something of the spirit of old Greece

Flashed o'er his soul a few heroic rays,

Such as lit onward to the Golden Fleece

His predecessors in the Colchian days;

'T is true he had no ardent love for peace—

Alas! his country showed no path to praise:

Hate to the world and war with every nation

He waged, in vengeance of her degradation.

LVI.

Still o'er his mind the influence of the clime

Shed its Ionian elegance, which showed

Its power unconsciously full many a time,—

A taste seen in the choice of his abode,

A love of music and of scenes sublime,

A pleasure in the gentle stream that flowed

Past him in crystal, and a joy in flowers,

Bedewed his spirit in his calmer hours.

LVII.

But whatsoe'er he had of love reposed

On that belovéd daughter; she had been

The only thing which kept his heart unclosed

Amidst the savage deeds he had done and seen,

A lonely pure affection unopposed:

There wanted but the loss of this to wean

His feelings from all milk of human kindness,

And turn him like the Cyclops mad with blindness.[CP]

LVIII.

The cubless tigress in her jungle raging

Is dreadful to the shepherd and the flock;

The Ocean when its yeasty war is waging

Is awful to the vessel near the rock;

But violent things will sooner bear assuaging,

Their fury being spent by its own shock,

Than the stern, single, deep, and wordless ire[CQ]

Of a strong human heart, and in a Sire.

LIX.

It is a hard although a common case

To find our children running restive—they

In whom our brightest days we would retrace,

Our little selves re-formed in finer clay,

Just as old age is creeping on apace,

And clouds come o'er the sunset of our day,

They kindly leave us, though not quite alone,

But in good company—the gout or stone.

LX.

Yet a fine family is a fine thing

(Provided they don't come in after dinner);

'T is beautiful to see a matron bring

Her children up (if nursing them don't thin her);

Like cherubs round an altar-piece they cling

To the fire-side (a sight to touch a sinner).

A lady with her daughters or her nieces

Shine like a guinea and seven-shilling pieces.

LXI.

Old Lambro passed unseen a private gate,

And stood within his hall at eventide;

Meantime the lady and her lover sate

At wassail in their beauty and their pride:

An ivory inlaid table spread with state

Before them, and fair slaves on every side;[183]

Gems, gold, and silver, formed the service mostly,

Mother of pearl and coral the less costly.

LXII.

The dinner made about a hundred dishes;

Lamb and pistachio nuts—in short, all meats,

And saffron soups, and sweetbreads; and the fishes

Were of the finest that e'er flounced in nets,

Dressed to a Sybarite's most pampered wishes;

The beverage was various sherbets

Of raisin, orange, and pomegranate juice,

Squeezed through the rind, which makes it best for use.

LXIII.

These were ranged round, each in its crystal ewer,

And fruits, and date-bread loaves closed the repast,

And Mocha's berry, from Arabia pure,

In small fine China cups, came in at last;

Gold cups of filigree, made to secure

The hand from burning, underneath them placed;

Cloves, cinnamon, and saffron too were boiled

Up with the coffee, which (I think) they spoiled.

LXIV.

The hangings of the room were tapestry, made

Of velvet panels, each of different hue,

And thick with damask flowers of silk inlaid;

And round them ran a yellow border too;

The upper border, richly wrought, displayed,

Embroidered delicately o'er with blue,

Soft Persian sentences, in lilac letters,

From poets, or the moralists their betters.

LXV.

These Oriental writings on the wall,

Quite common in those countries, are a kind

Of monitors adapted to recall,

Like skulls at Memphian banquets, to the mind,

The words which shook Belshazzar in his hall,

And took his kingdom from him: You will find,

Though sages may pour out their wisdom's treasure,

There is no sterner moralist than Pleasure.

LXVI.

A Beauty at the season's close grown hectic,

A Genius who has drunk himself to death,

A Rake turned methodistic, or Eclectic—[184]

(For that's the name they like to pray beneath)—[CR]

But most, an Alderman struck apoplectic,

Are things that really take away the breath,—

And show that late hours, wine, and love are able

To do not much less damage than the table.

LXVII.

Haidée and Juan carpeted their feet

On crimson satin, bordered with pale blue;

Their sofa occupied three parts complete

Of the apartment—and appeared quite new;

The velvet cushions (for a throne more meet)

Were scarlet, from whose glowing centre grew

A sun embossed in gold, whose rays of tissue,

Meridian-like, were seen all light to issue.[CS]

LXVIII.

Crystal and marble, plate and porcelain,

Had done their work of splendour; Indian mats

And Persian carpets, which the heart bled to stain,

Over the floors were spread; gazelles and cats,

And dwarfs and blacks, and such like things, that gain

Their bread as ministers and favourites (that's

To say, by degradation) mingled there

As plentiful as in a court, or fair.

LXIX.

There was no want of lofty mirrors, and

The tables, most of ebony inlaid

With mother of pearl or ivory, stood at hand,

Or were of tortoise-shell or rare woods made,

Fretted with gold or silver:—by command

The greater part of these were ready spread

With viands and sherbets in ice—and wine—

Kept for all comers at all hours to dine.

LXX.

Of all the dresses I select Haidée's:

She wore two jelicks—one was of pale yellow;

Of azure, pink, and white was her chemise—

'Neath which her breast heaved like a little billow:

With buttons formed of pearls as large as peas,

All gold and crimson shone her jelick's fellow,

And the striped white gauze baracan that bound her,

Like fleecy clouds about the moon, flowed round her.

LXXI.

One large gold bracelet clasped each lovely arm,

Lockless—so pliable from the pure gold

That the hand stretched and shut it without harm,

The limb which it adorned its only mould;

So beautiful—its very shape would charm,

And clinging, as if loath to lose its hold,

The purest ore enclosed the whitest skin

That e'er by precious metal was held in.[185]

LXXII.

Around, as Princess of her father's land,

A like gold bar above her instep rolled[186]

Announced her rank; twelve rings were on her hand;

Her hair was starred with gems; her veil's fine fold

Below her breast was fastened with a band

Of lavish pearls, whose worth could scarce be told;

Her orange silk full Turkish trousers furled

About the prettiest ankle in the world.

LXXIII.

Her hair's long auburn waves down to her heel

Flowed like an Alpine torrent which the sun

Dyes with his morning light,—and would conceal

Her person[187] if allowed at large to run,

And still they seemed resentfully to feel

The silken fillet's curb, and sought to shun

Their bonds whene'er some Zephyr caught began

To offer his young pinion as her fan.

LXXIV.

Round her she made an atmosphere of life,[188]

The very air seemed lighter from her eyes,

They were so soft and beautiful, and rife

With all we can imagine of the skies,

And pure as Psyche ere she grew a wife—

Too pure even for the purest human ties;

Her overpowering presence made you feel

It would not be idolatry to kneel.[189]

LXXV.

Her eyelashes, though dark as night, were tinged

(It is the country's custom, but in vain),

For those large black eyes were so blackly fringed,

The glossy rebels mocked the jetty stain,

And in their native beauty stood avenged:

Her nails were touched with henna; but, again,

The power of Art was turned to nothing, for

They could not look more rosy than before.

LXXVI.

The henna should be deeply dyed to make

The skin relieved appear more fairly fair;

She had no need of this, day ne'er will break

On mountain tops more heavenly white than her:

The eye might doubt if it were well awake,

She was so like a vision; I might err,

But Shakespeare also says, 't is very silly

"To gild refinéd gold, or paint the lily."[190]

LXXVII.

Juan had on a shawl of black and gold,

But a white baracan, and so transparent

The sparkling gems beneath you might behold,

Like small stars through the milky way apparent;

His turban, furled in many a graceful fold,

An emerald aigrette, with Haidée's hair in't,

Surmounted as its clasp—a glowing crescent,

Whose rays shone ever trembling, but incessant.

LXXVIII.

And now they were diverted by their suite,

Dwarfs, dancing girls, black eunuchs, and a poet,

Which made their new establishment complete;

The last was of great fame, and liked to show it;

His verses rarely wanted their due feet—

And for his theme—he seldom sung below it,

He being paid to satirise or flatter,

As the Psalm says, "inditing a good matter."

LXXIX.

He praised the present, and abused the past,

Reversing the good custom of old days,

An Eastern anti-jacobin at last

He turned, preferring pudding to no praise—

For some few years his lot had been o'ercast

By his seeming independent in his lays,

But now he sung the Sultan and the Pacha—

With truth like Southey, and with verse[191] like Crashaw.[CT]

LXXX.

He was a man who had seen many changes,

And always changed as true as any needle;

His Polar Star being one which rather ranges,

And not the fixed—he knew the way to wheedle:

So vile he 'scaped the doom which oft avenges;

And being fluent (save indeed when fee'd ill),

He lied with such a fervour of intention—

There was no doubt he earned his laureate pension.

LXXXI.

But he had genius,—when a turncoat has it,

The Vates irritabilis[192] takes care

That without notice few full moons shall pass it;

Even good men like to make the public stare:—

But to my subject—let me see—what was it?—

Oh!—the third canto—and the pretty pair—

Their loves, and feasts, and house, and dress, and mode

Of living in their insular abode.

LXXXII.

Their poet, a sad trimmer, but, no less,[CU]

In company a very pleasant fellow,

Had been the favourite of full many a mess

Of men, and made them speeches when half mellow;[CV]

And though his meaning they could rarely guess,

Yet still they deigned to hiccup or to bellow

The glorious meed of popular applause,

Of which the first ne'er knows the second cause.[CW]

LXXXIII.

But now being lifted into high society,

And having picked up several odds and ends

Of free thoughts in his travels for variety,

He deemed, being in a lone isle, among friends,

That, without any danger of a riot, he

Might for long lying make himself amends;

And, singing as he sung in his warm youth,

Agree to a short armistice with Truth.

LXXXIV.

He had travelled 'mongst the Arabs, Turks, and Franks,

And knew the self-loves of the different nations;

And having lived with people of all ranks,

Had something ready upon most occasions—

Which got him a few presents and some thanks.

He varied with some skill his adulations;

To "do at Rome as Romans do,"[193] a piece

Of conduct was which he observed in Greece.

LXXXV.

Thus, usually, when he was asked to sing,

He gave the different nations something national;

'T was all the same to him—"God save the King,"

Or "Ça ira," according to the fashion all:

His Muse made increment of anything,

From the high lyric down to the low rational;[CX][194]

If Pindar sang horse-races, what should hinder

Himself from being as pliable as Pindar?

LXXXVI.

In France, for instance, he would write a chanson;

In England a six canto quarto tale;

In Spain he'd make a ballad or romance on

The last war—much the same in Portugal;

In Germany, the Pegasus he'd prance on

Would be old Goethe's—(see what says De Staël);[195]

In Italy he'd ape the "Trecentisti;"

In Greece, he'd sing some sort of hymn like this t' ye:[196]

1.

The Isles of Greece, the Isles of Greece!

Where burning Sappho loved and sung,

Where grew the arts of War and Peace,

Where Delos rose, and Phoebus sprung!

Eternal summer gilds them yet,

But all, except their Sun, is set.

2.

The Scian and the Teian muse,

The Hero's harp, the Lover's lute,

Have found the fame your shores refuse:

Their place of birth alone is mute

To sounds which echo further west

Than your Sires' "Islands of the Blest."[197]

3.

The mountains look on Marathon—[CY]

And Marathon looks on the sea;

And musing there an hour alone,

I dreamed that Greece might still be free;

For standing on the Persians' grave,

I could not deem myself a slave.

4.[198]

A King sate on the rocky brow

Which looks o'er sea-born Salamis;

And ships, by thousands, lay below,

And men in nations;—all were his!

He counted them at break of day—

And, when the Sun set, where were they?

5.

And where are they? and where art thou,

My Country? On thy voiceless shore

The heroic lay is tuneless now—

The heroic bosom beats no more![CZ]

And must thy Lyre, so long divine,

Degenerate into hands like mine?

6.

'T is something, in the dearth of Fame,

Though linked among a fettered race,

To feel at least a patriot's shame,

Even as I sing, suffuse my face;

For what is left the poet here?

For Greeks a blush—for Greece a tear.

7.

Must we but weep o'er days more blest?

Must we but blush?—Our fathers bled.

Earth! render back from out thy breast

A remnant of our Spartan dead!

Of the three hundred grant but three,

To make a new Thermopylæ!

8.

What, silent still? and silent all?

Ah! no;—the voices of the dead

Sound like a distant torrent's fall,

And answer, "Let one living head,

But one arise,—we come, we come!"

'T is but the living who are dumb.

9.

In vain—in vain: strike other chords;

Fill high the cup with Samian wine!

Leave battles to the Turkish hordes,

And shed the blood of Scio's vine!

Hark! rising to the ignoble call—

How answers each bold Bacchanal!

10.

You have the Pyrrhic dance as yet,[199]

Where is the Pyrrhic phalanx gone?

Of two such lessons, why forget

The nobler and the manlier one?

You have the letters Cadmus gave—

Think ye he meant them for a slave?

11.

Fill high the bowl with Samian wine!

We will not think of themes like these!

It made Anacreon's song divine:

He served—but served Polycrates—[200]

A Tyrant; but our masters then

Were still, at least, our countrymen.

12.

The Tyrant of the Chersonese

Was Freedom's best and bravest friend;

That tyrant was Miltiades!

Oh! that the present hour would lend

Another despot of the kind!

Such chains as his were sure to bind.

13.

Fill high the bowl with Samian wine!

On Suli's rock, and Parga's shore,

Exists the remnant of a line

Such as the Doric mothers bore;

And there, perhaps, some seed is sown,

The Heracleidan blood might own.[DA]

14.

Trust not for freedom to the Franks—[201]

They have a king who buys and sells;

In native swords, and native ranks,

The only hope of courage dwells;

But Turkish force, and Latin fraud,

Would break your shield, however broad.

15.

Fill high the bowl with Samian wine!

Our virgins dance beneath the shade—

I see their glorious black eyes shine;

But gazing on each glowing maid,

My own the burning tear-drop laves,

To think such breasts must suckle slaves.

16.

Place me on Sunium's marbled steep,[202]

Where nothing, save the waves and I,

May hear our mutual murmurs sweep;

There, swan-like, let me sing and die:

A land of slaves shall ne'er be mine—

Dash down yon cup of Samian wine!

LXXXVII.

Thus sung, or would, or could, or should have sung,

The modern Greek, in tolerable verse;

If not like Orpheus quite, when Greece was young,

Yet in these times he might have done much worse:

His strain displayed some feeling—right or wrong;

And feeling,[203] in a poet, is the source

Of others' feeling; but they are such liars,

And take all colours—like the hands of dyers.

LXXXVIII.

But words are things,[204] and a small drop of ink,

Falling like dew, upon a thought, produces

That which makes thousands, perhaps millions, think;

'T is strange, the shortest letter which man uses

Instead of speech, may form a lasting link

Of ages; to what straits old Time reduces

Frail man, when paper—even a rag like this,

Survives himself, his tomb, and all that's his!

LXXXIX.

And when his bones are dust, his grave a blank,

His station, generation, even his nation,

Become a thing, or nothing, save to rank

In chronological commemoration,

Some dull MS. Oblivion long has sank,

Or graven stone found in a barrack's station

In digging the foundation of a closet,[DB]

May turn his name up, as a rare deposit.

XC.

And Glory long has made the sages smile;

'T is something, nothing, words, illusion, wind—

Depending more upon the historian's style

Than on the name a person leaves behind:

Troy owes to Homer what whist owes to Hoyle:[205]

The present century was growing blind

To the great Marlborough's skill in giving knocks,

Until his late Life by Archdeacon Coxe.[206]

XCI.

Milton's the Prince of poets—so we say;

A little heavy, but no less divine:

An independent being in his day—

Learned, pious, temperate in love and wine;

But, his life falling into Johnson's way,

We're told this great High Priest of all the Nine

Was whipped at college—a harsh sire—odd spouse,

For the first Mrs. Milton left his house.[207]

XCII.

All these are, certes, entertaining facts,

Like Shakespeare's stealing deer, Lord Bacon's bribes;

Like Titus' youth, and Cæsar's earliest acts;[208]

Like Burns (whom Doctor Currie well describes);[209]

Like Cromwell's pranks;[210]—but although Truth exacts

These amiable descriptions from the scribes,

As most essential to their Hero's story,

They do not much contribute to his glory.

XCIII.

All are not moralists, like Southey, when

He prated to the world of "Pantisocracy;"[211]

Or Wordsworth unexcised,[212] unhired, who then

Seasoned his pedlar poems with Democracy;[DC]

Or Coleridge[213] long before his flighty pen

Let to the Morning Post its aristocracy;[DD]

When he and Southey, following the same path,

Espoused two partners (milliners of Bath).[214]

XCIV.

Such names at present cut a convict figure,

The very Botany Bay in moral geography;

Their loyal treason, renegado rigour,

Are good manure for their more bare biography;

Wordsworth's last quarto, by the way, is bigger

Than any since the birthday of typography;

A drowsy, frowzy poem, called the "Excursion,"

Writ in a manner which is my aversion.

XCV.

He there builds up a formidable dyke

Between his own and others' intellect;

But Wordsworth's poem, and his followers, like

Joanna Southcote's Shiloh[215] and her sect,

Are things which in this century don't strike

The public mind,—so few are the elect;

And the new births of both their stale Virginities

Have proved but Dropsies, taken for Divinities.

XCVI.

But let me to my story: I must own,

If I have any fault, it is digression,

Leaving my people to proceed alone,

While I soliloquize beyond expression:

But these are my addresses from the throne,

Which put off business to the ensuing session:

Forgetting each omission is a loss to

The world, not quite so great as Ariosto.

XCVII.

I know that what our neighbours call "longueurs,"

(We've not so good a word, but have the thing,

In that complete perfection which insures

An epic from Bob Southey every spring—)

Form not the true temptation which allures

The reader; but 't would not be hard to bring

Some fine examples of the Epopée,

To prove its grand ingredient is Ennui.[216]

XCVIII.

We learn from Horace, "Homer sometimes sleeps;"[217]

We feel without him,—Wordsworth sometimes wakes,—

To show with what complacency he creeps,

With his dear "Waggoners," around his lakes.[218]

He wishes for "a boat" to sail the deeps—

Of Ocean?—No, of air; and then he makes

Another outcry for "a little boat,"

And drivels seas to set it well afloat.[219]

XCIX.

If he must fain sweep o'er the ethereal plain,

And Pegasus runs restive in his "Waggon,"

Could he not beg the loan of Charles's Wain?

Or pray Medea for a single dragon?[220]

Or if, too classic for his vulgar brain,

He feared his neck to venture such a nag on,

And he must needs mount nearer to the moon,

Could not the blockhead ask for a balloon?

C.

"Pedlars," and "Boats," and "Waggons!" Oh! ye shades

Of Pope and Dryden, are we come to this?

That trash of such sort not alone evades

Contempt, but from the bathos' vast abyss

Floats scumlike uppermost, and these Jack Cades

Of sense and song above your graves may hiss—

The "little boatman" and his Peter Bell

Can sneer at him who drew "Achitophel!"[221]

CI.

T' our tale.—The feast was over, the slaves gone,

The dwarfs and dancing girls had all retired;

The Arab lore and Poet's song were done,

And every sound of revelry expired;

The lady and her lover, left alone,

The rosy flood of Twilight's sky admired;—

Ave Maria! o'er the earth and sea,

That heavenliest hour of Heaven is worthiest thee!

CII.

Ave Maria! blesséd be the hour!

The time, the clime, the spot, where I so oft

Have felt that moment in its fullest power

Sink o'er the earth—so beautiful and soft—

While swung the deep bell in the distant tower,[DE]

Or the faint dying day-hymn stole aloft,

And not a breath crept through the rosy air,

And yet the forest leaves seemed stirred with prayer.

CIII.

Ave Maria! 't is the hour of prayer!

Ave Maria! 't is the hour of Love!

Ave Maria! may our spirits dare

Look up to thine and to thy Son's above!

Ave Maria! oh that face so fair!

Those downcast eyes beneath the Almighty Dove—

What though 't is but a pictured image?—strike—

That painting is no idol,—'t is too like.

CIV.

Some kinder casuists are pleased to say,

In nameless print[DF]—that I have no devotion;

But set those persons down with me to pray,

And you shall see who has the properest notion

Of getting into Heaven the shortest way;

My altars are the mountains and the Ocean,

Earth—air—stars,[222]—all that springs from the great Whole,

Who hath produced, and will receive the Soul.

CV.

Sweet Hour of Twilight!—in the solitude

Of the pine forest, and the silent shore

Which bounds Ravenna's immemorial wood,

Rooted where once the Adrian wave flowed o'er,

To where the last Cæsarean fortress stood,[223]

Evergreen forest! which Boccaccio's lore

And Dryden's lay made haunted ground to me,

How have I loved the twilight hour and thee![224]

CVI.

The shrill cicalas, people of the pine,

Making their summer lives one ceaseless song,

Were the sole echoes, save my steed's and mine,

And Vesper bell's that rose the boughs along;

The spectre huntsman of Onesti's line,

His hell-dogs, and their chase, and the fair throng

Which learned from this example not to fly

From a true lover,—shadowed my mind's eye.[225]

CVII.

Oh, Hesperus! thou bringest all good things—[226]

Home to the weary, to the hungry cheer,

To the young bird the parent's brooding wings,

The welcome stall to the o'erlaboured steer;

Whate'er of peace about our hearthstone clings,

Whate'er our household gods protect of dear,

Are gathered round us by thy look of rest;

Thou bring'st the child, too, to the mother's breast.

CVIII.

Soft Hour! which wakes the wish and melts the heart

Of those who sail the seas, on the first day

When they from their sweet friends are torn apart;

Or fills with love the pilgrim on his way

As the far bell of Vesper makes him start,

Seeming to weep the dying day's decay;[227]

Is this a fancy which our reason scorns?

Ah! surely Nothing dies but Something mourns!

CIX.

When Nero perished by the justest doom

Which ever the Destroyer yet destroyed,

Amidst the roar of liberated Rome,

Of nations freed, and the world overjoyed,

Some hands unseen strewed flowers upon his tomb:[228]

Perhaps the weakness of a heart not void

Of feeling for some kindness done, when Power

Had left the wretch an uncorrupted hour.

CX.

But I'm digressing; what on earth has Nero,

Or any such like sovereign buffoons,[DG]

To do with the transactions of my hero,

More than such madmen's fellow man—the moon's?

Sure my invention must be down at zero,

And I grown one of many "Wooden Spoons"

Of verse, (the name with which we Cantabs please

To dub the last of honours in degrees).

CXI.

I feel this tediousness will never do—

T' is being too epic, and I must cut down

(In copying) this long canto into two;

They'll never find it out, unless I own

The fact, excepting some experienced few;

And then as an improvement 't will be shown:

I'll prove that such the opinion of the critic is

From Aristotle passim.—See ΠΟΙΗΤΙΚΗΣ.[229]

FOOTNOTES:

[169] [November 30, 1819. Copied in 1820 (MS.D.). Moore (Life, 421) says that Byron was at work on the third canto when he stayed with him at Venice, in October, 1819. "One day, before dinner, [he] read me two or three hundred lines of it; beginning with the stanzas "Oh Wellington," etc., which, at the time, formed the opening of the third canto, but were afterwards reserved for the commencement of the ninth." The third canto, as it now stands, was completed by November 8, 1819; see Letters, 1900, iv. 375. The date on the MS. may refer to the first fair copy.]

[CH] {144}And fits her like a stocking or a glove.—[MS. D.]

[170] ["On peut trouver des femmes qui n'ont jamais eu de galanterie, mais il est rare d'en trouver qui n'en aient jamais eu qu'une."—Réflexions ... du Duc de la Rochefoucauld, No. lxxiii.

Byron prefixed the maxim as a motto to his "Ode to a Lady whose Lover was killed by a Ball, which at the same time shivered a Portrait next his Heart."—Poetical Works, 1901, iv. 552.]

[171] {145}[Merchant of Venice, act iv. sc. 1, line 254.]

[CI]

Had Petrarch's passion led to Petrarch's wedding,

How many sonnets had ensued the bedding?—[MS.]

[172] [The Ballad of "Death and the Lady" was printed in a small volume, entitled A Guide to Heaven, 1736, 12mo. It is mentioned in The Vicar of Wakefield (chap. xvii.), Works of Oliver Goldsmith, 1854, i. 369. See Old English Popular Music, by William Chappell, F.S.A., 1893, ii. 170, 171.]

[173] {146}[See The Prophecy of Dante, Canto I. lines 172-174, Poetical Works, 1901, iv. 253, note 1.]

[174] Milton's first wife ran away from him within the first month. If she had not, what would John Milton have done?

[Mary Powell did not "run away," but at the end of the honeymoon obtained her husband's consent to visit her family at Shotover, "upon a promise of returning at Michaelmas." "And in the mean while his studies went on very vigorously; and his chief diversion, after the business of the day, was now and then in an evening to visit the Lady Margaret Lee.... This lady, being a woman of excellent wit and understanding, had a particular honour for our author, and took great delight in his conversation; as likewise did her husband, Captain Hobson." See, too, his sonnet "To the Lady Margaret Ley."—The Life of Milton (by Thomas Newton, D.D.), Paradise Regained, ed. (Baskerville), 1758, pp. xvii., xviii.]

[175] ["Yesterday a very pretty letter from Annabella.... She is a poetess—a mathematician—a metaphysician."—Journal November 30, 1813, Letters, 1898, ii. 357.]

[CJ] {147}

Displayed much more of nerve, perhaps, of wit,

Than any of the parodies of Pitt.—[MS.]

[CK] {148} —— toothpicks, a bidet.—[MS. Alternative reading.]

"Dr. Murray—As you are squeamish you may put 'teapot, tray,' in case the other piece of feminine furniture frightens you.—B."

[176] [For Byron's menagerie, see Werner, act i. sc. 1, line 216, Poetical Works, 1902, v. 348, note 1.]

[177] {149}["But as for canine recollections ... I had one (half a wolf by the she-side) that doted on me at ten years old, and very nearly ate me at twenty. When I thought he was going to enact Argus, he bit away the backside of my breeches, and never would consent to any kind of recognition, in despite of all kinds of bones which I offered him."—Letter to Moore, January 19, 1815, Letters, 1899, iii. 171, 172. Compare, too, Childe Harold, Canto I. Song, stanza ix., Poetical Works, 1899, ii. 30.]

[CL] {150}

Yet for all that don't stay away too long,

A sofa, like a bed, may come by wrong.—[MS.]

I've known the friend betrayed——.—[MS. D.]

[178] {151}[The Pyrrhic war-dance represented "by rapid movements of the body, the way in which missiles and blows from weapons were avoided, and also the mode in which the enemy was attacked" (Dict. of Ant.). Dodwell (Tour through Greece, 1819, ii. 21, 22) observes that in Thessaly and Macedon dances are performed at the present day by men armed with their musket and sword. See, too, Hobhouse's description (Travels in Albania, 1858, i. 166, 167) of the Albanian war-dance at Loutráki.]

[179] ["Their manner of dancing is certainly the same that Diana is sung to have danced on the banks of Eurotas. The great lady still leads the dance, and is followed by a troop of young girls, who imitate her steps, and, if she sings, make up the chorus. The tunes are extremely gay and lively, yet with something in them wonderfully soft. The steps are varied according to the pleasure of her that leads the dance, but always in exact time, and infinitely more agreeable than any of our dances."—Lady M.W. Montagu to Pope, April 1, O.S., 1817, Letters, etc., 1816, p. 138. The "kerchief-waving" dance is the Romaika. See The Waltz, line 125, Poetical Works, 1898, i. 492, note 1. See, too, Voyage Pittoresque ... by the Comte de Choiseul-Gouffier, 1782, vol. i. Planche 33.]

[CM] That would have set Tom Moore, though married, raving.—[MS.]

[180] {152}["Upon the whole, I think the part of Don Juan in which Lambro's return to his home, and Lambro himself are described, is the best, that is, the most individual, thing in all I know of Lord B.'s works. The festal abandonment puts one in mind of Nicholas Poussin's pictures."—Table Talk of S.T. Coleridge, June 7, 1824.]

[181] {153}[Compare Hudibras, Part I. canto iii. lines 1, 2—

"Ay me! what perils do environ

The man that meddles with cold iron!"

Byron's friend, C.S. Matthews, shouted these lines, con intenzione, under the windows of a Cambridge tradesman named Hiron, who had been instrumental in the expulsion from the University of Sir Henry Smyth, a riotous undergraduate. (See letter to Murray, October 19, 1820.)]

[CN] {154}

All had been open, heart, and open house,

Ever since Juan served her for a spouse.—[MS.]

[182] {155}

["Rispose allor Margutte: a dirtel tosto,

Io non credo più al nero ch' all' azzurro;

Ma nel cappone, o lesso, o vuogli arrosto,

E credo alcuna volta anche nel burro;

Nella cervogia, e quando io n' ho nel mosto,

E molto più nell' aspro che il mangurro;

Ma sopra tutto nel buon vino ho fede,

E credo che sia salvo chi gli crede."

Pulci, Morgante Maggiore, Canto XVIII. stanza cxv.]

[CO] {157}For instance, if a first or second wife.—[MS.]

[CP] {159}

And send him forth like Samson strong in blindness.—[MS. D.]

And make him Samson-like—more fierce with blindness.—[MS. M.]

[CQ]

Not so the single, deep, and wordless ire,

Of a strong human heart—.—[MS.]

[183] {160}["Almost all Don Juan is real life, either my own, or from people I knew. By the way, much of the description of the furniture, in Canto Third, is taken from Tully's Tripoli (pray note this), and the rest from my own observation. Remember, I never meant to conceal this at all, and have only not stated it, because Don Juan had no preface, nor name to it."—Letter to Murray, August 23, 1821, Letters, 1901, v. 346.

The first edition of "Tully's Tripoli" is entitled Narrative of a Ten Years' Residence in Tripoli In Africa: From the original correspondence in the possession of the Family of the late Richard Tully, Esq., the British Consul, 1816, 410. The book is in the form of letters (so says the Preface) written by the Consul's sister. The description of Haidée's dress is taken from the account of a visit to Lilla Kebbiera, the wife of the Bashaw (p. 30); the description of the furniture and refreshments from the account of a visit to "Lilla Amnani," Hadgi Abderrahmam's Greek wife (pp. 132-137). It is evident that the "Chiel" who took these "notes" was the Consul's sister, not the Consul: "Lilla Aisha, the Bey's wife, is thought to be very sensible, though rather haughty. Her apartments were grand, and herself superbly habited. Her chemise was covered with gold embroidery at the neck; over it she wore a gold and silver tissue jileck, or jacket without sleeves, and over that another of purple velvet richly laced with gold, with coral and pearl buttons set quite close together down the front; it had short sleeves finished with a gold band not far below the shoulder, and discovered a wide loose chemise of transparent gauze, with gold, silver, and ribband strips. She wore round her ancles ... a sort of fetter made of a thick bar of gold so fine that they bound it round the leg with one hand; it is an inch and a half wide, and as much in thickness: each of these weighs four pounds. Just above this a band three inches wide of gold thread finished the ends of a pair of trousers made of pale yellow and white silk."

Page 132. "[Lilla] rose to take coffee, which was served in very small china cups, placed in silver filigree cups; and gold filigree cups were put under those presented to the married ladies. They had introduced cloves, cinnamon, and saffron into the coffee, which was abundantly sweetened; but this mixture was very soon changed, and replaced by excellent simple coffee for the European ladies...."

Page 133. "The Greek then shewed us the gala furniture of her own room.... The hangings of the room were of tapestry, made in pannels of different coloured velvets, thickly inlaid with flowers of silk damask; a yellow border, of about a foot in depth, finished the tapestry at top and bottom, the upper border being embroidered with Moorish sentences from the Koran in lilac letters. The carpet was of crimson satin, with a deep border of pale blue quilted; this is laid over Indian mats and other carpets. In the best part of the room the sofa is placed, which occupies three sides in an alcove, the floor of which is raised. The sofa and the cushions that lay around were of crimson velvet, the centre cushions were embroidered with a sun in gold of highly embossed work, the rest were of gold and silver tissue. The curtains of the alcove were made to match those before the bed. A number of looking-glasses, and a profusion of fine china and chrystal completed the ornaments and furniture of the room, in which were neither tables nor chairs. A small table, about six inches high, is brought in when refreshments are served; it is of ebony, inlaid with mother-of-pearl, tortoiseshell, ivory, gold and silver, of choice woods, or of plain mahogany, according to the circumstances of the proprietor."

Page 136. "On the tables were placed all sorts of refreshments, and thirty or forty dishes of meat and poultry, dressed different ways; there were no knives nor forks, and only a few spoons of gold, silver, ivory, or coral...."

Page 137. "The beverage was various sherbets, some composed of the juice of boiled raisins, very sweet; some of the juice of pomegranates squeezed through the rind; and others of the pure juice of oranges. These sherbets were copiously supplied in high glass ewers, placed in great numbers on the ground.... After the dishes of meat were removed, a dessert of Arabian fruits, confectionaries, and sweetmeats was served; among the latter was the date-bread. This sweetmeat is made in perfection only by the blacks at Fezzan, of the ripe date of the country.... They make it in the shape of loaves, weighing from twenty to thirty pounds; the stones of the fruit are taken out, and the dates simply pressed together with great weights; thus preserved, it keeps perfectly good for a year."]

[184] {162}["He writes like a man who has that clear perception of the truth of things which is the result of the guilty knowledge of good and evil; and who, by the light of that knowledge, has deliberately preferred the evil with a proud malignity of purpose, which would seem to leave little for the last consummating change to accomplish. When he calculates that the reader is on the verge of pitying him, he takes care to throw him back the defiance of laughter, as if to let him know that all the Poet's pathos is but the sentimentalism of the drunkard between his cups, or the relenting softness of the courtesan, who the next moment resumes the bad boldness of her degraded character. With such a man, who would wish either to laugh or to weep?"—Eclectic Review (Lord Byron's Mazeppa), August, 1819, vol. xii. p. 150.]

[CR] For that's the name they like to cant beneath.—[MS.]

[CS] {163}The upholsterer's "fiat lux" had bade to issue.—[MS.]

[185] {164}This dress is Moorish, and the bracelets and bar are worn in the manner described. The reader will perceive hereafter, that as the mother of Haidée was of Fez, her daughter wore the garb of the country. [Vide ante, p. 160, note 1.]

[186] The bar of gold above the instep is a mark of sovereign rank in the women of the families of the Deys, and is worn as such by their female relatives. [Vide ibid.]

[187] This is no exaggeration: there were four women whom I remember to have seen, who possessed their hair in this profusion; of these, three were English, the other was a Levantine. Their hair was of that length and quantity, that, when let down, it almost entirely shaded the person, so as nearly to render dress a superfluity. Of these, only one had dark hair; the Oriental's had, perhaps, the lightest colour of the four.

[188] [Compare—

"Yet there was round thee such a dawn

Of Light ne'er seen before,

As Fancy never could have drawn,

And never can restore."

Song by Rev. C. Wolfe (1791-1823).

Compare, too—

"She was a form of Life and Light

That, seen, became a part of sight."

The Giaour, lines 1127, 1128.]

[189] {165}

[" ... but Psyche owns no lord—

She walks a goddess from above;

All saw, all praised her, all adored,

But no one ever dared to love."

The Golden Ass of Apuleius; in English verse, entitled Cupid and Psyche, by Hudson Gurney, 1799.]

[190] [King John, act iv. sc. 2, line 11.]

[191] {166} ["Richard Crashaw (died 1650), the friend of Cowley, was honoured," says Warton, "with the praise of Pope; who both read his poems and borrowed from them. After he was ejected from his Fellowship at Peterhouse for denying the covenant, he turned Roman Catholic, and died canon of the church at Loretto." Cowley sang his In Memoriam—

"Angels (they say) brought the famed Chappel there;

And bore the sacred Load in Triumph through the air:—

'T is surer much they brought thee there, and They,

And Thou, their charge, went singing all the way."

The Works, etc., 1668, pp. 29, 30.]

[CT] Believed like Southey—and perused like Crashaw.—[MS.]

[192] {167}[The second chapter of Coleridge's Biographia Literaria is on the "supposed irritability of men of genius." Ed. 1847, i. 29.]

[CU] Their poet a sad Southey.—[MS. D.]

[CV] Of rogues—.—[MS. D.]

[CW] Of which the causers never know the cause.—[MS. D.]

[193] {168}[Vide St. August. Epist., xxxvi., cap. xiv., "Ille [Ambrosius, Mediolanensis Episcopus] adjecit; Quando hic sum, non jejuno sabbato; quando Romae sum, jejuno sabbato."—Migne's Patrologiæ Cursus, 1845, xxxiii. 151.]

[CX] From the high lyrical to the low rational.—[MS.D.]

[194] [The allusion is to Coleridge's eulogy of Southey in the Biographia Literaria (ed. 1847, i. 61): "In poetry he has attempted almost every species of composition known before, and he has added new ones; and if we except the very highest lyric ... he has attempted every species successfully." But the satire, primarily and ostensibly aimed at Southey, now and again glances at Southey's eulogist.]

[195] ["Goethe pourroit représenter la littérature allemande toute entière."—De L'Allemagne, par Mme. la Baronne de Staël-Holstein, 1818, i. 227.]

[196] [The poet is not "a sad Southey," but is sketched from memory. "Lord Byron," writes Finlay (History of Greece, vi. 335, note), "used to describe an evening passed in the company of Londos [a Morean landowner, who took part in the first and second Greek Civil Wars], at Vostitza (in 1809), when both were young men, with a spirit that rendered the scene worthy of a place in Don Juan. After supper Londos, who had the face and figure of a chimpanzee, sprang upon a table, ... and commenced singing through his nose Rhiga's Hymn to Liberty. A new cadi, passing near the house, inquired the cause of the discordant hubbub. A native Mussulman replied, 'It is only the young primate Londos, who is drunk, and is singing hymns to the new panaghia of the Greeks, whom they call Eleutheria.'" (See letter to Andreas Londos (undated), Letters, 1901, vi. 320, note 1.)]

[197] {169}The Μακάρων νῆσοι [Hesiod, Works and Days, line 169] of the Greek poets were supposed to have been the Cape de Verd Islands, or the Canaries.

[CY]

Euboea looks on Marathon,

And Marathon looks on the sea, etc.—[MS.]

[198] [See Æschylus, Persæ, 463, sq.; and Herodotus, viii. 90. Harpocration records the preservation, in the Acropolis, of the silver-footed throne on which Xerxes sat when he watched the battle of Salamis from the slope of Mount Ægaleos.]

[CZ] {170}The Heroic heart awakes no more.—[MS. D.]

[199] {171}[For "that most ancient military dance, the Pyrrhica," see Travels, by E.D. Clarke, 1814, part ii. sect. 11, p. 641; and for specimens of "Cadmean characters," vide ibid., p. 593.]

[200] [After his birthplace Teos was taken by the Persians, B.C. 510, Anacreon migrated to Abdera, but afterwards lived at Samos, under the protection of Polycrates.]

[DA] Which Hercules might deem his own.—[MS.]

[201] {172}[See the translation of a speech delivered to the Pargiots, in 1815, by an aged citizen: "I exhort you well to consider, before you yield yourselves up to the English, that the King of England now has in his pay all the kings of Europe—obtaining money for this purpose from his merchants; whence, should it become advantageous to the merchants to sell you, in order to conciliate Ali, and obtain certain commercial advantages in his harbours, the English will sell you to Ali." —"Parga," Edinburgh Review, October, 1819. vol. 32, pp. 263-293. Here, perhaps, the "Franks" are the Russians. Compare—

"Greeks only should free Greece,

Not the barbarian with his masque of peace."

The Age of Bronze, lines 298, 299, Poetical Works, 1901, v. 557, note 1.]

[202]

[Γενοίμαν, ἵν' ὑλᾶεν ἔπεστι πόν-

του πρόβλημ' ἁλίκλυστον, ἄ-

κραν ὑπὸ πλάκα Σουνίου, κ.τ.λ.

Sophocles, Ajax, lines 1190-1192.]

[203] {173}[Compare—

"What poets feel not, when they make,

A pleasure in creating,

The world, in its turn, will not take

Pleasure in contemplating."

Matthew Arnold (Motto to Poems, 1869, vol. i. Fly-leaf).]

[204] [For this "sentence," see Journal, November 16, 1813, Letters, 1898, ii. 320, note 1; see, too, letter to Rogers, 1814, Letters, 1899, iii. 89, note 1.]

[DB] In digging drains for a new water-closet.—[MS.]

[205] [For Edmund Hoyle (1672-1769), see English Bards, etc., lines 966-968, Poetical Works, 1898, i. 372, note 4.]

[206] {174}[William Coxe (1747-1828), Archdeacon of Wilts, a voluminous historian and biographer, published Memoirs of John, Duke of Marlborough, in 1817-1819.]

[207] [See Life of Milton, Works of Samuel Johnson, 1825, vii. pp. 67, 68, 80, et vide ante, p. 146, note 2.]

[208] [According to Suetonius, the youthful Titus amused himself by copying handwriting, and boasted that he could have made a first-rate falsarius. One of Cæsar's "earliest acts" was to crucify some jovial pirates, who had kidnapped him, and with whom he pretended to be on pleasant if not friendly terms.]

[209] [James Currie, M.D. (1756-1805), published, anonymously, the Works of Robert Burns, with an account of his Life, etc., in 1800.]

[210] ["He [Cromwell] was very notorious for robbing orchards, a puerile crime ... but grown so scandalous and injurious by the frequent spoyls and damages of Trees, breaking of Hedges, and Inclosures, committed by this Apple-Dragon, that many solemn complaints were made both to his Father and Mother for redresse thereof; which missed not their satisfaction and expiation out of his hide," etc.—Flagellum, by James Heath, 1663, p. 5. See, too, for his "name of a Royster" at Cambridge, A Short View of the Late Troubles in England, by Sir William Dugdale, 1681, p. 459.]

[211] {175}[In The Friend, 1818, ii. 38, Coleridge refers to "a plan ... of trying the experiment of human perfectibility on the banks of the Susquehanna;" and Southey, in his Letter to William Smith, Esq. (1817), (Essays Moral and Political, by Robert Southey, 1832, ii. 17), speaks of his "purpose to retire with a few friends into the wilds of America, and there lay the foundations of a community," etc.; but the word "Pantisocracy" is not mentioned. It occurs, perhaps, for the first time in print, in George Dyer's biographical sketch of Southey, which he contributed to Public Characters of 1799-1800, p. 225, "Coleridge, no less than Southey, possessed a strong passion for poetry. They commenced, like two young poets, an enthusiastic friendship, and in connection with others, struck out a plan for settling in America, and for having all things in common. This scheme they called Pantisocracy." Hence, the phrase must have "caught on," for, in a footnote to his review of Coleridge's Literary Life (Edin. Rev., August, 1817, vol. xxviii. p. 501), Jeffrey speaks of "the Pantisocratic or Lake School."]

[212] [Wordsworth was "hired," but not, like Burns, "excised." Hazlitt (Lectures on the English Poets, 1870, p. 174) is responsible for the epithet: "Mr. Wordsworth might have shown the incompatibility between the Muse and the Excise," etc.]

[DC] Confined his pedlar poems to democracy.—[MS.]

[213] [Coleridge began his poetical contributions to the Morning Post in January, 1798; his poetical articles in 1800.]

[DD] Flourished its sophistry for aristocracy.—[MS.]

[214] [Coleridge was married to Sarah Fricker, October 5; Southey to her younger sister Edith, November 15, 1795. Their father, Stephen Fricker, who had been an innkeeper, and afterwards a potter at Bristol, migrated to Bath about the year 1780. For the last six years of his life he was owner and manager of a coal wharf. He had inherited a small fortune, and his wife brought him money, but he died bankrupt, and left his family destitute. His widow returned to Bristol, and kept a school. In a letter to Murray, dated September 11, 1822 (Letters, 1901, vi. 113), Byron quotes the authority of "Luttrell," and "his friend Mr. Nugent," for the statement that Mrs. Southey and "Coleridge's Sara ... before they were married ... were milliner's or dressmaker's apprentices." The story rests upon their evidence. It is certain that in 1794, when Coleridge appeared upon the scene, the sisters earned their living by going out to work in the houses of friends, and were not, at that time, "milliners of Bath."]

[215] {176}[For Joanna Southcott (1750-1814), see Letters, 1899, iii. 128-130, note 2.]

[216] [Here follows, in the original MS.—

"Time has approved Ennui to be the best

Of friends, and opiate draughts; your love and wine,

Which shake so much the human brain and breast,

Must end in languor;—men must sleep like swine:

The happy lover and the welcome guest

Both sink at last into a swoon divine;

Full of deep raptures and of bumpers, they

Are somewhat sick and sorry the next day."]

[217] {177}["Quandoque bonus dormitat Homerus."—Hor., Epist. Ad Pisones, line 359.]

[218] [Wordsworth's Benjamin the Waggoner, was written in 1805, but was not published till 1819. "Benjamin" was servant to William Jackson, a Keswick carrier, who built Greta Hall, and let off part of the house to Coleridge.]

[219]

["There's something in a flying horse,

There's something in a huge balloon;

But through the clouds I'll never float

Until I have a little Boat,

Shaped like the crescent-moon."

Wordsworth's Peter Bell, stanza i.]

[220] [For Medea's escape from the wrath of Jason, "Titaniacis ablata draconibus," see Ovid., Met., vii. 398.]

[221] [In his "Essay, Supplementary to the Preface," to his "Poems" of 1815, Wordsworth, commenting on a passage on Night in Dryden's Indian Emperor, says, "Dryden's lines are vague, bombastic, and senseless.... The verses of Dryden once celebrated are forgotten." He is not passing any general criticism on "him who drew Achitophel." In a letter to Sir Walter Scott (November 7, 1805), then engaged on his great edition of Dryden's Works, he admits that Dryden is not "as a poet any great favourite of mine. I admire his talents and genius highly, but he is not a poetical genius. The only qualities I can find in Dryden that are essentially poetical, are a certain ardour and impetuosity of mind, with an excellent ear" (Life of Wordsworth, by W. Knight, 1889, ii. 26-29). Scott may have remarked on Wordsworth's estimate of Dryden in conversation with Byron.]

[DE] {178}While swung the signal from the sacred tower.—[MS.]

[DF] {179}

Are not these pretty stanzas?—some folks say—

Downright in print—.—[MS.]

[222] [Compare Coleridge's Lines to Nature, which were published in the Morning Herald, in 1815, but must have been unknown to Byron—

"So will I build my altar in the fields,

And the blue sky my fretted dome shall be."]

[223] ["As early as the fifth or sixth century of the Christian era, the port of Augustus was converted into pleasant orchards, and a lovely grove of pines covered the ground where the Roman fleet once rode at anchor.... This advantageous situation was fortified by art and labour, and in the twentieth year of his age, the Emperor of the West ... retired to ... the walls and morasses of Ravenna."—Gibbon's Decline and Fall, 1825, ii. 244, 245.]

[224] ["The first time I had a conversation with Lord Byron on the subject of religion was at Ravenna, my native country, in 1820, while we were riding on horseback in an extensive solitary wood of pines. The scene invited to religious meditation. It was a fine day in spring. 'How,' he said, 'raising our eyes to heaven, or directing them to the earth, can we doubt of the existence of God?—or how, turning them to what is within us, can we doubt that there is something more noble and durable than the clay of which we are formed?'"—Count Gamba.]

[225] {180}[If the Pineta of Ravenna, bois funèbre, invited Byron "to religious meditation," the mental picture of the "spectre huntsman" pursuing his eternal vengeance on "the inexorable dame"—"that fatal she," who had mocked his woes—must have set in motion another train of thought. Such lines as these would "speak comfortably" to him—

"Because she deem'd I well deserved to die,

And made a merit of her cruelty, ...

Mine is the ungrateful maid by heaven design'd:

Mercy she would not give, nor mercy shall she find."

"By her example warn'd, the rest beware;

More easy, less imperious, were the fair;

And that one hunting, which the Devil design'd

For one fair female, lost him half the kind."

Dryden's Theodore and Honoria (sub fine).]

[226]

Εσπερε παντα φερεις

Φερεις οινον—φερεις αιγα

Φερεις ματερι παιδα.

Fragment of Sappho.

[Ϝέσπερε, πάντα φέρων, ὅσα φαίνολις ἐσκέδασ' αὔως·

Φέρεις οἴν φέρεις αἶγα, Φέρεις ἄπυ ματέρι παῖδα.

Sappho, Memoir, Text, by Henry Thornton Wharton, 1895, p. 136.

"Evening, all things thou bringest

Which dawn spread apart from each other;

The lamb and the kid thou bringest,

Thou bringest the boy to his mother."

J.A. Symonds.

Compare Tennyson's Locksley Hall, Sixty Years After—"Hesper, whom the poet call'd the Bringer home of all good things."]

[227] {181}

"Era già l'ora che volge il disio

Ai naviganti, e intenerisce il cuore;

Lo di ch' han detto ai dolci amici addio;

E che lo nuovo peregrin' damore

Punge, se ode squilla di lontano,

Che paia il giorno pianger che si more."

Dante's Purgatory, canto viii., lines 1-6.

This last line is the first of Gray's Elegy, taken by him without acknowledgment.

[228] See Suetonius for this fact.

["The public joy was so great upon the occasion of his death, that the common people ran up and down with caps upon their heads. And yet there were some, who for a long time trimmed up his tomb with spring and summer flowers, and, one while, placed his image upon his rostra dressed up in state robes, another while published proclamations in his name, as if he was yet alive, and would shortly come to Rome again, with a vengeance to all his enemies."—De XII. Cæs., lib. vi. cap. lvii.]

[DG]

But I'm digressing—what on earth have Nero

And Wordsworth—both poetical buffoons, etc.—[MS.]

[229] {182} [See De Poeticâ, cap. xxiv. See, too, the Preface to Dryden's "Dedication" of the Æneis (Works of John Dryden, 1821, xiv. 130-134). Dryden is said to have derived his knowledge of Aristotle from Dacier's translation, and it is probable that Byron derived his from Dryden. See letter to Hodgson (Letters, 1891, v. 284), in which he quotes Aristotle as quoted in Johnson's Life of Dryden.]

Canto IV

I.

Nothing so difficult as a beginning

In poesy, unless perhaps the end;

For oftentimes when Pegasus seems winning

The race, he sprains a wing, and down we tend,

Like Lucifer when hurled from Heaven for sinning;

Our sin the same, and hard as his to mend,

Being Pride,[230] which leads the mind to soar too far,

Till our own weakness shows us what we are.

II.

But Time, which brings all beings to their level,

And sharp Adversity, will teach at last

Man,—and, as we would hope,—perhaps the Devil,

That neither of their intellects are vast:

While Youth's hot wishes in our red veins revel,

We know not this—the blood flows on too fast;

But as the torrent widens towards the Ocean,

We ponder deeply on each past emotion.[231]

III.

As boy, I thought myself a clever fellow,

And wished that others held the same opinion;

They took it up when my days grew more mellow,

And other minds acknowledged my dominion:

Now my sere Fancy "falls into the yellow

Leaf,"[232] and Imagination droops her pinion,

And the sad truth which hovers o'er my desk

Turns what was once romantic to burlesque.

IV.

And if I laugh at any mortal thing,

'T is that I may not weep; and if I weep,

'T is that our nature cannot always bring

Itself to apathy, for we must steep[DH]

Our hearts first in the depths of Lethe's spring,[DI]

Ere what we least wish to behold will sleep:

Thetis baptized her mortal son in Styx;

A mortal mother would on Lethe fix.

V.

Some have accused me of a strange design

Against the creed and morals of the land,

And trace it in this poem every line:

I don't pretend that I quite understand

My own meaning when I would be very fine;

But the fact is that I have nothing planned,

Unless it were to be a moment merry—

A novel word in my vocabulary.

VI.

To the kind reader of our sober clime

This way of writing will appear exotic;

Pulci[233] was sire of the half-serious rhyme,[DJ]

Who sang when Chivalry was more quixotic,

And revelled in the fancies of the time,

True Knights, chaste Dames, huge Giants, Kings despotic;

But all these, save the last, being obsolete,

I chose a modern subject as more meet.

VII.

How I have treated it, I do not know;

Perhaps no better than they have treated me,

Who have imputed such designs as show

Not what they saw, but what they wished to see:

But if it gives them pleasure, be it so;

This is a liberal age, and thoughts are free:

Meantime Apollo plucks me by the ear,

And tells me to resume my story here.[234]

VIII.

Young Juan and his lady-love were left

To their own hearts' most sweet society;

Even Time the pitiless in sorrow cleft

With his rude scythe such gentle bosoms; he

Sighed to behold them of their hours bereft,

Though foe to Love; and yet they could not be

Meant to grow old, but die in happy Spring,

Before one charm or hope had taken wing.

IX.

Their faces were not made for wrinkles, their

Pure blood to stagnate, their great hearts to fail;

The blank grey was not made to blast their hair,

But like the climes that know nor snow nor hail,

They were all summer; lightning might assail

And shiver them to ashes, but to trail

A long and snake-like life of dull decay

Was not for them—they had too little clay.

X.

They were alone once more; for them to be

Thus was another Eden; they were never

Weary, unless when separate: the tree

Cut from its forest root of years—the river

Dammed from its fountain—the child from the knee

And breast maternal weaned at once for ever,—

Would wither less than these two torn apart;[DK]

Alas! there is no instinct like the Heart—

XI.

The Heart—which may be broken: happy they!

Thrice fortunate! who of that fragile mould,

The precious porcelain of human clay,

Break with the first fall: they can ne'er behold

The long year linked with heavy day on day,

And all which must be borne, and never told;

While Life's strange principle will often lie

Deepest in those who long the most to die.

XII.

"Whom the gods love die young," was said of yore,[235]

And many deaths do they escape by this:

The death of friends, and that which slays even more—

The death of Friendship, Love, Youth, all that is,

Except mere breath; and since the silent shore

Awaits at last even those who longest miss

The old Archer's shafts, perhaps the early grave[236]

Which men weep over may be meant to save.

XIII.

Haidée and Juan thought not of the dead—

The Heavens, and Earth, and Air, seemed made for them:

They found no fault with Time, save that he fled;

They saw not in themselves aught to condemn:

Each was the other's mirror, and but read

Joy sparkling in their dark eyes like a gem.

And knew such brightness was but the reflection

Of their exchanging glances of affection.

XIV.

The gentle pressure, and the thrilling touch,

The least glance better understood than words,

Which still said all, and ne'er could say too much;

A language,[237] too, but like to that of birds,

Known but to them, at least appearing such

As but to lovers a true sense affords;

Sweet playful phrases, which would seem absurd

To those who have ceased to hear such, or ne'er heard—

XV.

All these were theirs, for they were children still,

And children still they should have ever been;

They were not made in the real world to fill

A busy character in the dull scene,

But like two beings born from out a rill,

A Nymph and her belovéd, all unseen

To pass their lives in fountains and on flowers,

And never know the weight of human hours.

XVI.

Moons changing had rolled on, and changeless found

Those their bright rise had lighted to such joys

As rarely they beheld throughout their round;

And these were not of the vain kind which cloys,

For theirs were buoyant spirits, never bound

By the mere senses; and that which destroys[DL]

Most love—possession—unto them appeared

A thing which each endearment more endeared.

XVII.

Oh beautiful! and rare as beautiful!

But theirs was Love in which the Mind delights

To lose itself, when the old world grows dull,

And we are sick of its hack sounds and sights,

Intrigues, adventures of the common school,

Its petty passions, marriages, and flights,

Where Hymen's torch but brands one strumpet more,

Whose husband only knows her not a whore.

XVIII.

Hard words—harsh truth! a truth which many know.

Enough.—The faithful and the fairy pair,

Who never found a single hour too slow,

What was it made them thus exempt from care?

Young innate feelings all have felt below,

Which perish in the rest, but in them were

Inherent—what we mortals call romantic,

And always envy, though we deem it frantic.

XIX.

This is in others a factitious state,

An opium dream[238] of too much youth and reading,

But was in them their nature or their fate:

No novels e'er had set their young hearts bleeding,[DM]

For Haidée's knowledge was by no means great,

And Juan was a boy of saintly breeding;

So that there was no reason for their loves

More than for those of nightingales or doves.

XX.

They gazed upon the sunset; 't is an hour

Dear unto all, but dearest to their eyes,

For it had made them what they were: the power

Of Love had first o'erwhelmed them from such skies,

When Happiness had been their only dower,

And Twilight saw them linked in Passion's ties;

Charmed with each other, all things charmed that brought

The past still welcome as the present thought.

XXI.

I know not why, but in that hour to-night,

Even as they gazed, a sudden tremor came,

And swept, as 't were, across their hearts' delight,

Like the wind o'er a harp-string, or a flame,

When one is shook in sound, and one in sight:

And thus some boding flashed through either frame,

And called from Juan's breast a faint low sigh,

While one new tear arose in Haidée's eye.

XXII.

That large black prophet eye seemed to dilate

And follow far the disappearing sun,

As if their last day of a happy date

With his broad, bright, and dropping orb were gone;

Juan gazed on her as to ask his fate—

He felt a grief, but knowing cause for none,

His glance inquired of hers for some excuse

For feelings causeless, or at least abstruse.

XXIII.

She turned to him, and smiled, but in that sort

Which makes not others smile; then turned aside:

Whatever feeling shook her, it seemed short,

And mastered by her wisdom or her pride;

When Juan spoke, too—it might be in sport—

Of this their mutual feeling, she replied—

"If it should be so,—but—it cannot be—

Or I at least shall not survive to see."

XXIV.

Juan would question further, but she pressed

His lip to hers, and silenced him with this,

And then dismissed the omen from her breast,

Defying augury with that fond kiss;

And no doubt of all methods 't is the best:

Some people prefer wine—'t is not amiss;

I have tried both—so those who would a part take

May choose between the headache and the heartache.

XXV.

One of the two, according to your choice,

Woman or wine, you'll have to undergo;

Both maladies are taxes on our joys:

But which to choose, I really hardly know;

And if I had to give a casting voice,

For both sides I could many reasons show,

And then decide, without great wrong to either,

It were much better to have both than neither.

XXVI.

Juan and Haidée gazed upon each other

With swimming looks of speechless tenderness,

Which mixed all feelings—friend, child, lover, brother—

All that the best can mingle and express

When two pure hearts are poured in one another,

And love too much, and yet can not love less;

But almost sanctify the sweet excess

By the immortal wish and power to bless.

XXVII.

Mixed in each other's arms, and heart in heart,

Why did they not then die?—they had lived too long

Should an hour come to bid them breathe apart;

Years could but bring them cruel things or wrong;

The World was not for them—nor the World's art

For beings passionate as Sappho's song;

Love was born with them, in them, so intense,

It was their very Spirit—not a sense.

XXVIII.

They should have lived together deep in woods,

Unseen as sings the nightingale;[239] they were

Unfit to mix in these thick solitudes

Called social, haunts of Hate, and Vice, and Care:[DN]

How lonely every freeborn creature broods!

The sweetest song-birds nestle in a pair;

The eagle soars alone; the gull and crow

Flock o'er their carrion, just like men below.

XXIX.

Now pillowed cheek to cheek, in loving sleep,

Haidée and Juan their siesta took,

A gentle slumber, but it was not deep,

For ever and anon a something shook

Juan, and shuddering o'er his frame would creep;

And Haidée's sweet lips murmured like a brook

A wordless music, and her face so fair

Stirred with her dream, as rose-leaves with the air.[DO]

XXX.

Or as the stirring of a deep clear stream

Within an Alpine hollow, when the wind

Walks o'er it, was she shaken by the dream,

The mystical Usurper of the mind—

O'erpowering us to be whate'er may seem

Good to the soul which we no more can bind;

Strange state of being! (for 't is still to be)

Senseless to feel, and with sealed eyes to see.[DP]

XXXI.

She dreamed of being alone on the sea-shore,

Chained to a rock; she knew not how, but stir

She could not from the spot, and the loud roar

Grew, and each wave rose roughly, threatening her;

And o'er her upper lip they seemed to pour,

Until she sobbed for breath, and soon they were

Foaming o'er her lone head, so fierce and high—

Each broke to drown her, yet she could not die.

XXXII.

Anon—she was released, and then she strayed

O'er the sharp shingles with her bleeding feet,

And stumbled almost every step she made:

And something rolled before her in a sheet,

Which she must still pursue howe'er afraid:

'T was white and indistinct, nor stopped to meet

Her glance nor grasp, for still she gazed and grasped,

And ran, but it escaped her as she clasped.

XXXIII.

The dream changed:—in a cave[240] she stood, its walls

Were hung with marble icicles; the work

Of ages on its water-fretted halls,

Where waves might wash, and seals might breed and lurk;

Her hair was dripping, and the very balls

Of her black eyes seemed turned to tears, and mirk

The sharp rocks looked below each drop they caught,

Which froze to marble as it fell,—she thought.[DQ]

XXXIV.

And wet, and cold, and lifeless at her feet,

Pale as the foam that frothed on his dead brow,

Which she essayed in vain to clear, (how sweet

Were once her cares, how idle seemed they now!)

Lay Juan, nor could aught renew the beat

Of his quenched heart: and the sea dirges low

Rang in her sad ears like a Mermaid's song,

And that brief dream appeared a life too long.

XXXV.

And gazing on the dead, she thought his face

Faded, or altered into something new—

Like to her Father's features, till each trace

More like and like to Lambro's aspect grew—

With all his keen worn look and Grecian grace;

And starting, she awoke, and what to view?

Oh! Powers of Heaven! what dark eye meets she there?

'T is—'t is her Father's—fixed upon the pair!

XXXVI.

Then shrieking, she arose, and shrieking fell,

With joy and sorrow, hope and fear, to see

Him whom she deemed a habitant where dwell

The ocean-buried, risen from death, to be

Perchance the death of one she loved too well:

Dear as her father had been to Haidée,

It was a moment of that awful kind—

I have seen such—but must not call to mind.

XXXVII.

Up Juan sprang to Haidée's bitter shriek,

And caught her falling, and from off the wall

Snatched down his sabre, in hot haste to wreak

Vengeance on him who was the cause of all:

Then Lambro, who till now forbore to speak,

Smiled scornfully, and said, "Within my call,

A thousand scimitars await the word;

Put up, young man, put up your silly sword."

XXXVIII.

And Haidée clung around him; "Juan, 't is—

'T is Lambro—'t is my father! Kneel with me—

He will forgive us—yes—it must be—yes.

Oh! dearest father, in this agony

Of pleasure and of pain—even while I kiss

Thy garment's hem with transport, can it be

That doubt should mingle with my filial joy?

Deal with me as thou wilt, but spare this boy."

XXXIX.

High and inscrutable the old man stood,

Calm in his voice, and calm within his eye—

Not always signs with him of calmest mood:

He looked upon her, but gave no reply;

Then turned to Juan, in whose cheek the blood

Oft came and went, as there resolved to die;

In arms, at least, he stood, in act to spring

On the first foe whom Lambro's call might bring.

XL.

"Young man, your sword;" so Lambro once more said:

Juan replied, "Not while this arm is free."

The old man's cheek grew pale, but not with dread,

And drawing from his belt a pistol he

Replied, "Your blood be then on your own head."

Then looked close at the flint, as if to see

'T was fresh—for he had lately used the lock—

And next proceeded quietly to cock.

XLI.

It has a strange quick jar upon the ear,

That cocking of a pistol, when you know

A moment more will bring the sight to bear

Upon your person, twelve yards off, or so;

A gentlemanly distance, not too near,

If you have got a former friend for foe;

But after being fired at once or twice,

The ear becomes more Irish, and less nice.

XLII.

Lambro presented, and one instant more

Had stopped this Canto, and Don Juan's breath,

When Haidée threw herself her boy before;

Stern as her sire: "On me," she cried, "let Death

Descend—the fault is mine; this fatal shore

He found—but sought not. I have pledged my faith;

I love him—I will die with him: I knew

Your nature's firmness—know your daughter's too."

XLIII.

A minute past, and she had been all tears,

And tenderness, and infancy; but now

She stood as one who championed human fears—

Pale, statue-like, and stern, she wooed the blow;

And tall beyond her sex, and their compeers,

She drew up to her height, as if to show

A fairer mark; and with a fixed eye scanned

Her Father's face—but never stopped his hand.

XLIV.

He gazed on her, and she on him; 't was strange

How like they looked! the expression was the same;

Serenely savage, with a little change

In the large dark eye's mutual-darted flame;

For she, too, was as one who could avenge,

If cause should be—a Lioness, though tame.

Her Father's blood before her Father's face

Boiled up, and proved her truly of his race.

XLV.

I said they were alike, their features and

Their stature, differing but in sex and years;

Even to the delicacy of their hand[241]

There was resemblance, such as true blood wears;

And now to see them, thus divided, stand

In fixed ferocity, when joyous tears

And sweet sensations should have welcomed both,

Shows what the passions are in their full growth.

XLVI.

The father paused a moment, then withdrew

His weapon, and replaced it; but stood still,

And looking on her, as to look her through,

"Not I," he said, "have sought this stranger's ill;

Not I have made this desolation: few

Would bear such outrage, and forbear to kill;

But I must do my duty—how thou hast

Done thine, the present vouches for the past.[DR]

XLVII.

"Let him disarm; or, by my father's head,

His own shall roll before you like a ball!"

He raised his whistle, as the word he said,

And blew; another answered to the call,

And rushing in disorderly, though led,

And armed from boot to turban, one and all,

Some twenty of his train came, rank on rank;

He gave the word,—"Arrest or slay the Frank."

XLVIII.

Then, with a sudden movement, he withdrew

His daughter; while compressed within his clasp,

Twixt her and Juan interposed the crew;

In vain she struggled in her father's grasp—

His arms were like a serpent's coil: then flew

Upon their prey, as darts an angry asp,

The file of pirates—save the foremost, who

Had fallen, with his right shoulder half cut through.

XLIX.

The second had his cheek laid open; but

The third, a wary, cool old sworder, took

The blows upon his cutlass, and then put

His own well in; so well, ere you could look,

His man was floored, and helpless at his foot,

With the blood running like a little brook

From two smart sabre gashes, deep and red—

One on the arm, the other on the head.

L.

And then they bound him where he fell, and bore

Juan from the apartment: with a sign

Old Lambro bade them take him to the shore,

Where lay some ships which were to sail at nine.[DS]

They laid him in a boat, and plied the oar

Until they reached some galliots, placed in line;

On board of one of these, and under hatches,

They stowed him, with strict orders to the watches.

LI.

The world is full of strange vicissitudes,

And here was one exceedingly unpleasant:

A gentleman so rich in the world's goods,

Handsome and young, enjoying all the present,[DT]

Just at the very time when he least broods

On such a thing, is suddenly to sea sent,

Wounded and chained, so that he cannot move,

And all because a lady fell in love.

LII.

Here I must leave him, for I grow pathetic,

Moved by the Chinese nymph of tears, green tea!

Than whom Cassandra was not more prophetic;

For if my pure libations exceed three,

I feel my heart become so sympathetic,

That I must have recourse to black Bohea:

'T is pity wine should be so deleterious,

For tea and coffee leave us much more serious,

LIII.

Unless when qualified with thee, Cogniac!

Sweet Naïad of the Phlegethontic rill!

Ah! why the liver wilt thou thus attack,[DU]—

And make, like other nymphs, thy lovers ill?

I would take refuge in weak punch, but rack

(In each sense of the word), whene'er I fill

My mild and midnight beakers to the brim,

Wakes me next morning with its synonym.[242]

LIV.

I leave Don Juan for the present, safe—

Not sound, poor fellow, but severely wounded;

Yet could his corporal pangs amount to half

Of those with which his Haidée's bosom bounded?

She was not one to weep, and rave, and chafe,

And then give way, subdued because surrounded;

Her mother was a Moorish maid from Fez,

Where all is Eden, or a wilderness.

LV.

There the large olive rains its amber store

In marble fonts; there grain, and flower, and fruit,

Gush from the earth until the land runs o'er;[243]

But there, too, many a poison-tree has root,

And Midnight listens to the lion's roar,

And long, long deserts scorch the camel's foot,

Or heaving whelm the helpless caravan;

And as the soil is, so the heart of man.

LVI.

Afric is all the Sun's, and as her earth

Her human clay is kindled; full of power

For good or evil, burning from its birth,

The Moorish blood partakes the planet's hour,

And like the soil beneath it will bring forth:

Beauty and love were Haidée's mother's dower;

But her large dark eye showed deep Passion's force,

Though sleeping like a lion near a source.[DV]

LVII.

Her daughter, tempered with a milder ray,

Like summer clouds all silvery, smooth, and fair,

Till slowly charged with thunder they display

Terror to earth, and tempest to the air,

Had held till now her soft and milky way;

But overwrought with Passion and Despair,

The fire burst forth from her Numidian veins,

Even as the Simoom[244] sweeps the blasted plains.

LVIII.

The last sight which she saw was Juan's gore,

And he himself o'ermastered and cut down;

His blood was running on the very floor

Where late he trod, her beautiful, her own;

Thus much she viewed an instant and no more,—

Her struggles ceased with one convulsive groan;

On her Sire's arm, which until now scarce held

Her writhing, fell she like a cedar felled.

LIX.

A vein had burst, and her sweet lips' pure dyes[DW]

Were dabbled with the deep blood which ran o'er;[245]

And her head drooped, as when the lily lies

O'ercharged with rain: her summoned handmaids bore

Their lady to her couch with gushing eyes;

Of herbs and cordials they produced their store,

But she defied all means they could employ,

Like one Life could not hold, nor Death destroy.

LX.

Days lay she in that state unchanged, though chill—

With nothing livid, still her lips were red;

She had no pulse, but Death seemed absent still;

No hideous sign proclaimed her surely dead;

Corruption came not in each mind to kill

All hope; to look upon her sweet face bred

New thoughts of Life, for it seemed full of soul—

She had so much, Earth could not claim the whole.

LXI.

The ruling passion, such as marble shows

When exquisitely chiselled, still lay there,

But fixed as marble's unchanged aspect throws

O'er the fair Venus, but for ever fair;[246]

O'er the Laocoon's all eternal throes,

And ever-dying Gladiator's air,

Their energy like life forms all their fame,

Yet looks not life, for they are still the same.—[DX]

LXII.

She woke at length, but not as sleepers wake,

Rather the dead, for Life seemed something new,

A strange sensation which she must partake

Perforce, since whatsoever met her view

Struck not on memory, though a heavy ache

Lay at her heart, whose earliest beat still true

Brought back the sense of pain without the cause,

For, for a while, the Furies made a pause.

LXIII.

She looked on many a face with vacant eye,

On many a token without knowing what:

She saw them watch her without asking why,

And recked not who around her pillow sat;

Not speechless, though she spoke not—not a sigh

Relieved her thoughts—dull silence and quick chat

Were tried in vain by those who served; she gave

No sign, save breath, of having left the grave.

LXIV.

Her handmaids tended, but she heeded not;

Her Father watched, she turned her eyes away;

She recognised no being, and no spot,

However dear or cherished in their day;

They changed from room to room—but all forgot—

Gentle, but without memory she lay;

At length those eyes, which they would fain be weaning

Back to old thoughts, waxed full of fearful meaning.

LXV.

And then a slave bethought her of a harp;

The harper came, and tuned his instrument;

At the first notes, irregular and sharp,

On him her flashing eyes a moment bent,

Then to the wall she turned as if to warp

Her thoughts from sorrow through her heart re-sent;

And he began a long low island-song

Of ancient days, ere Tyranny grew strong.

LXVI.

Anon her thin wan fingers beat the wall

In time to his old tune: he changed the theme,

And sung of Love; the fierce name struck through all

Her recollection; on her flashed the dream

Of what she was, and is, if ye could call

To be so being; in a gushing stream

The tears rushed forth from her o'erclouded brain,

Like mountain mists at length dissolved in rain.

LXVII.

Short solace, vain relief!—Thought came too quick,

And whirled her brain to madness; she arose

As one who ne'er had dwelt among the sick,

And flew at all she met, as on her foes;

But no one ever heard her speak or shriek,

Although her paroxysm drew towards its close;—

Hers was a frenzy which disdained to rave,

Even when they smote her, in the hope to save.

LXVIII.

Yet she betrayed at times a gleam of sense;

Nothing could make her meet her Father's face,

Though on all other things with looks intense

She gazed, but none she ever could retrace;

Food she refused, and raiment; no pretence

Availed for either; neither change of place,

Nor time, nor skill, nor remedy, could give her

Senses to sleep—the power seemed gone for ever.

LXIX.

Twelve days and nights she withered thus; at last,

Without a groan, or sigh, or glance, to show

A parting pang, the spirit from her passed:

And they who watched her nearest could not know

The very instant, till the change that cast

Her sweet face into shadow, dull and slow,[DY]

Glazed o'er her eyes—the beautiful, the black—

Oh! to possess such lustre—and then lack!

LXX.

She died, but not alone; she held, within,

A second principle of Life, which might

Have dawned a fair and sinless child of sin;[DZ]

But closed its little being without light,

And went down to the grave unborn, wherein

Blossom and bough lie withered with one blight;

In vain the dews of Heaven descend above

The bleeding flower and blasted fruit of Love.

LXXI.

Thus lived—thus died she; never more on her

Shall Sorrow light, or Shame. She was not made

Through years or moons the inner weight to bear,

Which colder hearts endure till they are laid

By age in earth: her days and pleasures were

Brief, but delightful—such as had not staid

Long with her destiny; but she sleeps well[247]

By the sea-shore, whereon she loved to dwell.

LXXII.

That isle is now all desolate and bare,

Its dwellings down, its tenants passed away;

None but her own and Father's grave is there,

And nothing outward tells of human clay;

Ye could not know where lies a thing so fair,

No stone is there to show, no tongue to say,

What was; no dirge, except the hollow sea's,[EA]

Mourns o'er the beauty of the Cyclades.

LXXIII.

But many a Greek maid in a loving song

Sighs o'er her name; and many an islander

With her Sire's story makes the night less long;

Valour was his, and Beauty dwelt with her:

If she loved rashly, her life paid for wrong—

A heavy price must all pay who thus err,

In some shape; let none think to fly the danger,

For soon or late Love is his own avenger.

LXXIV.

But let me change this theme, which grows too sad,

And lay this sheet of sorrows on the shelf;

I don't much like describing people mad,

For fear of seeming rather touched myself—

Besides, I've no more on this head to add;

And as my Muse is a capricious elf,

We'll put about, and try another tack

With Juan, left half-killed some stanzas back.

LXXV.

Wounded and fettered, "cabined, cribbed, confined,"[248]

Some days and nights elapsed before that he

Could altogether call the past to mind;

And when he did, he found himself at sea,

Sailing six knots an hour before the wind;

The shores of Ilion lay beneath their lee—

Another time he might have liked to see 'em,

But now was not much pleased with Cape Sigeum.

LXXVI.

There, on the green and village-cotted hill, is

(Flanked by the Hellespont, and by the sea)

Entombed the bravest of the brave, Achilles;

They say so—(Bryant[249] says the contrary):

And further downward, tall and towering still, is

The tumulus—of whom? Heaven knows! 't may be

Patroclus, Ajax, or Protesilaus—

All heroes, who if living still would slay us.[EB]

LXXVII.

High barrows, without marble, or a name,

A vast, untilled, and mountain-skirted plain,[EC]

And Ida in the distance, still the same,

And old Scamander (if 't is he) remain;

The situation seems still formed for fame—

A hundred thousand men might fight again,

With ease; but where I sought for Ilion's walls,

The quiet sheep feeds, and the tortoise[250] crawls;[ED]

LXXVIII.

Troops of untended horses; here and there

Some little hamlets, with new names uncouth;

Some shepherds (unlike Paris) led to stare

A moment at the European youth

Whom to the spot their school-boy feelings bear;[EE]

A Turk, with beads in hand, and pipe in mouth,

Extremely taken with his own religion,

Are what I found there—but the devil a Phrygian.

LXXIX.

Don Juan, here permitted to emerge

From his dull cabin, found himself a slave;

Forlorn, and gazing on the deep blue surge,

O'ershadowed there by many a Hero's grave;

Weak still with loss of blood, he scarce could urge

A few brief questions; and the answers gave

No very satisfactory information

About his past or present situation.

LXXX.

He saw some fellow captives, who appeared

To be Italians (as they were in fact)—

From them, at least, their destiny he heard,

Which was an odd one; a troop going to act

In Sicily—all singers, duly reared

In their vocation, had not been attacked

In sailing from Livorno by the pirate,

But sold by the impresario at no high rate.[251]

LXXXI.

By one of these, the buffo[252] of the party,

Juan was told about their curious case;

For although destined to the Turkish mart, he

Still kept his spirits up—at least his face;

The little fellow really looked quite hearty,

And bore him with some gaiety and grace,

Showing a much more reconciled demeanour,

Than did the prima donna and the tenor.

LXXXII.

In a few words he told their hapless story,

Saying, "Our Machiavelian impresario,

Making a signal off some promontory,

Hailed a strange brig—Corpo di Caio Mario!

We were transferred on board her in a hurry,

Without a single scudo of salario;

But if the Sultan has a taste for song,

We will revive our fortunes before long.

LXXXIII.

"The prima donna, though a little old,

And haggard with a dissipated life,

And subject, when the house is thin, to cold,

Has some good notes; and then the tenor's wife,

With no great voice, is pleasing to behold;

Last carnival she made a deal of strife,

By carrying off Count Cesare Cicogna

From an old Roman Princess at Bologna.

LXXXIV.

"And then there are the dancers; there's the Nini,

With more than one profession gains by all;

Then there's that laughing slut the Pelegrini,

She, too, was fortunate last Carnival,

And made at least five hundred good zecchini,

But spends so fast, she has not now a paul;

And then there's the Grotesca—such a dancer!

Where men have souls or bodies she must answer.

LXXXV.

"As for the figuranti,[253] they are like

The rest of all that tribe; with here and there

A pretty person, which perhaps may strike—

The rest are hardly fitted for a fair;

There's one, though tall and stiffer than a pike,

Yet has a sentimental kind of air

Which might go far, but she don't dance with vigour—

The more's the pity, with her face and figure.

LXXXVI.

"As for the men, they are a middling set;

The musico is but a cracked old basin,

But, being qualified in one way yet,

May the seraglio do to set his face in,[EF]

And as a servant some preferment get;

His singing I no further trust can place in:

From all the Pope[254] makes yearly 't would perplex

To find three perfect pipes of the third sex.

LXXXVII.

"The tenor's voice is spoilt by affectation;

And for the bass, the beast can only bellow—

In fact, he had no singing education,

An ignorant, noteless, timeless, tuneless fellow;

But being the prima donna's near relation,

Who swore his voice was very rich and mellow,

They hired him, though to hear him you'd believe

An ass was practising recitative.

LXXXVIII.

"'T would not become myself to dwell upon

My own merits, and though young—I see, Sir—you

Have got a travelled air, which speaks you one

To whom the opera is by no means new:

You've heard of Raucocanti?—I'm the man;

The time may come when you may hear me too;

You was[255] not last year at the fair of Lugo,

But next, when I'm engaged to sing there—do go.

LXXXIX.

"Our baritone I almost had forgot,

A pretty lad, but bursting with conceit;

With graceful action, science not a jot,

A voice of no great compass, and not sweet,

He always is complaining of his lot,

Forsooth, scarce fit for ballads in the street;

In lovers' parts his passion more to breathe,

Having no heart to show, he shows his teeth."[EG]

XC.

Here Raucocanti's eloquent recital

Was interrupted by the pirate crew,

Who came at stated moments to invite all

The captives back to their sad berths; each threw

A rueful glance upon the waves, (which bright all

From the blue skies derived a double blue,

Dancing all free and happy in the sun,)

And then went down the hatchway one by one.

XCI.

They heard next day—that in the Dardanelles,

Waiting for his Sublimity's firman,[256]

The most imperative of sovereign spells,

Which everybody does without who can,

More to secure them in their naval cells,

Lady to lady, well as man to man,

Were to be chained and lotted out per couple,

For the slave market of Constantinople.

XCII.

It seems when this allotment was made out,

There chanced to be an odd male, and odd female,

Who (after some discussion and some doubt,

If the soprano might be deemed to be male,

They placed him o'er the women as a scout)

Were linked together, and it happened the male

Was Juan,—who, an awkward thing at his age,

Paired off with a Bacchante blooming visage.

XCIII.

With Raucocanti lucklessly was chained

The tenor; these two hated with a hate

Found only on the stage, and each more pained

With this his tuneful neighbour than his fate;

Sad strife arose, for they were so cross-grained,

Instead of bearing up without debate,

That each pulled different ways with many an oath,

"Arcades ambo," id est—blackguards both.[EH]

XCIV.

Juan's companion was a Romagnole,

But bred within the march of old Ancona,

With eyes that looked into the very soul

(And other chief points of a bella donna),

Bright—and as black and burning as a coal;

And through her clear brunette complexion shone a

Great wish to please—a most attractive dower,

Especially when added to the power.

XCV.

But all that power was wasted upon him,

For Sorrow o'er each sense held stern command;

Her eye might flash on his, but found it dim:

And though thus chained, as natural her hand

Touched his, nor that—nor any handsome limb

(And she had some not easy to withstand)

Could stir his pulse, or make his faith feel brittle;

Perhaps his recent wounds might help a little.

XCVI.

No matter; we should ne'er too much inquire,

But facts are facts: no Knight could be more true,

And firmer faith no Ladye-love desire;

We will omit the proofs, save one or two:

'T is said no one in hand "can hold a fire

By thought of frosty Caucasus"[257]—but few,

I really think—yet Juan's then ordeal

Was more triumphant, and not much less real.

XCVII.

Here I might enter on a chaste description,

Having withstood temptation in my youth,[EI]

But hear that several people take exception

At the first two books having too much truth;

Therefore I'll make Don Juan leave the ship soon,

Because the publisher declares, in sooth,

Through needles' eyes it easier for the camel is

To pass, than those two cantos into families.

XCVIII.

'T is all the same to me; I'm fond of yielding,

And therefore leave them to the purer page

Of Smollett, Prior, Ariosto, Fielding,

Who say strange things for so correct an age;[258]

I once had great alacrity in wielding

My pen, and liked poetic war to wage,

And recollect the time when all this cant

Would have provoked remarks—which now it shan't.

XCIX.

As boys love rows, my boyhood liked a squabble;

But at this hour I wish to part in peace,

Leaving such to the literary rabble;

Whether my verse's fame be doomed to cease

While the right hand which wrote it still is able,

Or of some centuries to take a lease,

The grass upon my grave will grow as long,

And sigh to midnight winds, but not to song.

C.

Of poets who come down to us through distance

Of time and tongues, the foster-babes of Fame,

Life seems the smallest portion of existence;

Where twenty ages gather o'er a name,

'T is as a snowball which derives assistance

From every flake, and yet rolls on the same,

Even till an iceberg it may chance to grow;

But, after all, 't is nothing but cold snow.

CI.

And so great names are nothing more than nominal,

And love of Glory's but an airy lust,

Too often in its fury overcoming all

Who would as 't were identify their dust

From out the wide destruction, which, entombing all,

Leaves nothing till "the coming of the just"—

Save change: I've stood upon Achilles' tomb,

And heard Troy doubted;[259] Time will doubt of Rome.

CII.

The very generations of the dead

Are swept away, and tomb inherits tomb,

Until the memory of an Age is fled,

And, buried, sinks beneath its offspring's doom:

Where are the epitaphs our fathers read?

Save a few gleaned from the sepulchral gloom

Which once-named myriads nameless lie beneath,

And lose their own in universal Death.

CIII.

I canter by the spot each afternoon

Where perished in his fame the hero-boy,

Who lived too long for men, but died too soon

For human vanity, the young De Foix!

A broken pillar, not uncouthly hewn,

But which Neglect is hastening to destroy,

Records Ravenna's carnage on its face,

While weeds and ordure rankle round the base.[260]

CIV.

I pass each day where Dante's bones are laid:[261]

A little cupola, more neat than solemn,

Protects his dust, but reverence here is paid[EJ]

To the Bard's tomb, and not the Warrior's column:

The time must come, when both alike decayed,

The Chieftain's trophy, and the Poet's volume,

Will sink where lie the songs and wars of earth,

Before Pelides' death, or Homer's birth.

CV.

With human blood that column was cemented,

With human filth that column is defiled,

As if the peasant's coarse contempt were vented

To show his loathing of the spot he soiled:[EK]

Thus is the trophy used, and thus lamented

Should ever be those blood-hounds, from whose wild

Instinct of gore and glory Earth has known

Those sufferings Dante saw in Hell alone.[EL]

CVI.

Yet there will still be bards: though Fame is smoke,

Its fumes are frankincense to human thought;

And the unquiet feelings, which first woke

Song in the world, will seek what then they sought;[EM]

As on the beach the waves at last are broke,

Thus to their extreme verge the passions brought

Dash into poetry, which is but Passion,

Or, at least, was so ere it grew a fashion.

CVII.

If in the course of such a life as was

At once adventurous and contemplative,

Men who partake all passions as they pass,

Acquire the deep and bitter power to give[EN]

Their images again as in a glass,

And in such colours that they seem to live;

You may do right forbidding them to show 'em,

But spoil (I think) a very pretty poem.[262]

CVIII.

Oh! ye, who make the fortunes of all books!

Benign Ceruleans of the second sex!

Who advertise new poems by your looks,

Your "Imprimatur" will ye not annex?

What! must I go to the oblivious cooks,[EO]

Those Cornish plunderers of Parnassian wrecks?

Ah! must I then the only minstrel be,

Proscribed from tasting your Castalian tea![263]

CIX.

What! can I prove "a lion" then no more?

A ball-room bard, a foolscap, hot-press darling?

To bear the compliments of many a bore,

And sigh, "I can't get out," like Yorick's starling;[264]

Why then I'll swear, as poet Wordy swore

(Because the world won't read him, always snarling),

That Taste is gone, that Fame is but a lottery,

Drawn by the blue-coat misses of a coterie.[265]

CX.

Oh! "darkly, deeply, beautifully blue,"[266]

As some one somewhere sings about the sky,

And I, ye learnéd ladies, say of you;

They say your stockings are so—(Heaven knows why,

I have examined few pair of that hue);

Blue as the garters which serenely lie

Round the Patrician left-legs, which adorn

The festal midnight, and the levee morn.[EP]

CXI.

Yet some of you are most seraphic creatures—

But times are altered since, a rhyming lover,

You read my stanzas, and I read your features:

And—but no matter, all those things are over;

Still I have no dislike to learnéd natures,

For sometimes such a world of virtues cover;

I knew one woman of that purple school,

The loveliest, chastest, best, but—quite a fool.[267]

CXIII.

Humboldt, "the first of travellers," but not

The last, if late accounts be accurate,

Invented, by some name I have forgot,

As well as the sublime discovery's date,

An airy instrument, with which he sought

To ascertain the atmospheric state,

By measuring "the intensity of blue:"[268]

Oh, Lady Daphne! let me measure you![EQ]

CXIII.

But to the narrative:—The vessel bound

With slaves to sell off in the capital,

After the usual process, might be found

At anchor under the seraglio wall;

Her cargo, from the plague being safe and sound,

Were landed in the market,[269] one and all;

And, there, with Georgians, Russians, and Circassians,

Bought up for different purposes and passions.

CXIV.

Some went off dearly; fifteen hundred dollars

For one Circassian, a sweet girl, were given,

Warranted virgin; Beauty's brightest colours

Had decked her out in all the hues of heaven:

Her sale sent home some disappointed bawlers,

Who bade on till the hundreds reached eleven;

But when the offer went beyond, they knew

'T was for the Sultan, and at once withdrew.

CXV.

Twelve negresses from Nubia brought a price

Which the West Indian market scarce could bring—

Though Wilberforce, at last, has made it twice

What 't was ere Abolition; and the thing

Need not seem very wonderful, for Vice

Is always much more splendid than a King:

The Virtues, even the most exalted, Charity,

Are saving—Vice spares nothing for a rarity.

CXVI.

But for the destiny of this young troop,

How some were bought by Pachas, some by Jews,

How some to burdens were obliged to stoop,

And others rose to the command of crews

As renegadoes; while in hapless group,

Hoping no very old Vizier might choose,

The females stood, as one by one they picked 'em,

To make a mistress, or fourth wife, or victim:[ER]

CXVII.

All this must be reserved for further song;

Also our Hero's lot, howe'er unpleasant

(Because this Canto has become too long),[ES]

Must be postponed discreetly for the present;

I'm sensible redundancy is wrong,

But could not for the Muse of me put less in 't:

And now delay the progress of Don Juan,

Till what is called in Ossian the fifth Duan.

Written Nov. 1819. Copied January, 1820.

FOOTNOTES:

[230] {183}

["Till Pride and worse Ambition threw me down,

Warring in Heaven against Heaven's matchless King."

Paradise Lost, iv. 40, 41.]

[231]

["Time hovers o'er, impatient to destroy,

And shuts up all the passages of joy:

In vain their gifts the bounteous seasons pour,

The fruit autumnal, and the vernal flow'r;

With listless eyes the dotard views the store,

He views, and wonders that they please no more."

Johnson's Vanity of Human Wishes.]

[232] {184}

[" ... my May of Life

Is fall'n into the sere, the yellow leaf."

Macbeth, act v. sc. 3, lines 22, 23.]

[DH] Itself to that fit apathy whose deed.—[MS.]

[DI] First in the icy depths of Lethe's spring.—[MS.]

[233] [See "Introduction to the Morgante Maggiore," Poetical Works, 1901, iv. 280.]

[DJ] Pulci being Father—.—[MS. Alternative reading.]

[234] {185} ["Cum canerem reges et prælia, Cynthius aurem Vellit, et admonuit." Virgil, Ecl. vi. lines 3, 4.]

[DK] {186}

—— from its mother's knee

When its last weaning draught is drained for ever,

The child divided—it were less to see,

Than these two from each other torn apart.—[MS.]

[235] [See Herodotus (Cleobis and Biton), i. 31. The sentiment is in a fragment of Menander.
Ὅν οἱ θεοὶ φιλοῦσιν ἀποθνήσκει νέος
or
Ὅν γὰρ φιλεῖ θεὸς  ἀποθνήσκει νέος.

Menandri at Philomenis reliquiæ, edidit Augustus Meineke, p. 48.

See Letters, 1898, ii. 22, note 1. Byron applied the saying to Allegra in a letter to Sir Walter Scott, dated May 4, 1822, Letters, 1901, vi. 57.]

[236] [Compare Childe Harold, Canto II. stanza xcvi. line 7. Compare, too, Young's Night Thoughts ("The Complaint," Night I. ed. 1825, p. 5)]

[237] {187}[Compare Swift's "little language" in his letter to Stella: Podefar, for instance, which is supposed to stand for "Poor dear foolish rogue," and Ppt., which meant "Poor pretty thing."—See The Journal of Stella, edited by G.A. Aitken, 1901, xxxv. note 1, and "Journal: March, 1710-11," 165, note 2.]

[DL]

For theirs were buoyant spirits, which would bound

'Gainst common failings, etc.—[MS.]

[238] {188}[The reference may be to Coleridge's Kubla Khan, which, to Medwin's wonderment, "delighted" Byron (Conversations, 1824, p. 264). De Quincy's Confessions of an English Opium Eater appeared in the London Magazine, October, November, 1821, after Cantos III., IV., V., of Don Juan were published. But, perhaps, he was contrasting the "simpler blisses" of Juan and Haidée with Shelley's mystical affinities and divagations.]

[DM] —— had set their hearts a bleeding.—[MS.]

[239] {190}

["The shadowy desert, unfrequented woods,

I better brook than flourishing peopled towns:

There can I sit alone, unseen of any,

And to the nightingale's complaining notes

Tune my distresses, and record, my woes."

Two Gentlemen of Verona, act v. sc. 4, lines 2-6.]

[DN] {191}Called social, where all Vice and Hatred are.—[MS.]

[DO] Moved with her dream——.—[MS.]

[DP]

Strange state of being!—for 't is still to be—

And who can know all false what then we see?—[MS.]

[240] {192}[Compare the description of the "spacious cave," in The Island, Canto IV. lines 121, sq., Poetical Works, 1901, v. 629, note 1.]

[DQ]—— methought.—[MS. Alternative reading.]

[241] {195}[The reader will observe a curious mark of propinquity which the poet notices, with respect to the hands of the father and daughter. Lord Byron, we suspect, is indebted for the first hint of this to Ali Pacha, who, by the bye, is the original of Lambro; for, when his lordship was introduced, with his friend Hobhouse, to that agreeable mannered tyrant, the Vizier said that he knew he was the Megalos Anthropos (i.e. the great Man), by the smallness of his ears and hands.—Galt. See Byron's letter to his mother, November 12, 1809, Letters, 1898, i. 251.]

[DR]

And if I did my duty as thou hast,

This hour were thine, and thy young minions last.—[MS.]

[DS] {196}Till further orders should his doom assign.—[MS.]

[DT] Loving and loved—.—[MS.]

[DU] {197}

But thou, sweet fury of the fiery rill,

Makest on the liver a still worse attack;

Besides, thy price is something dearer still.—[MS.]

[242] ["As squire Sullen says, '\My head aches consumedly,' 'Scrub, bring me a dram!' Drank some Imola wine, and some punch!"—Extracts from a Diary, February 25, 1821, Letters, 1901, v. 209. For rack or "arrack" punch, see Thackeray's Vanity Fair, A Novel without a Hero, chap. vi. ed. 1892, p. 44.]

[243] {198}["At Fas [Fez] the houses of the great and wealthy have, within-side, spacious courts, adorned with sumptuous galleries, fountains, basons of fine marble, and fish-ponds, shaded with orange, lemon, pomegranate, and fig trees, abounding with fruit, and ornamented with roses, hyacinths, jasmine, violets, and orange flowers, emitting a delectable fragrance."—Account of the Empire of Marocco and Suez, by James Grey Jackson, 1811, pp. 69, 70.]

[DV]

Beauty and Passion were the natural dower

Of Haidée's mother, but her climate's force

Lay at her heart, though sleeping at the source.

or, But in her large eye lay deep Passion's force,

Like to a lion sleeping by a source.

or, But in her large eye lay deep Passion's force,

As sleeps a lion by a river's source.—[MS.]

[244] [Compare Manfred, act iii. sc. 1, line 128, Poetical Works, 1901, iv. 125.]

[DW] {199}

The blood gushed from her lips, and ears, and eyes:

Those eyes, so beautiful—beheld no more.—[MS.]

[245] This is no very uncommon effect of the violence of conflicting and different passions. The Doge Francis Foscari, on his deposition in 1457, hearing the bells of St. Mark announce the election of his successor, "mourut subitement d'une hémorragie causée par une veine qui s'éclata dans sa poitrine" [see Sismondi, 1815, x. 46, and Daru, 1821, ii. 536; see, too, The Two Foscari, act v. sc. i, line 306, and Introduction to the Two Foscari, Poetical Works, 1901, v. 118, 193], at the age of eighty years, when "Who would have thought the old man had so much blood in him?" (Macbeth, act v. sc. 1, lines 34-36.) Before I was sixteen years of age I was witness to a melancholy instance of the same effect of mixed passions upon a young person, who, however, did not die in consequence, at that time, but fell a victim some years afterwards to a seizure of the same kind, arising from causes intimately connected with agitation of mind.

[246] {200}[The view of the Venus of Medici instantly suggests the lines in the "Seasons" [the description of "Musidora bathing" in Summer]—

" ... With wild surprise,

As if to marble struck, devoid of sense,

A stupid moment motionless she stood:

So stands the statue that enchants the world."

Hobhouse.

A still closer parallel to this stanza, and to Childe Harold, Canto IV. stanzas xlix., cxl., cxli., clx., clxi., is to be found in Thomson's Liberty, pt. iv. lines 131-206, where the "Farnese Hercules," the "Dying Gladiator," the "Venus of Medici," and the "Laocoon" group, are commemorated as typical works of art.]

[DX] Distinct from life, as being still the same.—[MS.]

[DY] {202}—working slow.—[MS.]

[DZ] Have dawned a child of beauty, though of sin.—[MS.]

[247]

[" ... Duncan is in his grave:

After life's fitful fever he sleeps well."

Macbeth, act iii. sc. 2., lines 22, 23.]

[EA] {203}

No stone is there to read, nor tongue to say,

No dirge—save when arise the stormy seas.—[MS.]

[248] ["But now I am cabined, cribbed," etc. Macbeth, act iii. sc. 4, line 24.]

[249] {204}[Jacob Bryant (1715-1804) published his Dissertation concerning the War of Troy, etc., in 1796. See The Bride of Abydos, Canto II. lines 510, sq., Poetical Works, 1900, iii. 179, note 1. See, too, Extracts from a Diary, January 11, 1821, Letters, 1901, v. 165, 166, "I have stood upon that plain [of Troy] daily, for more than a month, in 1810; and if anything diminished my pleasure, it was that the blackguard Bryant had impugned its veracity." Hobhouse, in his Travels in Albania, 1858, ii. 93, sq., discusses at length the identity of the barrows of the Troad with the tumuli of Achilles, Ajax, and Protesilaus, and refutes Bryant's arguments against the identity of Cape Janissary and the Sigean promontory.

[EB]

All heroes | { | who alive perhaps
if still alive | } | .—[MS. Alternative reading]

[EC]

— | { | and mountain-bounded
and mountain-outlined | } | plain.—[MS. Alternative reading]

[250] ["The whole region was, in a manner, in possession of the Salsette's crew, parties of whom, in their white summer dresses, might be seen scattered over the plains collecting the tortoises, which swarm on the sides of the rivulets, and are found under every furze-bush."—Travels in Albania, 1858, ii. 116. See, too, for mention of "hundreds of tortoises" falling "from the overhanging branches, and thick underwood," into the waters of the Mender, Travels, etc., by E.D. Clarke, 1812, Part II. sect. i. p. 96.]

[ED] —— and land tortoise crawls.—[MS. Alternative reading.]

[EE] {205}—their learned researches bear.—[MS. Alternative reading.]

[251] This is a fact. A few years ago a man engaged a company for some foreign theatre, embarked them at an Italian port, and carrying them to Algiers, sold them all. One of the women, returned from her captivity, I heard sing, by a strange coincidence, in Rossini's opera of L'Italiana in Algieri, at Venice, in the beginning of 1817.

[We have reason to believe that the following, which we take from the MS. journal of a highly respectable traveller, is a more correct account: "In 1812 a Signor Guariglia induced several young persons of both sexes—none of them exceeding fifteen years of age—to accompany him on an operatic excursion; part to form the opera, and part the ballet. He contrived to get them on board a vessel, which took them to Janina, where he sold them for the basest purposes. Some died from the effect of the climate, and some from suffering. Among the few who returned were a Signor Molinari, and a female dancer named Bonfiglia, who afterwards became the wife of Crespi, the tenor singer. The wretch who so basely sold them was, when Lord Byron resided at Venice, employed as capo de' vestarj, or head tailor, at the Fenice."—Maria Graham (Lady Callcot). Ed. 1832.]

[252] {206}[A comic singer in the opera buffa. The Italians, however, distinguish the buffo cantante, which requires good singing, from the buffo comico, in which there is more acting.—Ed. 1832.]

[253] {207}[The figuranti are those dancers of a ballet who do not dance singly, but many together, and serve to fill up the background during the exhibition of individual performers. They correspond to the chorus in the opera.—Maria Graham.]

[EF] To help the ladies in their dress and lacing.—[MS.]

[254] It is strange that it should be the Pope and the Sultan, who are the chief encouragers of this branch of trade—women being prohibited as singers at St. Peter's, and not deemed trustworthy as guardians of the harem.

["Scarcely a soul of them can read. Pacchierotti was one of the best informed of the castrati ... Marchesi is so grossly ignorant that he wrote the word opera, opperra, but Nature has been so bountiful to the animal, that his ignorance and insolence were forgotten the moment he sang."—Venice, etc., by a Lady of Rank, 1824, ii. 86.]

[255] {208}[The N. Engl. Dict. cites Bunyan, Walpole, Fielding, Miss Austen, and Dickens as authorities for the plural "was." See art. "be." Here, as elsewhere, Byron wrote as he spoke.]

[EG] He never shows his feelings, but his teeth.—[MS. Alternative reading.]

[256] ["Our firman arrived from Constantinople on the 30th of April (1810)."—Travels in Albania, 1858, ii. 186.]

[EH] {209}

That each pulled, different ways—and waxing rough,

Had cuffed each other, only for the cuff.—[MS.]

[257] {210}

["O, who can hold a fire in his hand,

By thinking on the frosty Caucasus?"

Richard II., act i. sc. 3, lines 294, 295.]

[EI] Having had some experience in my youth.—[MS. erased.]

[258] ["Don Juan will be known, by and by, for what it is intended—a Satire on abuses in the present states of society, and not an eulogy of vice. It may be now and then voluptuous:—I can't help that. Ariosto is worse. Smollett (see Lord Strutwell in vol. 2nd of R[oderick] R[andom][1793, pp. 119-127]) ten times worse; and Fielding no better."—Letter to Murray, December 25, 1822, Letters, 1901, vi. 155, 156.]

[259] {211} [Vide ante, p. 204, note 1. "It seems hardly to admit of doubt, that the plain of Anatolia, watered by the Mender, and backed by a mountainous ridge, of which Kazdaghy is the summit, offers the precise territory alluded to by Homer. The long controversy, excited by Mr. Bryant's publication, and since so vehemently agitated, would probably never have existed, had it not been for the erroneous maps of the country which, even to this hour, disgrace our geographical knowledge of that part of Asia."—Travels, etc., by E.D. Clarke, 1812, Part II. sect, i. p. 78.]

[260] {212}The pillar which records the battle of Ravenna is about two miles from the city, on the opposite side of the river to the road towards Forli. Gaston de Foix [(1489-1512) Duc de Nemours, nephew of Louis XII.], who gained the battle, was killed in it: there fell on both sides twenty thousand men. The present state of the pillar and its site is described in the text.

[Beyond the Porta Sisi, about two miles from Ravenna, on the banks of the Ronco, is a square pillar (La Colonna de Francesi), erected in 1557 by Pietro Cesi, president of Romagna, as a memorial of the battle gained by the combined army of Louis XII. and the Duke of Ferrara over the troops of Julius II. and the King of Spain, April 11 1512.—Handbook of Northern Italy, p. 548.]

[261] [Compare Childe Harold, Canto IV. stanza lvii. line i, Poetical Works, 1899, ii. 371, note i. See, too, Preface to the Prophecy of Dante, ibid., iv. 243.]

[EJ] Protects his tomb, but greater care is paid.—[MS.]

[EK] {213}

With human ordure is it now defiled,

As if the peasant's scorn this mode invented

To show his loathing of the thing he soiled.—[MS.]

[EL] Those sufferings once reserved for Hell alone.—[MS.]

[EM]

Its fumes are frankincense; and were there nought

Even of this vapour, still the chilling yoke

Of silence would not long be borne by Thought.—[MS.]

[EN]

I have drunk deep of passions as they pass,

And dearly bought the bitter power to give.—[MS.]

[262] [See, for instance, Wilson's review of Don Juan, in Blackwood's Edinburgh Magazine, August, 1819, vol. v. p. 512, sq.: "To confess ... to his Maker, and to weep over in secret agonies the wildest and most fantastic transgressions of heart and mind, is the part of a conscious sinner, in whom sin has not become the sole principle of life and action.... But to lay bare to the eye of man—and of woman—all the hidden convulsions of a wicked spirit," etc.]

[EO] {214}

What! must I go with Wordy to the cooks?

Read—were it but your Grandmother's to vex—

And let me not the only minstrel be

Cut off from tasting your Castalian tea.—[MS.]

[263] [Compare—

"I leave them to their daily 'tea is ready,'

Snug coterie, and literary lady."

Beppo, stanza lxxvi. lines 7, 8, Poetical Works, 1901, iv. 184, note.]

[264] [The caged starling, by its repeated cry, "I can't get out! I can't get out!" cured Yorick of his sentimental yearnings for imprisonment in the Bastille. See Sterne's Sentimental Journey, ed. 1804, pp. 100-106.]

[265] [In his Essay, Supplement to the Preface (Poems by William Wordsworth, ed. 1820, iii. 315-348), Wordsworth maintains that the appreciation of great poetry is a plant of slow growth, that immediate recognition is a mark of inferiority, or is to be accounted for by the presence of adventitious qualities: "So strange, indeed, are the obliquities of admiration, that they whose opinions are much influenced by authority will often be tempted to think that there are no fixed principles in human nature for this art to rest upon.... Away, then, with the senseless iteration of the word popular! ... The voice that issues from this spirit [of human knowledge] is that Vox Populi which the Deity inspires. Foolish must he be who can mistake for this a local acclamation, or a transitory outcry—transitory though it be for years, local though from a Nation. Still more lamentable is his error who can believe that there is anything of divine infallibility in this clamour of that small though loud portion of the community ever governed by factitious influence, which under the name of the Public, passes itself upon the unthinking for the People." Naturally enough Byron regarded this pronouncement as a taunt if not as a challenge. Wordsworth's noble appeal from a provincial to an imperial authority, from the present to the future, is not strengthened by the obvious reference to the popularity of contemporaries.]

[266] {215}[Southey's Madoc in Wales, Poetical Works, Part I. Canto V. Ed. 1838, v. 39.]

[EP]

Not having looked at many of that hue,

Nor garters—save those of the "honi soit"—which lie

Round the Patrician legs which walk about,

The ornaments of levee and of rout.—[M.S.]

[267] [Probably Lady Charlemont. See "Journal," November 22, 1813.]

[268] {216}[The cyanometer, an instrument for ascertaining the intensity of the blue colour of the sky, was invented by Horace Bénédict de Saussure (1740-1799); see his Essai sur l'Hygrométrie. F.H. Alexander von Humboldt (1769-1859) "made great use of his instrument on his voyages, and ascertained by the colour the degree of blueness, the accumulation and the nature of the non-transparent exhalations of the air."—Alexander von Humboldt, by Professor Klencke, translated by Juliette Bauer, 1852, pp. 45, 46.]

[EQ]

I'll back a London "Bas" against Peru.

or, I'll bet some pair of stocking beat Peru.

or, And so, old Sotheby, we'll measure you.—[MS.]

[269] ["The slave-market is a quadrangle, surrounded by a covered gallery, and ranges of small and separate apartments." Here the poor wretches sit in a melancholy posture. "Before they cheapen 'em, they turn 'em about from this side to that, survey 'em from top to bottom.... Such of 'em, both men and women, to whom Dame Nature has been niggardly of her charms, are set apart for the vilest services: but such girls as have youth and beauty pass their time well enough.... The retailers of this human ware are the Jews, who take good care of their slaves' education, that they may sell the better: their choicest they keep at home, and there you must go, if you would have better than ordinary; for 'tis here, as 'tis in markets for horses, the handsomest don't always appear, but are kept within doors."—A Voyage into the Levant, by M. Tournefort, 1741, ii. 198, 199. See, too, for the description of the sale of two Circassians and one Georgian, Voyage de Vienne à Belgrade, ... par N.E. Kleeman, 1780, pp. 141, 142. The "lowest offer for the prize Circassian was 4000 piastres."]

[ER]

The females stood, till chosen each as victim

To the soft oath of "Ana seing Siktum!"[*]—[MS.]

[* If the Turkish words are correctly given, "the oath" may be an imprecation on "your mother's" chastity.]

[ES] For fear the Canto should become too long.—[MS.]

Canto VII[364]

I.

O Love! O Glory! what are ye who fly

Around us ever, rarely to alight?

There's not a meteor in the polar sky

Of such transcendent and more fleeting flight.

Chill, and chained to cold earth, we lift on high

Our eyes in search of either lovely light;

A thousand and a thousand colours they

Assume, then leave us on our freezing way.

II.

And such as they are, such my present tale is,

A nondescript and ever-varying rhyme,

A versified Aurora Borealis,

Which flashes o'er a waste and icy clime.

When we know what all are, we must bewail us,

But ne'ertheless I hope it is no crime

To laugh at all things—for I wish to know

What, after all, are all things—but a show?

III.

They accuse me—Me—the present writer of

The present poem—of—I know not what—

A tendency to under-rate and scoff

At human power and virtue, and all that;[365]

And this they say in language rather rough.

Good God! I wonder what they would be at!

I say no more than hath been said in Danté's

Verse, and by Solomon and by Cervantes;

IV.

By Swift, by Machiavel, by Rochefoucault,

By Fénélon, by Luther, and by Plato;[HH]

By Tillotson, and Wesley, and Rousseau,

Who knew this life was not worth a potato.

'T is not their fault, nor mine, if this be so,—

For my part, I pretend not to be Cato,

Nor even Diogenes.—We live and die,

But which is best, you know no more than I.

V.

Socrates said, our only knowledge was[366]

"To know that nothing could be known;" a pleasant

Science enough, which levels to an ass

Each man of wisdom, future, past, or present.

Newton (that proverb of the mind), alas!

Declared, with all his grand discoveries recent,

That he himself felt only "like a youth

Picking up shells by the great ocean—Truth."[HI][367]

VI.

Ecclesiastes said, "that all is vanity"—

Most modern preachers say the same, or show it

By their examples of true Christianity:

In short, all know, or very soon may know it;

And in this scene of all-confessed inanity,

By Saint, by Sage, by Preacher, and by Poet,

Must I restrain me, through the fear of strife,

From holding up the nothingness of Life?[HJ]

VII.

Dogs, or men!—for I flatter you[368] in saying

That ye are dogs—your betters far—ye may

Read, or read not, what I am now essaying

To show ye what ye are in every way.

As little as the moon stops for the baying

Of wolves, will the bright Muse withdraw one ray

From out her skies—then howl your idle wrath!

While she still silvers o'er your gloomy path.

VIII.

"Fierce loves and faithless wars"—I am not sure

If this be the right reading—'t is no matter;

The fact's about the same, I am secure;

I sing them both, and am about to batter

A town which did a famous siege endure,

And was beleaguered both by land and water

By Souvaroff,[369] or Anglicè Suwarrow,

Who loved blood as an alderman loves marrow.

IX.

The fortress is called Ismail, and is placed

Upon the Danube's left branch and left bank,[370]

With buildings in the Oriental taste,

But still a fortress of the foremost rank,

Or was at least, unless 't is since defaced,

Which with your conquerors is a common prank:

It stands some eighty versts from the high sea,

And measures round of toises thousands three.[371]

X.

Within the extent of this fortification

A borough is comprised along the height

Upon the left, which from its loftier station

Commands the city, and upon its site

A Greek had raised around this elevation

A quantity of palisades upright,

So placed as to impede the fire of those

Who held the place, and to assist the foe's.[372]

XI.

This circumstance may serve to give a notion

Of the high talents of this new Vauban:

But the town ditch below was deep as Ocean,

The rampart higher than you'd wish to hang:

But then there was a great want of precaution

(Prithee, excuse this engineering slang),

Nor work advanced, nor covered way was there,[373]

To hint, at least, "Here is no thoroughfare."

XII.

But a stone bastion, with a narrow gorge,

And walls as thick as most skulls born as yet;

Two batteries, cap-à-pie, as our St. George,

Casemated[374] one, and t' other "a barbette,"[375]

Of Danube's bank took formidable charge;

While two-and-twenty cannon duly set

Rose over the town's right side, in bristling tier,

Forty feet high, upon a cavalier.[376]

XIII.

But from the river the town's open quite,

Because the Turks could never be persuaded

A Russian vessel e'er would heave in sight;[377]

And such their creed was till they were invaded,

When it grew rather late to set things right:

But as the Danube could not well be waded,

They looked upon the Muscovite flotilla,

And only shouted, "Allah!" and "Bis Millah!"

XIV.

The Russians now were ready to attack;

But oh, ye goddesses of War and Glory!

How shall I spell the name of each Cossacque

Who were immortal, could one tell their story?

Alas! what to their memory can lack?

Achilles' self was not more grim and gory

Than thousands of this new and polished nation,

Whose names want nothing but—pronunciation.

XV.

Still I'll record a few, if but to increase

Our euphony: there was Strongenoff, and Strokonoff,

Meknop, Serge Lwow, Arséniew of modern Greece,

And Tschitsshakoff, and Roguenoff, and Chokenoff,[378]

And others of twelve consonants apiece;

And more might be found out, if I could poke enough

Into gazettes; but Fame (capricious strumpet),

It seems, has got an ear as well as trumpet,

XVI.

And cannot tune those discords of narration,[HK]

Which may be names at Moscow, into rhyme;

Yet there were several worth commemoration,

As e'er was virgin of a nuptial chime;

Soft words, too, fitted for the peroration

Of Londonderry drawling against time,

Ending in "ischskin," "ousckin," "iffskchy," "ouski,"

Of whom we can insert but Rousamouski,[379]

XVII.

Scherematoff and Chrematoff, Koklophti,

Koclobski, Kourakin, and Mouskin Pouskin,

All proper men of weapons, as e'er scoffed high[380]

Against a foe, or ran a sabre through skin:

Little cared they for Mahomet or Mufti,

Unless to make their kettle-drums a new skin

Out of their hides, if parchment had grown dear,

And no more handy substitute been near.

XVIII.

Then there were foreigners of much renown,

Of various nations, and all volunteers;

Not fighting for their country or its crown,

But wishing to be one day brigadiers;

Also to have the sacking of a town;—

A pleasant thing to young men at their years.

'Mongst them were several Englishmen of pith,

Sixteen called Thomson, and nineteen named Smith.

XIX.

Jack Thomson and Bill Thomson;—all the rest

Had been called "Jemmy," after the great bard;

I don't know whether they had arms or crest,

But such a godfather's as good a card.

Three of the Smiths were Peters; but the best

Amongst them all, hard blows to inflict or ward,

Was he, since so renowned "in country quarters

At Halifax;"[381] but now he served the Tartars.

XX.

The rest were Jacks and Gills and Wills and Bills,

But when I've added that the elder Jack Smith

Was born in Cumberland among the hills,

And that his father was an honest blacksmith,

I've said all I know of a name that fills

Three lines of the despatch in taking "Schmacksmith,"

A village of Moldavia's waste, wherein

He fell, immortal in a bulletin.

XXI.

I wonder (although Mars no doubt's a god I

Praise) if a man's name in a bulletin

May make up for a bullet in his body?

I hope this little question is no sin,

Because, though I am but a simple noddy,

I think one Shakespeare puts the same thought in

The mouth of some one in his plays so doting,

Which many people pass for wits by quoting.[382]

XXII.

Then there were Frenchmen, gallant, young, and gay;

But I'm too great a patriot to record

Their Gallic names upon a glorious day;

I'd rather tell ten lies than say a word

Of truth;—such truths are treason; they betray

Their country; and as traitors are abhorred,

Who name the French in English, save to show

How Peace should make John Bull the Frenchman's foe.

XXIII.

The Russians, having built two batteries on

An isle near Ismail, had two ends in view;

The first was to bombard it, and knock down

The public buildings and the private too,

No matter what poor souls might be undone:[HL]

The city's shape suggested this, 't is true,

Formed like an amphitheatre—each dwelling

Presented a fine mark to throw a shell in.[383]

XXIV.

The second object was to profit by

The moment of the general consternation,

To attack the Turk's flotilla, which lay nigh

Extremely tranquil, anchored at its station:

But a third motive was as probably

To frighten them into capitulation;[384]

A phantasy which sometimes seizes warriors,

Unless they are game as bull-dogs and fox-terriers.[HM]

XXV.

A habit rather blameable, which is

That of despising those we combat with,

Common in many cases, was in this

The cause[385] of killing Tchitchitzkoff and Smith—

One of the valorous "Smiths" whom we shall miss

Out of those nineteen who late rhymed to "pith;"

But 't is a name so spread o'er "Sir" and "Madam,"

That one would think the first who bore it "Adam."

XXVI.

The Russian batteries were incomplete,

Because they were constructed in a hurry;[386]

Thus the same cause which makes a verse want feet,

And throws a cloud o'er Longman and John Murray,

When the sale of new books is not so fleet

As they who print them think is necessary,

May likewise put off for a time what story

Sometimes calls "Murder," and at others "Glory."

XXVII.

Whether it was their engineer's stupidity,

Their haste or waste, I neither know nor care,

Or some contractor's personal cupidity,

Saving his soul by cheating in the ware

Of homicide, but there was no solidity

In the new batteries erected there;

They either missed, or they were never missed,

And added greatly to the missing list.

XXVIII.

A sad miscalculation about distance

Made all their naval matters incorrect;

Three fireships lost their amiable existence

Before they reached a spot to take effect;

The match was lit too soon, and no assistance

Could remedy this lubberly defect;

They blew up in the middle of the river,

While, though 't was dawn, the Turks slept fast as ever.[387]

XXIX.

At seven they rose, however, and surveyed

The Russ flotilla getting under way;

'T was nine, when still advancing undismayed,

Within a cable's length their vessels lay

Off Ismail, and commenced a cannonade,

Which was returned with interest, I may say,

And by a fire of musketry and grape,

And shells and shot of every size and shape.[388]

XXX.

For six hours bore they without intermission

The Turkish fire, and, aided by their own

Land batteries, worked their guns with great precision;

At length they found mere cannonade alone

By no means would produce the town's submission,

And made a signal to retreat at one.

One bark blew up, a second near the works

Running aground, was taken by the Turks.[389]

XXXI.

The Moslem, too, had lost both ships and men;

But when they saw the enemy retire,

Their Delhis[390] manned some boats, and sailed again,

And galled the Russians with a heavy fire,

And tried to make a landing on the main;

But here the effect fell short of their desire:

Count Damas drove them back into the water

Pell-mell, and with a whole gazette of slaughter.[391]

XXXII.

"If" (says the historian here) "I could report

All that the Russians did upon this day,

I think that several volumes would fall short,

And I should still have many things to say;"[392]

And so he says no more—but pays his court

To some distinguished strangers in that fray;

The Prince de Ligne, and Langeron, and Damas,

Names great as any that the roll of Fame has.[393]

XXXIII.

This being the case, may show us what Fame is:

For out of these three "preux Chevaliers," how

Many of common readers give a guess

That such existed? (and they may live now

For aught we know.) Renown's all hit or miss;

There's fortune even in Fame, we must allow.

'T is true, the Memoirs of the Prince de Ligne[394]

Have half withdrawn from him Oblivion's screen.

XXXIV.

But here are men who fought in gallant actions

As gallantly as ever heroes fought,

But buried in the heap of such transactions

Their names are rarely found, nor often sought.

Thus even good fame may suffer sad contractions,

And is extinguished sooner than she ought:

Of all our modern battles, I will bet

You can't repeat nine names from each Gazette.

XXXV.

In short, this last attack, though rich in glory,

Showed that somewhere, somehow, there was a fault,

And Admiral Ribas[395] (known in Russian story)

Most strongly recommended an assault;

In which he was opposed by young and hoary,

Which made a long debate; but I must halt,

For if I wrote down every warrior's speech,

I doubt few readers e'er would mount the breach.

XXXVI.

There was a man, if that he was a man,

Not that his manhood could be called in question,

For had he not been Hercules, his span

Had been as short in youth as indigestion

Made his last illness, when, all worn and wan,

He died beneath a tree, as much unblest on

The soil of the green province he had wasted,

As e'er was locust on the land it blasted.

XXXVII.

This was Potemkin[396]—a great thing in days

When homicide and harlotry made great;

If stars and titles could entail long praise,

His glory might half equal his estate.

This fellow, being six foot high, could raise

A kind of phantasy proportionate

In the then Sovereign of the Russian people,

Who measured men as you would do a steeple.

XXXVIII.

While things were in abeyance, Ribas sent

A courier to the Prince, and he succeeded

In ordering matters after his own bent;

I cannot tell the way in which he pleaded,

But shortly he had cause to be content.

In the mean time, the batteries proceeded,

And fourscore cannon on the Danube's border

Were briskly fired and answered in due order.[397]

XXXIX.

But on the thirteenth, when already part

Of the troops were embarked, the siege to raise,

A courier on the spur inspired new heart

Into all panters for newspaper praise,[HN]

As well as dilettanti in War's art,

By his despatches (couched in pithy phrase)

Announcing the appointment of that lover of

Battles to the command, Field-Marshal Souvaroff.[398]

XL.

The letter of the Prince to the same Marshal

Was worthy of a Spartan, had the cause

Been one to which a good heart could be partial—

Defence of freedom, country, or of laws;

But as it was mere lust of Power to o'er-arch all

With its proud brow, it merits slight applause,

Save for its style, which said, all in a trice,

"You will take Ismail at whatever price."[399]

XLI.

"Let there be Light! said God, and there was Light!"

"Let there be Blood!" says man, and there's a sea!

The fiat of this spoiled child of the Night

(For Day ne'er saw his merits) could decree

More evil in an hour, than thirty bright

Summers could renovate, though they should be

Lovely as those which ripened Eden's fruit;

For War cuts up not only branch, but root.

XLII.

Our friends, the Turks, who with loud "Allahs" now

Began to signalise the Russ retreat,[400]

Were damnably mistaken; few are slow

In thinking that their enemy is beat,[401]

(Or beaten, if you insist on grammar, though

I never think about it in a heat,)

But here I say the Turks were much mistaken,

Who hating hogs, yet wished to save their bacon.

XLIII.

For, on the sixteenth, at full gallop, drew

In sight two horsemen, who were deemed Cossacques

For some time, till they came in nearer view:

They had but little baggage at their backs,

For there were but three shirts between the two;

But on they rode upon two Ukraine hacks,

Till, in approaching, were at length descried

In this plain pair, Suwarrow and his guide.[402]

XLIV.

"Great joy to London now!" says some great fool,

When London had a grand illumination,

Which to that bottle-conjuror, John Bull,

Is of all dreams the first hallucination;

So that the streets of coloured lamps are full,

That sage (said John) surrenders at discretion[HO]

His purse, his soul, his sense, and even his nonsense,

To gratify, like a huge moth, this one sense.

XLV.

'T is strange that he should further "Damn his eyes,"

For they are damned; that once all-famous oath

Is to the Devil now no further prize,

Since John has lately lost the use of both.

Debt he calls Wealth, and taxes Paradise;

And Famine, with her gaunt and bony growth,

Which stare him in the face, he won't examine,

Or swears that Ceres hath begotten Famine.

XLVI.

But to the tale;—great joy unto the camp!

To Russian, Tartar, English, French, Cossacque,

O'er whom Suwarrow shone like a gas lamp,

Presaging a most luminous attack;

Or like a wisp along the marsh so damp,

Which leads beholders on a boggy walk,

He flitted to and fro a dancing light,

Which all who saw it followed, wrong or right.

XLVII.

But, certes, matters took a different face;

There was enthusiasm and much applause,

The fleet and camp saluted with great grace,

And all presaged good fortune to their cause.

Within a cannot-shot length of the place

They drew, constructed ladders, repaired flaws

In former works, made new, prepared fascines,

And all kinds of benevolent machines.

XLVIII.

'T is thus the spirit of a single mind

Makes that of multitudes take one direction,

As roll the waters to the breathing wind,

Or roams the herd beneath the bull's protection;

Or as a little dog will lead the blind,

Or a bell-wether form the flock's connection

By tinkling sounds, when they go forth to victual;

Such is the sway of your great men o'er little.

XLIX.

The whole camp rung with joy; you would have thought

That they were going to a marriage feast

(This metaphor, I think, holds good as aught,

Since there is discord after both at least):

There was not now a luggage boy but sought

Danger and spoil with ardour much increased;

And why? because a little—odd—old man,

Stripped to his shirt, was come to lead the van.

L.

But so it was; and every preparation

Was made with all alacrity: the first

Detachment of three columns took its station,

And waited but the signal's voice to burst

Upon the foe: the second's ordination

Was also in three columns, with a thirst

For Glory gaping o'er a sea of Slaughter:

The third, in columns two, attacked by water.[403]

LI.

New batteries were erected, and was held

A general council, in which Unanimity,

That stranger to most councils, here prevailed,[404]

As sometimes happens in a great extremity;[HP]

And every difficulty being dispelled,

Glory began to dawn with due sublimity,[HQ]

While Souvaroff, determined to obtain it,

Was teaching his recruits to use the bayonet.[405]

LII.

It is an actual fact, that he, commander

In chief, in proper person deigned to drill

The awkward squad, and could afford to squander

His time, a corporal's duty to fulfil;

Just as you'd break a sucking salamander

To swallow flame, and never take it ill:[HR]

He showed them how to mount a ladder (which

Was not like Jacob's) or to cross a ditch.[406]

LIII.

Also he dressed up, for the nonce, fascines

Like men with turbans, scimitars, and dirks,

And made them charge with bayonet these machines,

By way of lesson against actual Turks;[407]

And when well practised in these mimic scenes,

He judged them proper to assail the works,—

(At which your wise men sneered in phrases witty),[HS]

He made no answer—but he took the city.

LIV.

Most things were in this posture on the eve

Of the assault, and all the camp was in

A stern repose; which you would scarce conceive;

Yet men resolved to dash through thick and thin

Are very silent when they once believe

That all is settled:—there was little din,

For some were thinking of their home and friends,

And others of themselves and latter ends.[HT]

LV.

Suwarrow chiefly was on the alert,

Surveying, drilling, ordering, jesting, pondering;

For the man was, we safely may assert,

A thing to wonder at beyond most wondering;

Hero, buffoon, half-demon, and half-dirt,

Praying, instructing, desolating, plundering—Now

Mars, now Momus—and when bent to storm

A fortress, Harlequin in uniform.[408]

LVI.

The day before the assault, while upon drill—

For this great conqueror played the corporal—

Some Cossacques, hovering like hawks round a hill,

Had met a party towards the Twilight's fall,

One of whom spoke their tongue—or well or ill,

'T was much that he was understood at all;

But whether from his voice, or speech, or manner,

They found that he had fought beneath their banner.

LVII.

Whereon immediately at his request

They brought him and his comrades to head-quarters;

Their dress was Moslem, but you might have guessed

That these were merely masquerading Tartars,

And that beneath each Turkish-fashioned vest

Lurked Christianity—which sometimes barters

Her inward grace for outward show, and makes

It difficult to shun some strange mistakes.

LVIII.

Suwarrow, who was standing in his shirt

Before a company of Calmucks, drilling,

Exclaiming, fooling, swearing at the inert,

And lecturing on the noble art of killing,—

For deeming human clay but common dirt

This great philosopher was thus instilling

His maxims,[409] which to martial comprehension

Proved death in battle equal to a pension;—

LIX.

Suwarrow, when he saw this company

Of Cossacques and their prey, turned round and cast

Upon them his slow brow and piercing eye:—

"Whence come ye?"—"From Constantinople last,

Captives just now escaped," was the reply.

"What are ye?"—"What you see us." Briefly passed

This dialogue; for he who answered knew

To whom he spoke, and made his words but few.

LX.

"Your names?"—"Mine's Johnson, and my comrade's Juan;

The other two are women, and the third

Is neither man nor woman." The Chief threw on

The party a slight glance, then said, "I have heard

Your name before, the second is a new one:

To bring the other three here was absurd:

But let that pass:—I think I have heard your name

In the Nikolaiew regiment?"—"The same."

LXI.

"You served at Widdin?"—"Yes."—"You led the attack?"

"I did."—"What next?"—"I really hardly know"—

"You were the first i' the breach?"—"I was not slack

At least to follow those who might be so"—

"What followed?"—"A shot laid me on my back,

And I became a prisoner to the foe"—

"You shall have vengeance, for the town surrounded

Is twice as strong as that where you were wounded.

LXII.

"Where will you serve?"—"Where'er you please."—"I know

You like to be the hope of the forlorn,

And doubtless would be foremost on the foe

After the hardships you've already borne.

And this young fellow—say what can he do?

He with the beardless chin and garments torn?"—

"Why, General, if he hath no greater fault

In War than Love, he had better lead the assault"—

LXIII.

"He shall if that he dare." Here Juan bowed

Low as the compliment deserved. Suwarrow

Continued: "Your old regiment's allowed,

By special providence, to lead to-morrow,

Or, it may be, to-night, the assault: I have vowed

To several Saints, that shortly plough or harrow

Shall pass o'er what was Ismail, and its tusk[410]

Be unimpeded by the proudest mosque.

LXIV.

"So now, my lads, for Glory!"—Here he turned

And drilled away in the most classic Russian,

Until each high heroic bosom burned

For cash and conquest, as if from a cushion

A preacher had held forth (who nobly spurned

All earthly goods save tithes) and bade them push on

To slay the Pagans who resisted, battering

The armies of the Christian Empress Catherine.

LXV.

Johnson, who knew by this long colloquy

Himself a favourite, ventured to address

Suwarrow, though engaged with accents high

In his resumed amusement. "I confess

My debt in being thus allowed to die

Among the foremost; but if you'd express

Explicitly our several posts, my friend

And self would know what duty to attend."

LXVI.

"Right! I was busy, and forgot. Why, you

Will join your former regiment, which should be

Now under arms. Ho! Katskoff, take him to"—

(Here he called up a Polish orderly)

"His post, I mean the regiment Nikolaiew:

The stranger stripling may remain with me;

He's a fine boy. The women may be sent

To the other baggage, or to the sick tent."

LXVII.

But here a sort of scene began to ensue:

The ladies,—who by no means had been bred

To be disposed of in a way so new,

Although their Harem education led,

Doubtless, to that of doctrines the most true,

Passive obedience,—now raised up the head

With flashing eyes and starting tears, and flung

Their arms, as hens their wings about their young,

LXVIII.

O'er the promoted couple of brave men

Who were thus honoured by the greatest Chief

That ever peopled Hell with heroes slain,

Or plunged a province or a realm in grief.

Oh, foolish mortals! Always taught in vain!

Oh, glorious Laurel! since for one sole leaf

Of thine imaginary deathless tree,

Of blood and tears must flow the unebbing sea.[HU]

LXIX.

Suwarrow, who had small regard for tears,

And not much sympathy for blood, surveyed

The women with their hair about their ears

And natural agonies, with a slight shade

Of feeling: for however Habit sears

Men's hearts against whole millions, when their trade

Is butchery, sometimes a single sorrow

Will touch even heroes—and such was Suwarrow.

LXX.

He said,—and in the kindest Calmuck tone,—

"Why, Johnson, what the devil do you mean

By bringing women here? They shall be shown

All the attention possible, and seen

In safety to the waggons, where alone

In fact they can be safe. You should have been

Aware this kind of baggage never thrives;

Save wed a year, I hate recruits with wives"—

LXXI.

"May it please your Excellency," thus replied

Our British friend, "these are the wives of others,

And not our own. I am too qualified

By service with my military brothers

To break the rules by bringing one's own bride

Into a camp: I know that nought so bothers

The hearts of the heroic on a charge,

As leaving a small family at large.

LXXII.

"But these are but two Turkish ladies, who

With their attendant aided our escape,

And afterwards accompanied us through

A thousand perils in this dubious shape.

To me this kind of life is not so new;

To them, poor things, it is an awkward scrape:

I therefore, if you wish me to fight freely,

Request that they may both be used genteelly."

LXXIII.

Meantime these two poor girls, with swimming eyes,

Looked on as if in doubt if they could trust

Their own protectors; nor was their surprise

Less than their grief (and truly not less just)

To see an old man, rather wild than wise

In aspect, plainly clad, besmeared with dust,

Stripped to his waistcoat, and that not too clean,

More feared than all the Sultans ever seen.

LXXIV.

For everything seemed resting on his nod,

As they could read in all eyes. Now to them,

Who were accustomed, as a sort of god,

To see the Sultan, rich in many a gem,

Like an imperial peacock stalk abroad

(That royal bird, whose tail's a diadem,)

With all the pomp of Power, it was a doubt

How Power could condescend to do without.

LXXV.

John Johnson, seeing their extreme dismay,

Though little versed in feelings oriental,

Suggested some slight comfort in his way:

Don Juan, who was much more sentimental,

Swore they should see him by the dawn of day,

Or that the Russian army should repent all:

And, strange to say, they found some consolation

In this—for females like exaggeration.

LXXVI.

And then with tears, and sighs, and some slight kisses,

They parted for the present—these to await,

According to the artillery's hits or misses,

What sages call Chance, Providence, or Fate—

(Uncertainty is one of many blisses,

A mortgage on Humanity's estate;)[HV]

While their belovéd friends began to arm,

To burn a town which never did them harm.

LXXVII.

Suwarrow,—who but saw things in the gross.

Being much too gross to see them in detail,

Who calculated life as so much dross,

And as the wind a widowed nation's wail,

And cared as little for his army's loss

(So that their efforts should at length prevail)

As wife and friends did for the boils of Job,—

What was 't to him to hear two women sob?

LXXVIII.

Nothing.—The work of Glory still went on

In preparations for a cannonade

As terrible as that of Ilion,

If Homer had found mortars ready made;

But now, instead of slaying Priam's son,

We only can but talk of escalade,

Bombs, drums, guns, bastions, batteries, bayonets, bullets—

Hard words, which stick in the soft Muses' gullets.

LXXIX.

Oh, thou eternal Homer! who couldst charm

All ears, though long; all ages, though so short,

By merely wielding with poetic arm

Arms to which men will never more resort,

Unless gunpowder should be found to harm

Much less than is the hope of every court,

Which now is leagued young Freedom to annoy;

But they will not find Liberty a Troy:—

LXXX.

Oh, thou eternal Homer! I have now

To paint a siege, wherein more men were slain,

With deadlier engines and a speedier blow,

Than in thy Greek gazette of that campaign;

And yet, like all men else, I must allow,

To vie with thee would be about as vain

As for a brook to cope with Ocean's flood,—

But still we moderns equal you in blood:[HW]

LXXXI.

If not in poetry, at least in fact;

And fact is Truth, the grand desideratum!

Of which, howe'er the Muse describes each act,

There should be ne'ertheless a slight substratum.

But now the town is going to be attacked;

Great deeds are doing—how shall I relate 'em?

Souls of immortal Generals! Phoebus watches

To colour up his rays from your despatches.[HX]

LXXXII.

Oh, ye great bulletins of Bonaparte!

Oh, ye less grand long lists of killed and wounded!

Shade of Leonidas, who fought so hearty,

When my poor Greece was once, as now, surrounded!

Oh, Cæsar's Commentaries! now impart, ye

Shadows of Glory! (lest I be confounded),

A portion of your fading twilight hues—

So beautiful, so fleeting—to the Muse.

LXXXIII.

When I call "fading" martial immortality,

I mean, that every age and every year,

And almost every day, in sad reality,

Some sucking hero is compelled to rear,

Who, when we come to sum up the totality

Of deeds to human happiness most dear,

Turns out to be a butcher in great business,

Afflicting young folks with a sort of dizziness.

LXXXIV.

Medals, rank, ribands, lace, embroidery, scarlet,

Are things immortal to immortal man,

As purple to the Babylonian harlot;[HY]

An uniform to boys is like a fan

To women; there is scarce a crimson varlet

But deems himself the first in Glory's van.

But Glory's glory; and if you would find

What that is—ask the pig who sees the wind!

LXXXV.

At least he feels it, and some say he sees,

Because he runs before it like a pig;

Or, if that simple sentence should displease,

Say, that he scuds before it like a brig,

A schooner, or—but it is time to ease

This Canto, ere my Muse perceives fatigue.

The next shall ring a peal to shake all people,

Like a bob-major from a village steeple.

LXXXVI.

Hark! through the silence of the cold, dull night,

The hum of armies gathering rank on rank!

Lo! dusky masses steal in dubious sight

Along the leaguered wall and bristling bank

Of the armed river, while with straggling light

The stars peep through the vapours dim and dank,

Which curl in various wreaths:—how soon the smoke

Of Hell shall pall them in a deeper cloak!

LXXXVII.

Here pause we for the present—as even then

That awful pause, dividing Life from Death,

Struck for an instant on the hearts of men,—

Thousands of whom were drawing their last breath!

A moment—and all will be Life again!

The march! the charge! the shouts of either faith,

Hurrah! and Allah! and one moment more—

The death-cry drowning in the Battle's roar.[HZ][411]

FOOTNOTES:

[364] {302}["These [the seventh and eighth] Cantos contain a full detail (like the storm in Canto Second) of the siege and assault of Ismael, with much of sarcasm on those butchers in large business, your mercenary soldiery.... With these things and these fellows it is necessary, in the present clash of philosophy and tyranny, to throw away the scabbard. I know it is against fearful odds; but the battle must be fought; and it will be eventually for the good of mankind, whatever it may be for the individual who risks himself."—Letter to Moore, August 8, 1822, Letters, 1901, vi. 101.]

[365] [Byron attributes this phrase to Orator Henley (Letters, 1898, i. 227); and to Bayes in the Duke of Buckingham's play, The Rehearsal (Letters, 1901, v. 80).]

[HH] Of Fenelon, of Calvin and of Christ.—[MS. erased.]

[366] [Compare Childe Harold, Canto II. stanza vii. line 1, Poetical Works, 1899, ii. 103, note 2.]

[HI] Picking a pebble on the shore of Truth.—[MS. erased.]

[367] ["Sir Isaac Newton, a little before he died, said, 'I don't know what I may seem to the world; but, as to myself, I seem to have been only like a boy playing on the sea shore, and diverting myself in now and then finding a smoother pebble or a prettier shell than ordinary whilst the great ocean of truth lay all undiscovered before me.'"—Spence, Anecdotes (quoting Chevalier Ramsay), 1858, p. 40.]

[HJ] {304}From fools who dread to know the truth of Life.—[MS. erased.]

[368] [Compare "Inscription on the Monument of a Newfoundland Dog," lines 7, sq., Poetical Works, 1898, i. 280.]

[369] [Aleksandr Vasilievitch Suvóroff (1729-1800) opened his attack on Ismail, November 30, 1790. His forces, including Kossacks, exceeded 27,000 men.—Essai sur l'Histoire Ancienne et Moderne de la Nouvelle Russie, par le Marquis Gabriel de Castelnau, 1827, ii. 201.]

[370] ["Ismaël est situé sur la rive gauche du bras gauche (i.e. the ilia) du Danube."—Ibid..]

[371] {305}[——"à peu près à quatre-vingts verstes de la mer: elle a près de trois milles toises de tour."—Hist. de la Nouvelle Russie, ii. 201.]

[372] ["On a compris dans ces fortifications un faubourg moldave, situé à la gauche de la ville, sur une hauteur qui la domine: l'ouvrage a été terminé par un Grec. Pour donner une idée des talens de cet ingénieur, il suffira de dire qu'il fit placer les palissades perpendiculairement sur le parapet, de manière qu'elles favorisaient les assiégeans, et arrêtaient le feu des assiégés."—Ibid., p. 202.]

[373] ["Le rempart en terre est prodigieusement élevé à cause de l'immense profondeur du fossé; il est cependant absolument rasant: il n'y a ni ouvrage avancé, ni chemin couvert."—Ibid., p. 202.]

[374] [Casemate is a work made under the rampart, like a cellar or cave, with loopholes to place guns in it, and is bomb proof.—Milit. Dict.]

[375] [When the breastwork of a battery is only of such height that the guns may fire over it without being obliged to make embrasures, the guns are said to fire in barbet.—Ibid.]

[376] {306}["Un bastion de pierres, ouvert par une gorge très-étroite, et dont les murailles son fort épaisses, a une batterie casematée et une à barbette; il défend la rive du Danube. Du côté droit de la ville est un cavalier de quarante pieds d'élévation à pic, garni de vingt-deux pièces de canon, et qui défend la partie gauche."—Hist. de la Nouvelle Russie, ii. 202.]

[377] ["Du côté du fleuve, la ville est absolument ouverte; les Turcs ne croyaient pas que les Russes pussent jamais avoir une flotille dans le Danube."—Ibid., p. 203.]

[378] [Meknop [supposed to be a corruption of McNab], etc., in line three, are real names: Strongenoff stands for Strogonof, Tschitsshakoff for Tchitchagof, and, perhaps, Chokenoff for Tchoglokof.]

[HK] {307}—— these discords of damnation.—[MS. erased.]

[379] ["La première attaque était composée de trois colonnes, commandées par les lieutenans-generaux Paul Potiemkin, Serge Lwow, les généraux-majors Maurice Lascy, Théodore Meknop.... Trois autres colonnes ... avaient pour chefs le comte de Samoïlow, les généraux Êlie de Bezborodko, Michel Koutousow; les brigadiers Orlow, Platow, Ribaupierre.... La troisième attaque par eau n'avait que deux colonnes, sous les ordres des généraux-majors Ribas et Arséniew, des brigadiers Markoff et Tchépéga," etc.—Hist. de la Nouvelle Russie, ii. 207.

Compare—

"Oscharoffsky and Rostoffsky,

And all the others that end in-offsky.

And Kutousoff he cut them off," etc.

Southey's March to Moscow, 1813.]

[380] [Count Boris Petrowitch Scheremetov, Russian general, died 1819; Prince Alexis Borisovitch Kourakin (1759-1829), and Count Alexis Iwanowitch Moussine-Pouschkine (1744-1817) were distinguished statesmen; Chrematoff is, perhaps, a rhyming double of Scherematoff, and Koklophti "a match-piece" to Koclobski.]

[381] {308}[Captain Smith, in the song—

"A Captain bold, in Halifax,

That dwelt in country quarters,

Seduc'd a maid who hang'd herself

One Monday in her garters."

See George Colman's farce, Love Laughs at Locksmiths, 1818, p. 31.]

[382] {309}[Compare—

"While to my shame I see

The imminent death of twenty thousand men,

That for a fantasy and trick of fame

Go to their graves like beds."

Hamlet, act iv. sc. 4, lines 56-59.]

[HL] The Conquest seemed not difficult——.—[MS. erased.]

[383] ["On s'était proposé deux buts également avantageux, par la construction de deux batteries sur l'île qui avoisine Ismaël: le premier, de bombarder la place, d'en abattre les principaux édifices avec du canon de quarante-huit, effet d'autant plus probable, que la ville étant bâtie en amphithéâtre, presque aucun coup ne serait perdu."—Hist. de la Nouvelle Russie, ii. 203.]

[384] ["Le second objet était de profiter de ce moment d'alarme pour que la flottille, agissant en même temps, put détruire celle des Turcs. Un troisième motif, et vraisemblablement le plus plausible, était de jeter la consternation parmi les Turcs, et de les engager à capituler."—Hist. de la Nouvelle Russie, ii. 203.]

[HM] {310}

Unless they are as game as bull-dogs or even tarriers.

or, A thing which sometimes hath occurred to warriors,

Unless they happened to be as game as tarriers.—

[MS. A. Alternative reading.]

Unless they are Game as bull-dogs or even terriers.—[MS. B.]

(Byron erased the reading of MS. B. and superscribed the reading of the text.)

[385] ["Une habitude blâmable, celle de mépriser son ennemi, fut la cause."—Ibid., p. 203.]

[386] [" ... du défaut de perfection dans la construction des batteries; on voulait agir promptement, et on négligea de donner aux ouvrages la solidité qu'ils exigaient."—Ibid., p. 203.]

[387] {311}["Le même esprit fit manquer l'effet de trois brûlots; on calcula mal la distance; on se pressa d'allumer la méche, ils brûlèrent au milieu du fleuve, et quoiqu'il fût six heures du matin, les Turcs, encore couchés, n'en prirent aucun ombrage."—Hist. de la Nouvelle Russie, ii. 203.]

[388] ["1er Dec. 1790. La flottille russe s'avança vers les sept heures; il en était neuf lorsqu'elle se trouva à cinquante toises de la ville [d'Ismaël]: elle souffrit, avec une constance calme, un feu de mitraille et de mousqueterie...."—Ibid., p. 204.]

[389] [" ... près de six heures ... les batteries de terre secondaient la flottille; mais on reconnut alors que les canonnades ne suffiraient pas pour réduire la place, on fit la retraite à une heure. Un lançon sauta pendant l'action, un autre dériva par la force du courant, et fut pris par l'ennemi."'—Hist. de la Nouvelle Russie, ii. 204.]

[390] {312}[For Delhis, see Poetical Works, 1899, ii., note 1.]

[391] ["Les Turcs perdirent beaucoup de monde et plusieurs vaisseaux. A peine la retraite des Russes fut-elle remarquée, que les plus braves d'entre les ennemis se jetèrent dans de petites barques et essayèrent une descente: le Comte de Damas les mit en fuite, et leur tua plusieurs officiers et grand nombre de soldats."—Hist. de la Nouvelle Russie, p. 204.]

[392] ["On ne tarirait pas si on voulait rapporter tout ce que les Russes firent de mémorable dans cette journée; pour conter les hauts faits d'armes, pour particulariser toutes les actions d'éclat, il faudrait composer des volumes."—Ibid., p. 204.]

[393] ["Parmi les étrangers, le prince de Ligne se distingua de manière à mériter l'estime générale; de vrais chevaliers français, attirés par l'amour de la gloire, se montrèrent dignes d'elle: les plus marquans étaient le jeune Duc de Richelieu, les Comtes de Langeron et de Damas."—Ibid., p. 204.

Andrault, Comte de Langeron, born at Paris, January 13, 1763, on the outbreak of the Revolution (1790) took service in the Russian Army. He fought against the Swedes in 1790, and the Turks in 1791, and, after serving as a volunteer in the army of the Duke of Brunswick (1792-93), returned to Russia, and was raised to the rank of general in 1799. He commanded a division of the Russian Army in the German campaign of 1813, and entered Paris with Blücher, March 30, 1814. He was afterwards Governor of Odessa and of New Russia; and, a second time, fought against the Turks in 1828. He died at St. Petersburg, July 4, 1831. Joseph Elizabeth Roger, Comte de Damas d'Antigny, born at Paris, September 4, 1765, owed his commission in the Russian Army to the influence of the Prince de Ligne. He fought against the Turks in 1787-88, and was distinguished for bravery and daring. At the Restoration in 1814 he re-entered the French Army, was made Governor of Lyons; shared the temporary exile of Louis XVIII. at Ghent in 1815, and, in the following year, as commandant of a division, took part in repressing the revolutionary disturbances in the central and southern departments of France. He died at Cirey, September 3, 1823.—La Grande Encyclopédie.]

[394] {313}[Charles Joseph, Prince de Ligne, was born at Brussels, May 12, 1735. In 1782 he visited St. Petersburg as envoy of the Emperor Joseph II., won Catherine's favour, and was appointed Field Marshal in the Russian Army. In 1788 he was sent to assist Potemkin at the siege of Ochakof. His Mélanges Militaires, etc., were first published in 1795. He died in November, 1814.

Josef de Ribas (1737-c. 1797).]

[395] ["L'Amiral de Ribas ... déclara, en plein conseil, que ce n'était qu'en donnant l'assaut qu'on obtiendrait la place: cet avis parut hardi; on lui opposa mille raisons, auxquelles il répondit par de meilleures." —Hist. de la Nouvelle Russie, ii, 205.]

[396] {314}[Prince (Gregor Alexandrovitch) Potemkin, born 1736, died October 15, 1791. "He alighted from his carriage in the midst of the highway, threw himself on the grass, and died under a tree" (Life of Catherine II., by W. Tooke, 1880, iii. 324). His character has been drawn by Louis Philippe, Comte de Ségur, who, writes Tooke (ibid., p. 326), "lived a long time in habits of intimacy with him, and was so obliging as to delineate it at our solicitation." "In his person were collected the most opposite defects and advantages of every kind. He was avaricious and ostentatious, ... haughty and obliging, politic and confiding, licentious and superstitious, bold and timid, ambitious and indiscreet; lavish of his bounties to his relations, his mistresses, and his favourites, yet frequently paying neither his household nor his creditors. His consequence always depended on a woman, and he was always unfaithful to her. Nothing could equal the activity of his mind, nor the indolence of his body. No dangers could appal his courage; no difficulties force him to abandon his projects. But the success of an enterprise always brought on disgust.... Everything with him was desultory; business, pleasure, temper, carriage. His presence was a restraint on every company. He was morose to all that stood in awe of him, and caressed all such as accosted him with familiarity.... None had read less than he; few people were better informed.... One while he formed the project of becoming Duke of Courland; at another he thought of bestowing on himself the crown of Poland. He frequently gave intimations of an intention to make himself a bishop, or even a simple monk. He built a superb palace, and wanted to sell it before it was finished. In his youth he had pleased her [Catherine] by the ardour of his passion, by his valour, and by his masculine beauty.... Become the rival of Orloff, he performed for his sovereign whatever the most romantic passion could inspire. He put out his eye, to free it from a blemish which diminished his beauty. Banished by his rival, he ran to meet death in battle, and returned with glory."]

[397] {315}["Ce projet, remis à un autre jour, éprouva encore les plus grandes difficultés; son courage les surmonta: il ne s'agíssait que de déterminer le Prince Potiemkin; il y réussit. Tandis qu'il se démenait pour l'exécution de projet agréé, on construisait de nouvelles batteries; on comptait, le 12 décembre, quatre-vingts pièces de canon sur le bord du Danube, et cette journée se passa en vives canonnades."—Histoire de la Nouvelle Russie, ii. 205.]

[HN] Into all aspirants for martial praise.—[MS. erased.]

[398] ["Le 13e, une partie des troupes était embarquée; on allait lever le siège: un courrier arrive.... Ce courrier annonce, de la part du prince, que le maréchal Souwarow va prendre le commandement des forces réunies sous Ismaël."—Ibid., p. 205.]

[399] {316}["La lettre du Prince Potiemkin à Souwarow est très courte; elle peint le caractere de ces deux personnages. La voici dans toute sa teneur: 'Vous prendrez Ismaël à quel frix que ce soit!'"—Hist, de la Nouvelle Russie, ii. 205.]

[400] ["[Le courrier] est témoin des cris de joie du Turc, qui se croyait à la fin de ses maux."-Ibid., p. 205.]

[401] ["Beat," as in "dead-beat," is occasionally used for "beaten."—See N.E.D., art. "Beat," 10.]

[402] ["Le 16e, on voit venir de loin deux hommes courant à toute bride: on les prit pour des Kozaks; l'un était Souwarow, et l'autre son guide, portant un paquet gros comme le poing, et renfermant le bagage du général."-Hist, de la Nouvelle Russie, ii. 205.

M. de Castelnau in his description of the arrival of Suvóroff on the field of battle (Hist, de la N.R., 1827, ii. pp, 205, 206) summarizes the Journal of the Duc de Richelieu. The original passage runs as follows:—

"L'arrivée du comte Souvorow produisit un grand effet parmi les troupes.... La manière d'être plus que simple, puis-qu'il logeait sous une canonnière, et qu'il n'avait pas même de chaises dans sa tente, son affabilité, sa bonhomie lui conciliaient l'affection de tous les individus de son armée. Cet homme singulier qui ressemble plus à un chef de cosaques ou de Tartares, qu'au général d'une armée européenne, est doué d'une intrépidité et d'une hardiesse peu communes.... La manière de vivre, de s'habiller et de parler du comte Souvorow, est aussi singulière que ses opinions militaires.... Il mangeait dans sa tente assis par terre autour d'une natte sur laquelle il prenait le plus détestable repas. L'après-midi, un semblable repas lui servait de souper, il s'endormait ensuite pendant quelques heures, passait une partie de la nuit à chanter, et a la pointe du jour il sortait presque nu et se roulait sur l'herbe assurant que cet exercice lui était necessaire pour le préserver des rhumatismes.... Sa manière de s'exprimer dans toutes les langues est aussi singulière que toute sa façon d'être, ses phrases sont incohérentes, et s'il n'est pas insensé, il dit et fait du moins tout ce qu'il faut pour le paraître; mais il est heureux et cette qualité dont le Cardinal Mazarin faisait tant de cas, est, à bon droit, fort estimée de l'Impératrice et du Prince Potemkin ... Le moment de l'arrivée du Comte Souvorow fut annoncé par une décharge générale des batteries ou camp et de la flotte."—Journal de mon Voyage en Allemagne. Soc, Imp. d'Hist de Russie, 1886, tom. liv. pp. 168, 169.]

[HO] {317}That sage John Bull——.—[MS.]

That fool John Bull——.—[MS. erased.]

[403] {319}["La première attaque était composée de trois colonnes ... Trois autres colonnes, destinées a la seconde attaque, avaient pour chefs, etc.... La troisième attaque par eau n'avait que deux colonnes."—Hist, de la Nouvelle Russie, ii. 207.]

[404] ["On construisit de nouvelles batteries le 18e.... On tint un conseil de guerre, on y examina les plans pour l'assaut proposés par M. de Ribas, ils réunirent tous les souffrages."—Ibid., p. 208.]

[HP] For once by some odd sort of magnanimity.—[MS. erased.]

[HQ] Bellona shook her spear with much sublimity.—[MS. erased.]

[405] Fact: Suwaroff did this in person.

[HR]—— and neither swerve nor spill.—[MS. erased.]

[406] ["Le 19e et le 20e, Souwarow exerçailes soldats; il leur montra comment il fallait s'y prendre pour escalader; il enseigna aux recrues la manière de donner le coup de baïonnette."—Ibid., p. 208.]

[407] {320}["Pour ces exercices d'un nouveau genre, il se servit de fascines disposées de manière a représenter un Turc."-Hist, de la Nauvelle Russie, ii. 208.]

[HS]

At which your wise men laughed, but all their Wit is

Lost, for his repartee was taking cities.—[MS. erased.]

[HT]

For some were thinking of their wives and families,

And others of themselves (as poet Samuel is).

—[MS. Alternative reading.]

And others of themselves (as my friend Samuel is).

—[MS. erased.]

[408] [For a detailed account of Suvóroff's personal characteristics, see The Life of Field-Marshal Souvaroff, by L.M.P. Tranchant de Laverne, 1814, pp. 267-291; and Suvóroff, by Lieut.-Colonel Spalding, 1890, pp. 222-229.

Byron's epithet "buffoon" (line 5) may, perhaps, be traced to the following anecdote recorded by Tranchant de Laverne (p. 281): "During the first war of Poland ... he published, in the order of the day, that at the first crowing of the cock the troops would march to attack the enemy, and caused the spy to send word that the Russians would be upon them some time after midnight. But about eight o'clock Souvarof ran through the camp, imitating the crowing of a cock.... The enemy, completely surprised, lost a great number of men."

For his "praying" (line 6), vide ibid., pp. 272, 273: "He made a short prayer after each meal, and again when going to bed. He usually performed his devotions before an image of St. Nicholas, the patron saint of Russia."

"Half-dirt" (line 5) is, however, a calumny (ibid. p. 272): "It was his custom to rise at the earliest dawn; several buckets of cold water were thrown over his naked body."

The same writer (p. 268) repudiates the charges of excessive barbarity and cruelty brought against Suvóroff by C.F.P. Masson, in his Mémoires Secrets sur la Russie (vide, e.g., ed. 1800, i. 311): "Souvorow ne scroit que le plus ridicule bouffon, s'il n'étoit pas montré le plus barbare guerrier. C'est un monstre, qui renferme dans le corps d'un singe l'âme d'un chien de boucher. Attila, son compatriote, et don't il descend, peut-être ne fut ni si heureux, ni si féroce."

Suvóroff did not regard himself as "half-demon." "Your pencil," he reminded the artist Müller, "will delineate the features of my face. These are visible: but my inner man is hidden. I must tell you that I have shed rivers of blood. I tremble, but I love my neighbour. In my whole life I have made no one unhappy; not an insect hath perished by my hand. I was little; I was big. In fortune's ebb and flow, relying on God, I stood immovable—even as now." (Suvóroff, 1890, p. 228, note.)]

[409] {322}[See, for instance, The Storm, in "Souvarof's Catechism," Appendix (pp. 299-305) to the Life, etc., by Tranchant de Laverne, 1814: "Break down the fence.... Fly over the walls! Stab them on the ramparts!... Fire down the streets! Fire briskly!... Kill every enemy in the streets! Let the cavalry hack them!" etc.]

[410] {323}[The "tusk" of the plough is the coulter or share. Compare "Dens vomeris" (Virg., Georg., i. 22).]

[HU] {324}

Of thine imaginary deathless bough

The unebbing sea of blood and tears must flow.—[MS. erased.]

[HV] {326}Entailed upon Humanity's estate.—[MS. erased.]

[HW] {327}

As a brook's stream to cope with Ocean's flood shed

But still we moderns equal you in bloodshed.—[MS. erased.]

[HX] {328}

As in a General's letter when well whacked

Whatever deeds be done I will relate 'em,

With some small variations in the text

Of killed and wounded who will not be missed.—[MS. erased.]

[HY] Whose leisure hours are wasted on an harlot.—[MS. erased.]

[HZ] {329}The desperate death-cry and the Battle's roar.—[MS. erased.]

[411] End of Canto 7. 1822.—[MS.]

Canto IX

I.[476]

Oh, Wellington! (or "Villainton"[477]—for Fame[IT]

Sounds the heroic syllables both ways;

France could not even conquer your great name,

But punned it down to this facetious phrase—

Beating or beaten she will laugh the same,)

You have obtained great pensions and much praise:

Glory like yours should any dare gainsay,

Humanity would rise, and thunder "Nay!"[478]

II.

I don't think that you used Kinnaird quite well

In Marinèt's affair[479]—in fact, 't was shabby,

And like some other things won't do to tell

Upon your tomb in Westminster's old Abbey.

Upon the rest 't is not worth while to dwell,

Such tales being for the tea-hours of some tabby;[480]

But though your years as man tend fast to zero,

In fact your Grace is still but a young Hero.

III.

Though Britain owes (and pays you too) so much,

Yet Europe doubtless owes you greatly more:

You have repaired Legitimacy's crutch,

A prop not quite so certain as before:

The Spanish, and the French, as well as Dutch,

Have seen, and felt, how strongly you restore;

And Waterloo has made the world your debtor

(I wish your bards would sing it rather better).

IV.

You are "the best of cut-throats:"[481]—do not start;

The phrase is Shakespeare's, and not misapplied:—

War's a brain-spattering, windpipe-slitting art,

Unless her cause by right be sanctified.

If you have acted once a generous part,

The World, not the World's masters, will decide,

And I shall be delighted to learn who,

Save you and yours, have gained by Waterloo?

V.

I am no flatterer—you've supped full of flattery:[482]

They say you like it too—'t is no great wonder.

He whose whole life has been assault and battery,

At last may get a little tired of thunder;

And swallowing eulogy much more than satire, he

May like being praised for every lucky blunder,

Called "Saviour of the Nations"—not yet saved,—

And "Europe's Liberator"—still enslaved.[483]

VI.

I've done. Now go and dine from off the plate

Presented by the Prince of the Brazils,

And send the sentinel before your gate

A slice or two from your luxurious meals:[484]

He fought, but has not fed so well of late.

Some hunger, too, they say the people feels:—

There is no doubt that you deserve your ration,

But pray give back a little to the nation.

VII.

I don't mean to reflect—a man so great as

You, my lord Duke! is far above reflection:

The high Roman fashion, too, of Cincinnatus,

With modern history has but small connection:

Though as an Irishman you love potatoes,

You need not take them under your direction;

And half a million for your Sabine farm

Is rather dear!—I'm sure I mean no harm.

VIII.

Great men have always scorned great recompenses:

Epaminondas saved his Thebes, and died,

Not leaving even his funeral expenses:[485]

George Washington had thanks, and nought beside,

Except the all-cloudless glory (which few men's is)

To free his country: Pitt too had his pride,

And as a high-souled Minister of state is

Renowned for ruining Great Britain gratis.[486]

IX.

Never had mortal man such opportunity,

Except Napoleon, or abused it more:

You might have freed fallen Europe from the unity

Of Tyrants, and been blest from shore to shore:

And now—what is your fame? Shall the Muse tune it ye?

Now—that the rabble's first vain shouts are o'er?

Go! hear it in your famished country's cries!

Behold the World! and curse your victories!

X.

As these new cantos touch on warlike feats,

To you the unflattering Muse deigns to inscribe[IU]

Truths, that you will not read in the Gazettes,

But which 't is time to teach the hireling tribe

Who fatten on their country's gore, and debts,

Must be recited—and without a bribe.

You did great things, but not being great in mind,

Have left undone the greatest—and mankind.

XI.

Death laughs—Go ponder o'er the skeleton

With which men image out the unknown thing

That hides the past world, like to a set sun

Which still elsewhere may rouse a brighter spring—

Death laughs at all you weep for!—look upon

This hourly dread of all! whose threatened sting

Turns Life to terror, even though in its sheath:

Mark! how its lipless mouth grins without breath!

XII.

Mark! how it laughs and scorns at all you are!

And yet was what you are; from ear to ear

It laughs not—there is now no fleshy bar

So called; the Antic long hath ceased to hear,

But still he smiles; and whether near or far,

He strips from man that mantle (far more dear

Than even the tailor's), his incarnate skin,[IV]

White, black, or copper—the dead bones will grin.

XIII.

And thus Death laughs,—it is sad merriment,

But still it is so; and with such example

Why should not Life be equally content

With his Superior, in a smile to trample

Upon the nothings which are daily spent

Like bubbles on an Ocean much less ample

Than the Eternal Deluge, which devours

Suns as rays—worlds like atoms—years like hours?

XIV.

"To be, or not to be? that is the question,"

Says Shakespeare,[487] who just now is much in fashion.

I am neither Alexander nor Hephæstion,

Nor ever had for abstract fame much passion;

But would much rather have a sound digestion

Than Buonaparte's cancer:—could I dash on

Through fifty victories to shame or fame—

Without a stomach what were a good name?

XV.

"O dura ilia messorum!"[488]—"Oh

Ye rigid guts of reapers!" I translate[IW]

For the great benefit of those who know

What indigestion is—that inward fate

Which makes all Styx through one small liver flow.

A peasant's sweat is worth his lord's estate:

Let this one toil for bread—that rack for rent,

He who sleeps best may be the most content.

XVI.

"To be, or not to be?"—Ere I decide,

I should be glad to know that which is being.

'T is true we speculate both far and wide,

And deem, because we see, we are all-seeing:

For my part, I'll enlist on neither side,

Until I see both sides for once agreeing.

For me, I sometimes think that Life is Death,

Rather than Life a mere affair of breath.

XVII.

"Que scais-je"[489] was the motto of Montaigne,

As also of the first academicians:

That all is dubious which man may attain,

Was one of their most favourite positions.

There's no such thing as certainty, that's plain

As any of Mortality's conditions;

So little do we know what we're about in

This world, I doubt if doubt itself be doubting.

XVIII.

It is a pleasant voyage perhaps to float,

Like Pyrrho,[490] on a sea of speculation;

But what if carrying sail capsize the boat?

Your wise men don't know much of navigation;

And swimming long in the abyss of thought

Is apt to tire: a calm and shallow station

Well nigh the shore, where one stoops down and gathers

Some pretty shell, is best for moderate bathers.

XIX.

"But Heaven," as Cassio says, "is above all—[491]

No more of this, then, let us pray!" We have

Souls to save, since Eve's slip and Adam's fall,

Which tumbled all mankind into the grave,

Besides fish, beasts, and birds. "The sparrow's fall

Is special providence,"[492] though how it gave

Offence, we know not; probably it perched

Upon the tree which Eve so fondly searched.

XX.

Oh! ye immortal Gods! what is Theogony?

Oh! thou, too, mortal man! what is Philanthropy?

Oh! World, which was and is, what is Cosmogony?

Some people have accused me of Misanthropy;

And yet I know no more than the mahogany

That forms this desk, of what they mean;—Lykanthropy[493]

I comprehend, for without transformation

Men become wolves on any slight occasion.

XXI.

But I, the mildest, meekest of mankind,

Like Moses, or Melancthon,[494] who have ne'er[IX]

Done anything exceedingly unkind,—

And (though I could not now and then forbear

Following the bent of body or of mind)

Have always had a tendency to spare,—

Why do they call me Misanthrope? Because

They hate me, not I them:—and here we'll pause.

XXII.

'T is time we should proceed with our good poem,—

For I maintain that it is really good,

Not only in the body but the proem,

However little both are understood

Just now,—but by and by the Truth will show 'em

Herself in her sublimest attitude:

And till she doth, I fain must be content

To share her beauty and her banishment.

XXIII.

Our hero (and, I trust, kind reader! yours)

Was left upon his way to the chief city

Of the immortal Peter's polished boors,

Who still have shown themselves more brave than witty.

I know its mighty Empire now allures

Much flattery—even Voltaire's,[495] and that's a pity.

For me, I deem an absolute autocrat

Not a barbarian, but much worse than that.

XXIV.

And I will war, at least in words (and—should

My chance so happen—deeds), with all who war

With Thought;—and of Thought's foes by far most rude,

Tyrants and sycophants have been and are.

I know not who may conquer: if I could

Have such a prescience, it should be no bar

To this my plain, sworn, downright detestation

Of every despotism in every nation.[IY]

XXV.

It is not that I adulate the people:

Without me, there are demagogues enough,[496]

And infidels, to pull down every steeple,

And set up in their stead some proper stuff.

Whether they may sow scepticism to reap Hell,

As is the Christian dogma rather rough,

I do not know;—I wish men to be free

As much from mobs as kings—from you as me.

XXVI.

The consequence is, being of no party,

I shall offend all parties:—never mind!

My words, at least, are more sincere and hearty

Than if I sought to sail before the wind.

He who has nought to gain can have small art: he

Who neither wishes to be bound nor bind,

May still expatiate freely, as will I,

Nor give my voice to slavery's jackal cry.[IZ]

XXVII.

That's an appropriate simile, that jackal;—

I've heard them in the Ephesian ruins howl[497]

By night, as do that mercenary pack all,

Power's base purveyors, who for pickings prowl,

And scent the prey their masters would attack all.

However, the poor jackals are less foul

(As being the brave lions' keen providers)

Than human insects, catering for spiders.[JA]

XXVIII.

Raise but an arm! 't will brush their web away,

And without that, their poison and their claws

Are useless. Mind, good people! what I say—

(Or rather Peoples)—go on without pause!

The web of these Tarantulas each day

Increases, till you shall make common cause:

None, save the Spanish Fly and Attic Bee,

As yet are strongly stinging to be free.[JB]

XXIX.

Don Juan, who had shone in the late slaughter,

Was left upon his way with the despatch,

Where blood was talked of as we would of water;

And carcasses that lay as thick as thatch

O'er silenced cities, merely served to flatter

Fair Catherine's pastime—who looked on the match

Between these nations as a main of cocks,

Wherein she liked her own to stand like rocks.

XXX.

And there in a kibitka he rolled on,

(A cursed sort of carriage without springs,

Which on rough roads leaves scarcely a whole bone,)

Pondering on Glory, Chivalry, and Kings,

And Orders, and on all that he had done—

And wishing that post-horses had the wings

Of Pegasus, or at the least post-chaises

Had feathers, when a traveller on deep ways is.

XXXI.

At every jolt—and they were many—still

He turned his eyes upon his little charge,

As if he wished that she should fare less ill

Than he, in these sad highways left at large

To ruts, and flints, and lovely Nature's skill,

Who is no paviour, nor admits a barge

On her canals, where God takes sea and land,

Fishery and farm, both into his own hand.

XXXII.

At least he pays no rent, and has best right

To be the first of what we used to call

"Gentlemen farmers"—a race worn out quite,

Since lately there have been no rents at all,

And "gentlemen" are in a piteous plight,

And "farmers" can't raise Ceres from her fall:

She fell with Buonaparte,[498]—What strange thoughts

Arise, when we see Emperors fall with oats!

XXXIII.

But Juan turned his eyes on the sweet child

Whom he had saved from slaughter—what a trophy

Oh! ye who build up monuments, defiled

With gore, like Nadir Shah,[499] that costive Sophy,

Who, after leaving Hindostan a wild,

And scarce to the Mogul a cup of coffee

To soothe his woes withal, was slain, the sinner!

Because he could no more digest his dinner;—[JC][500]

XXXIV.

Oh ye! or we! or he! or she! reflect,

That one life saved, especially if young

Or pretty, is a thing to recollect

Far sweeter than the greenest laurels sprung

From the manure of human clay, though decked

With all the praises ever said or sung:

Though hymned by every harp, unless within

Your heart joins chorus, Fame is but a din.

XXXV.

Oh! ye great authors luminous, voluminous!

Ye twice ten hundred thousand daily scribes!

Whose pamphlets, volumes, newspapers, illumine us!

Whether you're paid by government in bribes,

To prove the public debt is not consuming us—

Or, roughly treading on the "courtier's kibes"

With clownish heel[501] your popular circulation

Feeds you by printing half the realm's starvation;—

XXXVI.

Oh, ye great authors!—A propos des bottes,—

I have forgotten what I meant to say,

As sometimes have been greater sages' lots;—

'T was something calculated to allay

All wrath in barracks, palaces, or cots:

Certes it would have been but thrown away,

And that's one comfort for my lost advice,

Although no doubt it was beyond all price.

XXXVII.

But let it go:—it will one day be found

With other relics of "a former World,"

When this World shall be former, underground,

Thrown topsy-turvy, twisted, crisped, and curled,

Baked, fried, or burnt, turned inside-out, or drowned,

Like all the worlds before, which have been hurled

First out of, and then back again to chaos—

The superstratum which will overlay us.[JD]

XXXVIII.

So Cuvier says:[502]—and then shall come again

Unto the new creation, rising out

From our old crash, some mystic, ancient strain

Of things destroyed and left in airy doubt;

Like to the notions we now entertain

Of Titans, giants, fellows of about

Some hundred feet in height, not to say miles,

And mammoths, and your winged crocodiles.

XXXIX.

Think if then George the Fourth should be dug up![503]

How the new worldlings of the then new East

Will wonder where such animals could sup!

(For they themselves will be but of the least:

Even worlds miscarry, when too oft they pup,

And every new creation hath decreased

In size, from overworking the material—

Men are but maggots of some huge Earth's burial.)

XL.

How will—to these young people, just thrust out

From some fresh Paradise, and set to plough,

And dig, and sweat, and turn themselves about,

And plant, and reap, and spin, and grind, and sow,

Till all the arts at length are brought about,

Especially of War and taxing,—how,

I say, will these great relics, when they see 'em,

Look like the monsters of a new Museum!

XLI.

But I am apt to grow too metaphysical:

"The time is out of joint,"[504]—and so am I;

I quite forget this poem's merely quizzical,

And deviate into matters rather dry.

I ne'er decide what I shall say, and this I call[JE]

Much too poetical: men should know why

They write, and for what end; but, note or text,

I never know the word which will come next.

XLII.

So on I ramble, now and then narrating,

Now pondering:—it is time we should narrate.

I left Don Juan with his horses baiting—

Now we'll get o'er the ground at a great rate:

I shall not be particular in stating

His journey, we've so many tours of late:

Suppose him then at Petersburgh; suppose

That pleasant capital of painted snows;[505]

XLIII.

Suppose him in a handsome uniform—

A scarlet coat, black facings, a long plume,

Waving, like sails new shivered in a storm,

Over a cocked hat in a crowded room,

And brilliant breeches, bright as a Cairn Gorme,

Of yellow casimire we may presume,

White stockings drawn uncurdled as new milk

O'er limbs whose symmetry set off the silk;[JF]

XLIV.

Suppose him sword by side, and hat in hand,

Made up by Youth, Fame, and an army tailor—

That great enchanter, at whose rod's command

Beauty springs forth, and Nature's self turns paler,

Seeing how Art can make her work more grand

(When she don't pin men's limbs in like a gaoler),—

Behold him placed as if upon a pillar! He[JG]

Seems Love turned a Lieutenant of Artillery![506]

XLV.

His bandage slipped down into a cravat—

His wings subdued to epaulettes—his quiver

Shrunk to a scabbard, with his arrows at

His side as a small sword, but sharp as ever—

His bow converted into a cocked hat—

But still so like, that Psyche were more clever

Than some wives (who make blunders no less stupid),

If she had not mistaken him for Cupid.

XLVI.

The courtiers stared, the ladies whispered, and

The Empress smiled: the reigning favourite frowned—[JH]

I quite forget which of them was in hand

Just then, as they are rather numerous found,[507]

Who took, by turns, that difficult command

Since first her Majesty was singly crowned:[508]

But they were mostly nervous six-foot fellows,

All fit to make a Patagonian jealous.

XLVII.

Juan was none of these, but slight and slim,

Blushing and beardless; and, yet, ne'ertheless,

There was a something in his turn of limb,

And still more in his eye, which seemed to express,

That, though he looked one of the Seraphim,

There lurked a man beneath the Spirit's dress.

Besides, the Empress sometimes liked a boy,

And had just buried the fair-faced Lanskoi.[JI][509]

XLVIII.

No wonder then that Yermoloff, or Momonoff,[510]

Or Scherbatoff, or any other off

Or on, might dread her Majesty had not room enough

Within her bosom (which was not too tough),

For a new flame; a thought to cast of gloom enough

Along the aspect, whether smooth or rough,

Of him who, in the language of his station,

Then held that "high official situation."

XLIX.

O gentle ladies! should you seek to know

The import of this diplomatic phrase,

Bid Ireland's Londonderry's Marquess[511] show

His parts of speech, and in the strange displays

Of that odd string of words, all in a row,

Which none divine, and every one obeys,

Perhaps you may pick out some queer no meaning,—

Of that weak wordy harvest the sole gleaning.

L.

I think I can explain myself without

That sad inexplicable beast of prey—

That Sphinx, whose words would ever be a doubt,

Did not his deeds unriddle them each day—

That monstrous hieroglyphic—that long spout

Of blood and water—leaden Castlereagh!

And here I must an anecdote relate,

But luckily of no great length or weight.

LI.

An English lady asked of an Italian,

What were the actual and official duties

Of the strange thing some women set a value on,

Which hovers oft about some married beauties,

Called "Cavalier Servente?"[512]—a Pygmalion

Whose statues warm (I fear, alas! too true 't is)

Beneath his art:[JJ]—the dame, pressed to disclose them,

Said—"Lady, I beseech you to suppose them."

LII.

And thus I supplicate your supposition,

And mildest, matron-like interpretation,

Of the imperial favourite's condition.

'T was a high place, the highest in the nation

In fact, if not in rank; and the suspicion

Of any one's attaining to his station,

No doubt gave pain, where each new pair of shoulders,

If rather broad, made stocks rise—and their holders.

LIII.

Juan, I said, was a most beauteous boy,

And had retained his boyish look beyond

The usual hirsute seasons which destroy,

With beards and whiskers, and the like, the fond

Parisian aspect, which upset old Troy

And founded Doctors' Commons:[JK]—I have conned

The history of divorces, which, though chequered,

Calls Ilion's the first damages on record.

LIV.

And Catherine, who loved all things (save her Lord,

Who was gone to his place), and passed for much,

Admiring those (by dainty dames abhorred)

Gigantic gentlemen, yet had a touch

Of sentiment: and he she most adored

Was the lamented Lanskoi, who was such

A lover as had cost her many a tear,

And yet but made a middling grenadier.

LV.

Oh thou "teterrima causa" of all "belli"—[513]

Thou gate of Life and Death—thou nondescript!

Whence is our exit and our entrance,—well I

May pause in pondering how all souls are dipped

In thy perennial fountain:—how man fell I

Know not, since Knowledge saw her branches stripped

Of her first fruit; but how he falls and rises

Since,—thou hast settled beyond all surmises.

LVI.

Some call thee "the worst cause of War," but I

Maintain thou art the best:—for after all,

From thee we come, to thee we go, and why

To get at thee not batter down a wall,

Or waste a World? since no one can deny

Thou dost replenish worlds both great and small:

With—or without thee—all things at a stand[JL]

Are, or would be, thou sea of Life's dry land![JM]

LVII.

Catherine, who was the grand Epitome

Of that great cause of War, or Peace, or what

You please (it causes all the things which be,

So you may take your choice of this or that)—

Catherine, I say, was very glad to see

The handsome herald, on whose plumage sat[514]

Victory; and, pausing as she saw him kneel

With his despatch, forgot to break the seal.

LVIII.

Then recollecting the whole Empress, nor

Forgetting quite the Woman (which composed

At least three parts of this great whole), she tore

The letter open with an air which posed

The Court, that watched each look her visage wore,

Until a royal smile at length disclosed

Fair weather for the day. Though rather spacious,

Her face was noble, her eyes fine, mouth gracious.[515]

LIX.

Great joy was hers, or rather joys: the first

Was a ta'en city, thirty thousand slain:

Glory and triumph o'er her aspect burst,

As an East Indian sunrise on the main:—

These quenched a moment her Ambition's thirst—

So Arab deserts drink in Summer's rain:

In vain!—As fall the dews on quenchless sands,

Blood only serves to wash Ambition's hands!

LX.

Her next amusement was more fanciful;

She smiled at mad Suwarrow's rhymes, who threw

Into a Russian couplet rather dull

The whole gazette of thousands whom he slew:

Her third was feminine enough to annul

The shudder which runs naturally through

Our veins, when things called Sovereigns think it best

To kill, and Generals turn it into jest.

LXI.

The two first feelings ran their course complete,

And lighted first her eye, and then her mouth:

The whole court looked immediately most sweet,

Like flowers well watered after a long drouth:—

But when on the Lieutenant at her feet

Her Majesty, who liked to gaze on youth

Almost as much as on a new despatch,

Glanced mildly,—all the world was on the watch.

LXII.

Though somewhat large, exuberant, and truculent,

When wroth—while pleased, she was as fine a figure

As those who like things rosy, ripe, and succulent,

Would wish to look on, while they are in vigour.

She could repay each amatory look you lent

With interest, and, in turn, was wont with rigour

To exact of Cupid's bills the full amount

At sight, nor would permit you to discount.

LXIII.

With her the latter, though at times convenient,

Was not so necessary; for they tell

That she was handsome, and though fierce looked lenient,

And always used her favourites too well.

If once beyond her boudoir's precincts in ye went,

Your "fortune" was in a fair way "to swell

A man" (as Giles says);[516] for though she would widow all

Nations, she liked Man as an individual.

LXIV.

What a strange thing is Man! and what a stranger

Is Woman! What a whirlwind is her head,

And what a whirlpool full of depth and danger

Is all the rest about her! Whether wed,

Or widow—maid—or mother, she can change her

Mind like the wind: whatever she has said

Or done, is light to what she'll say or do;—

The oldest thing on record, and yet new!

LXV.

Oh Catherine! (for of all interjections,

To thee both oh! and ah! belong, of right,

In Love and War) how odd are the connections

Of human thoughts, which jostle in their flight!

Just now yours were cut out in different sections:

First Ismail's capture caught your fancy quite;

Next of new knights, the fresh and glorious batch:

And thirdly he who brought you the despatch!

LXVI.

Shakespeare talks of "the herald Mercury

New lighted on a heaven-kissing hill:"[517]

And some such visions crossed her Majesty,

While her young herald knelt before her still.

'T is very true the hill seemed rather high,

For a Lieutenant to climb up; but skill

Smoothed even the Simplon's steep, and by God's blessing,

With Youth and Health all kisses are "Heaven-kissing."

LXVII.

Her Majesty looked down, the youth looked up—

And so they fell in love;—she with his face,

His grace, his God-knows-what: for Cupid's cup

With the first draught intoxicates apace,

A quintessential laudanum or "Black Drop,"

Which makes one drunk at once, without the base

Expedient of full bumpers; for the eye

In love drinks all Life's fountains (save tears) dry.

LXVIII.

He, on the other hand, if not in love,

Fell into that no less imperious passion,

Self-love—which, when some sort of thing above

Ourselves, a singer, dancer, much in fashion,

Or Duchess—Princess—Empress, "deigns to prove"[518]

('T is Pope's phrase) a great longing, though a rash one,

For one especial person out of many,

Make us believe ourselves as good as any.

LXIX.

Besides, he was of that delighted age

Which makes all female ages equal—when

We don't much care with whom we may engage,

As bold as Daniel in the lions' den,

So that we can our native sun assuage

In the next ocean, which may flow just then—

To make a twilight in, just as Sol's heat is

Quenched in the lap of the salt sea, or Thetis.

LXX.

And Catherine (we must say thus much for Catherine),

Though bold and bloody, was the kind of thing

Whose temporary passion was quite flattering,

Because each lover looked a sort of King,

Made up upon an amatory pattern,

A royal husband in all save the ring—[JN]

Which, (being the damnedest part of matrimony,)

Seemed taking out the sting to leave the honey:

LXXI.

And when you add to this, her Womanhood

In its meridian, her blue eyes[519] or gray—

(The last, if they have soul, are quite as good,

Or better, as the best examples say:

Napoleon's, Mary's[520] (Queen of Scotland), should

Lend to that colour a transcendent ray;

And Pallas also sanctions the same hue,

Too wise to look through optics black or blue)—

LXXII.

Her sweet smile, and her then majestic figure,[JO]

Her plumpness, her imperial condescension,

Her preference of a boy to men much bigger

(Fellows whom Messalina's self would pension),

Her prime of life, just now in juicy vigour,

With other extras, which we need not mention,—

All these, or any one of these, explain

Enough to make a stripling very vain.

LXXIII.

And that's enough, for Love is vanity,

Selfish in its beginning as its end,[JP]

Except where 't is a mere insanity,

A maddening spirit which would strive to blend

Itself with Beauty's frail inanity,

On which the Passion's self seems to depend;

And hence some heathenish philosophers

Make Love the main-spring of the Universe.

LXXIV.

Besides Platonic love, besides the love

Of God, the love of sentiment, the

loving Of faithful pairs—(I needs must rhyme with dove,

That good old steam-boat which keeps verses moving

'Gainst reason—Reason ne'er was hand-and-glove

With rhyme, but always leant less to improving

The sound than sense)—besides all these pretences

To Love, there are those things which words name senses;

LXXV.

Those movements, those improvements in our bodies

Which make all bodies anxious to get out

Of their own sand-pits, to mix with a goddess,

For such all women are at first no doubt.[JQ]

How beautiful that moment! and how odd is

That fever which precedes the languid rout

Of our sensations! What a curious way

The whole thing is of clothing souls in clay![JR]

LXXVI.[521]

The noblest kind of love is love Platonical,

To end or to begin with; the next grand

Is that which may be christened love canonical,

Because the clergy take the thing in hand;

The third sort to be noted in our chronicle

As flourishing in every Christian land,

Is when chaste matrons to their other ties

Add what may be called marriage in disguise.

LXXVII.

Well, we won't analyse—our story must

Tell for itself: the Sovereign was smitten,

Juan much flattered by her love, or lust;—

I cannot stop to alter words once written,

And the two are so mixed with human dust,

That he who names one, both perchance may hit on:

But in such matters Russia's mighty Empress

Behaved no better than a common sempstress.

LXXVIII.

The whole court melted into one wide whisper,

And all lips were applied unto all ears!

The elder ladies' wrinkles curled much crisper

As they beheld; the younger cast some leers

On one another, and each lovely lisper

Smiled as she talked the matter o'er; but tears

Of rivalship rose in each clouded eye

Of all the standing army who stood by.

LXXIX.

All the ambassadors of all the powers

Inquired, Who was this very new young man,

Who promised to be great in some few hours?

Which is full soon (though Life is but a span).

Already they beheld the silver showers

Of rubles rain, as fast as specie can,

Upon his cabinet, besides the presents

Of several ribands, and some thousand peasants.[522]

LXXX.

Catherine was generous,—all such ladies are:

Love—that great opener of the heart and all

The ways that lead there, be they near or far,

Above, below, by turnpikes great or small,—

Love—(though she had a cursed taste for War,

And was not the best wife unless we call

Such Clytemnestra, though perhaps 't is better

That one should die—than two drag on the fetter)—

LXXXI.

Love had made Catherine make each lover's fortune,

Unlike our own half-chaste Elizabeth,

Whose avarice all disbursements did importune,

If History, the grand liar, ever saith

The truth; and though grief her old age might shorten,

Because she put a favourite to death,

Her vile, ambiguous method of flirtation,

And stinginess, disgrace her sex and station.

LXXXII.

But when the levée rose, and all was bustle

In the dissolving circle, all the nations'

Ambassadors began as 't were to hustle

Round the young man with their congratulations.

Also the softer silks were heard to rustle

Of gentle dames, among whose recreations

It is to speculate on handsome faces,

Especially when such lead to high places.

LXXXIII.

Juan, who found himself, he knew not how,

A general object of attention, made

His answers with a very graceful bow,

As if born for the ministerial trade.

Though modest, on his unembarrassed brow

Nature had written "Gentleman!" He said

Little, but to the purpose; and his manner

Flung hovering graces o'er him like a banner.

LXXXIV.

An order from her Majesty consigned

Our young Lieutenant to the genial care

Of those in office: all the world looked kind,

(As it will look sometimes with the first stare,

Which Youth would not act ill to keep in mind,)

As also did Miss Protasoff[523] then there,[JS]

Named from her mystic office "l'Eprouveuse,"

A term inexplicable to the Muse.

LXXXV.

With her then, as in humble duty bound,

Juan retired,—and so will I, until

My Pegasus shall tire of touching ground.

We have just lit on a "heaven-kissing hill,"

So lofty that I feel my brain turn round,

And all my fancies whirling like a mill;

Which is a signal to my nerves and brain,

To take a quiet ride in some green lane.[524]

FOOTNOTES:

[476] {373}[Stanzas i.-viii., which are headed "Don Juan, Canto III., July 10, 1819," are in the handwriting of (?) the Countess Guiccioli. Stanzas ix., x., which were written on the same sheet of paper, are in Byron's handwriting. The original MS. opens with stanza xi., "Death laughs," etc. (See letter to Moore, July 12, 1822, Letters, 1901, vi. 96.)]

[477]

["Faut qu' lord Villain-ton ait tout pris;

N'y a plus d' argent dans c' gueux de Paris."

De Béranger, "Complainte d'une de ces Demoiselles a l'Occasion des Affaires du Temps (Février, 1816)," Chansons, 1821, ii. 17.

Compare a retaliatory epigram which appeared in a contemporary newspaper—

"These French petit-maîtres who the spectacle throng,

Say of Wellington's dress qu'il fait vilain ton!

But, at Waterloo, Wellington made the French stare

When their army he dressed à la mode Angleterre!"]

[IT] Oh Wellington (or "Vilainton")——.—[MS. B.]

[478] Query, Ney?—Printer's Devil. [Michel Ney, Duke of Elchingen, "the bravest of the brave" (see Ode from the French, stanza i. Poetical Works, 1900, iii. 431), born January 10, 1769, was arrested August 5, and shot December 7, 1815.]

[479] [The story of the attempted assassination (February 11, 1818) of the Duke of Wellington, which is dismissed by Alison in a few words (Hist. of Europe (1815-1852), 1853, i. 577, 578), occupies many pages of the Supplementary Despatches (1865, xii. 271-546). Byron probably drew his own conclusions as to the Kinnaird-Marinet incident, from the Letter to the Duke of Wellington on the Arrest of M. Marinet, by Lord Kinnaird, 1818. The story, which is full of interest, may be briefly recounted. On January 30, 1818, Lord Kinnaird informed Sir George Murray (Chief of the Staff of the Army of Occupation) that a person, whose name he withheld, had revealed to him the existence of a plot to assassinate the Duke of Wellington. At 12.30 a.m., February 11, 1818, the Duke, on returning to his Hotel, was fired at by an unknown person; and then, but not till then, he wrote to urge Lord Clancarty to advise the Prince Regent to take steps to persuade or force Kinnaird to disclose the name of his informant. A Mr. G.W. Chad, of the Consular Service, was empowered to proceed to Brussels, and to seek an interview with Kinnaird. He carried with him, among other documents, a letter from the Duke to Lord Clancarty, dated February 12, 1818. A postscript contained this intimation: "It may be proper to mention to you that the French Government are disposed to go every length in the way of negotiation with the person mentioned by Lord Kinnaird, or others, to discover the plot."

Kinnaird absolutely declined to give up the name of his informant, but, acting on the strength of the postscript, which had been read but not shown to him, started for Paris with "the great unknown." Some days after their arrival, and while Kinnaird was a guest of the Duke, the man was arrested, and discovered to be one Nicholle or Marinet, who had been appointed receveur under the restored government of Louis XVIII., but during the Cent jours had fled to Belgium, retaining the funds he had amassed during his term of office. Kinnaird regarded this action of the French Government as a breach of faith, and in a "Memorial" to the French Chamber of Peers, and his Letter, maintained that the Duke's postscript implied a promise of a safe conduct for Marinet to and from Paris to Brussels. The Duke, on the other hand, was equally positive (see his letter to Lord Liverpool, May 30, 1818) "that he never intended to have any negotiations with anybody." Kinnaird was a "dog with a bad name." He had been accused (see his Letter to the Earl of Liverpool, 1816, p. 16) of "the promulgation of dangerous opinions," and of intimacy "with persons suspected." The Duke speaks of him as "the friend of Revolutionists"! It is evident that he held the dangerous doctrine that a promise to a rogue is a promise, and that the authorities took a different view of the ethics of the situation. It is clear, too, that the Duke's postscript was ambiguous, but that it did not warrant the assumption that if Marinet went to Paris he should be protected. The air was full of plots. The great Duke despised and was inclined to ignore the pistol or the dagger of the assassin; but he believed that "mischief was afoot," and that "great personages" might or might not be responsible. He was beset by difficulties at every turn, and would have been more than mortal if he had put too favourable a construction on the scruples, or condoned the imprudence of a "friend of Revolutionists."]

[480] {374}[The reference may be to the Duke of Wellington's intimacy with Lady Frances Wedderburn Webster. Byron had "passed that way" himself (see Letters, 1898, ii. 251, note i, 323, etc.), and could hardly attack the Duke on that score.]

[481] ["Thou art the best o' the cut-throats."

Macbeth, act iii. sc. 4, line 17.]

[482] ["I have supped full of horrors."

Macbeth, act v. sc. 5, line 13.]

[483] Vide speeches in Parliament, after the battle of Waterloo.

[484] {376}["I at this time got a post, being for fatigue, with four others. We were sent to break biscuit, and make a mess for Lord Wellington's hounds. I was very hungry, and thought it a good job at the time, as we got our own fill, while we broke the biscuit,—a thing I had not got for some days. When thus engaged, the Prodigal Son was never once out of my mind; and I sighed, as I fed the dogs, over my humble situation and my ruined hopes."—Journal of a Soldier of the 71st Regiment, 1806 to 1815 (Edinburgh, 1822), pp. 132, 133.]

[485] ["We are assured that Epaminondas died so poor that the Thebans buried him at the public charge; for at his death nothing was found in his house but an iron spit."—Plutarch's Fabius Maximus, Langhorne's translation, 1838, p. 140. See, too, Cornelius Nepos, Epam., cap. iii. "Paupertatem adeo facilè perpessus est, ut de Republica nihil præter gloriam ceperit."]

[486] [For Pitt's refusal to accept £100,000 from the merchants of London towards the payment of his debts, or £30,000 from the King's Privy Purse, see Pitt, by Lord Rosebery, 1891. p. 231.]

[IU] {377}To you this one unflattering Muse inscribes.—[MS. erased.]

[IV] {378}

He strips from man his mantle (which is dear

Though beautiful in youth) his carnal skin.—[MS. erased.]

[487] [Hamlet, act iii. sc. i, line 56.]

[488] ["O dura messorum ilia!" etc.-Hor., Epod. iii. 4.]

[IW] Ye iron guts——.—[MS. erased.]

[489] {379}["Ce n'est qu'à l'édition de 1635 qu'on voit paraître la devise que Montaigne avait adoptée, le que sais-je? avec l'emblème des balances. ... Ce que sais-je que Pascal a si sévèrement analysé se lit au chapitre douze du livre ii; il caractérise parfaitement la philosophie de Montaigne; il est la conséquence de cette maxime qu'il avait inscrite en grec sur les solives de sa librairie: 'Il n'est point de raisonnement au quel on n'oppose un raissonnement contraire.'"—Oeuvres de ... Montaigne, 1837, "Notice Bibliographique," p. xvii.]

[490] [Concerning the Pyrrhonists or Sceptics and their master Pyrrho, who held that Truth was incomprehensible (inprensibilis), and that you may not affirm of aught that it be rather this or that, or neither this nor that (οὐ μᾶλλον οὕτως ἔχει τόδε ἢ ἐκείνως ἢ οὐδετέρως), see Aul. Gellii Noct. Attic., lib. xi. cap. v.]

[491] See Othello, [act ii. sc. 3, lines 206, 207: "Well, God's above all, and there be souls must be saved; and there be souls must not be saved—Let's have no more of this."]

[492] {380}[Hamlet, act v. sc. 2, lines 94, 98, 102.]

[493] [For "Lycanthropy," see "The Soldier's Story" in the Satyricôn of Petronius Arbiter, cap. 62; see, too, Letters on Demonology, etc., by Sir W. Scott, 1830, pp. 211, 212.]

[494] [In respect of suavity and forbearance Melancthon was the counterpart of Luther. John Arrowsmith (1602-1657), in his Tractica Sacra, describes him as "Vir in quo cum pietate doctrina, et cum utrâque candor certavit."]

[IX] Like Moses or like Cobbett who have ne'er.

Moses and Cobbet proclaim themselves the "meekest of men." See their writings.—[MS.]

Like Moses who was "very meek" had ne'er.—[MS. erased.]

[495] {381}[See his "Correspondance avec L'Impératrice de Russie," Oeuvres Complètes de Voltaire, 1836, x. 393-477. M. Waliszewski, in his Story of a Throne, 1895, i. 224, has gathered a handful of these flowers of speech: "She is the chief person in the world.... She is the fire and life of nations.... She is a saint.... She is above all saints.... She is equal to the mother of God.... She is the divinity of the North.—Te Catherinam laudamus, te Dominam confitemur, etc., etc."]

[IY] Of everything that ever cursed a nation.—[MS. erased.]

[496] ["It is still more difficult to say which form of government is the worst—all are so bad. As for democracy, it is the worst of the whole; for what is (in fact) democracy?—an Aristocracy of Blackguards."—See "My Dictionary" (May 1, 1821), Letters, 1901, v. 405, 406.]

[IZ] {382}Though priests and slaves may join the servile cry.—[MS. erased.]

[497] In Greece I never saw or heard these animals; but among the ruins of Ephesus I have heard them by hundreds.

[See Childe Harold, Canto IV. stanza cliii. line 6, Poetical Works, 1899, ii. 441; and Siege of Corinth, line 329, ibid., 1900, iii. 462, note 1.]

[JA] Whereas the others hunt for rascal spiders.—[MS. erased.]

[JB] Which still are strongly fluttering to be free.—[MS. erased.]

[498] {383}[Compare The Age of Bronze, line 576, sq., Poetical Works, 1901, v. 570.]

[499] {384}[Nadir Shah, or Thamas Kouli Khan, born November, 1688, invaded India, 1739-40, was assassinated June 19, 1747.]

[JC]

—— went mad and was

Killed because what he swallowed would not pass.—[MS. erased.]

[500] He was killed in a conspiracy, after his temper had been exasperated by his extreme costivity to a degree of insanity.

[To such a height had his madness (attributed to melancholia produced by dropsy) attained, that he actually ordered the Afghan chiefs to rise suddenly upon the Persian guard, and seize the ... chief nobles; but the project being discovered, the intended victims conspired in turn, and a body of them, including Nadir's guard, and the chief of his own tribe of Afshar, entered his tent at midnight, and, after a moment's involuntary pause—when challenged by the deep voice at which they had so often trembled—rushed upon the king, who being brought to the ground by a sabre-stroke, begged for life, and attempted to rise, but soon expired beneath the repeated blows of the conspirators.—The Indian Empire, by R. Montgomery Martin (1857), i. 172.]

[501] [Compare Childe Harold, Canto I. stanza lxvii. line 5, Poetical Works, 1899, ii. 64, note 3.]

[JD] {385}Or the substrata——.—[MS.]

[502] [Compare Preface to Cain, Poetical Works, 1901, V. 210, note 1.]

[503] [Vide ante, Canto VIII. stanza cxxvi. line 9, p. 368.]

[504] {386}[Hamlet, act i. sc. 5, line 189.]

[JE] I never know what's next to come——.—[MS. erased.]

[505] [It is possible that the phrase "painted snows" was suggested by Tooke's description of the winter-garden of the Taurida Palace: "The genial warmth, ... the voluptuous silence that reigns in this enchanting garden, lull the fancy into sweet romantic dreams: we think ourselves in the groves of Italy, while torpid nature, through the windows of this pavilion, announces the severity of a northern winter" (The Life, etc., 1800, iii. 48).]

[JF] {387}O'er limits which mightily——:—[MS. erased.]

[JG]—— in Youth and Glory's pillory.—[MS. erased.]

[506] [In his Notes sur le Don Juanisme (Mercure de France, 1898, xxvi. 66), M. Bruchard says that this phrase defines and summarizes the Byronic Don Juan.]

[JH]

The Empress smiled while all the Orloff frowned—

A numerous family, to whose heart or hand

Mild Catherine owed the chance of being crowned,.—[MS. erased.]

[507] {388}[C.F.P. Masson, in his Mémoires Secrets, etc., 1880, i. 150-178, gives a list of twelve favourites, and in this Canto, Don Juan takes upon himself the characteristics of at least three, Lanskoï, Zoritch (or Zovitch), and Plato Zoubof. For example (p. 167), "Zoritch ... est le seul étranger qu'elle ait osé créer son favori pendant son regne. C'étoit un Servien échappé du bagne de Constantinople où il étoit prisonnier: il parut, pour la première fois, en habit de hussard à la cour. Il éblouit tout le monde par sa beauté, et les vielles dames en parlent encore comme d'un Adonis." M. Waliszewski, in his Romance of an Empress (1894), devotes a chapter to "Private Life and Favouritism" (ii. 234-286), in which he graphically describes the election and inauguration of the Vremienchtchik, "the man of the moment," paramour regnant, and consort of the Empress pro hac vice: "'We may observe in Russia a sort of interregnum in affairs, caused by the displacement of one favourite and the installation of his successor.' ... The interregnums are, however, of very short duration. Only one lasts for several months, between the death of Lanskoï (1784) and the succession of Iermolof.... There is no lack of candidates. The place is good.... Sometimes, too, on the height by the throne, reached at a bound, these spoilt children of fate grow giddy.... It is over in an instant, at an evening reception it is noticed that the Empress has gazed attentively at some obscure lieutenant, presented but just before ... next day it is reported that he has been appointed aide-de-camp to her Majesty. What that means is well known. Next day he finds himself in the special suite of rooms.... The rooms are already vacated, and everything is prepared for the new-comer. All imaginable comfort and luxury ... await him; and, on opening a drawer, he finds a hundred thousand roubles [about £20,000], the usual first gift, a foretaste of Pactolus. That evening, before the assembled court, the Empress appears, leaning familiarly on his arm, and on the stroke of ten, as she retires, the new favourite follows her" (ibid., pp. 246-249).]

[508] [After the death or murder of her husband, Peter III., Catherine Alexievna (1729-1796) (born Sophia Augusta), daughter of the Prince of Anhalt Zerbst, was solemnly crowned (September, 1762) Empress of all the Russias.]

[JI] {389}And almost died for the scarce-fledged Lanskoi.—[MS. erased.]

[509] He was the grande passion of the grande Catherine. See her Lives under the head of "Lanskoi."

[Lanskoi was a youth of as fine and interesting a figure as the imagination can paint. Of all Catherine's favourites, he was the man whom she loved the most. In 1784 he was attacked with a fever, and perished in the arms of her Majesty. When he was no more, Catherine gave herself up to the most poignant grief, and remained three months without going out of her palace of Tzarsko-selo. She afterwards raised a superb monument to his memory. (See Life of Catherine II., by W. Tooke, 1800, iii. 88, 89.)]

[510] [Ten months after the death of Lanskoi, the Empress consoled herself with Iermolof, described, by Bezborodky, as "a modest refined young man, who cultivates the society of serious people." In less than a year this excellent youth is, in turn, displaced by Dmitrief Mamonof. His petit nom was Red Coat, and, for a time, he is a "priceless creature." "He has," says Catherine, "two superb black eyes, with eyebrows outlined as one rarely sees; about the middle height, noble in manner, easy in demeanour." But Mamonof suffered from "scruples of conscience," and, after a while, with Catherine's consent and blessing, was happily married to the Princess Shtcherbatof, a maid of honour, and not, as Byron supposed, a rival "man of the moment."—See The Story of a Throne, by K. Waliszewski, 1895, ii. 135, sq.]

[511] This was written long before the suicide of that person. [For "his parts of speech" compare—

" ... that long mandarin

C-stle-r-agh (whom Fum calls the Confucius of Prose)

Was rehearsing a speech upon Europe's repose

To the deep double bass of the fat Idol's nose."

Moore's Fum and Hum, The Two Birds of Royalty.]

[512] {390}[Compare Beppo, stanza xvii. line 8, Poetical Works, 1901, iv. 165. See, too, letter to Hoppner, December 31, 1819, Letters, 1900, iv. 393.]

[JJ]

Beneath his chisel—

or, Beneath his touches——.—[MS. erased.]

[JK] {391}—— and bound fair Helen in a bond.—[MS. erased.]

[513] Hor., Sat., lib. i. sat. iii. lines 107, 108.

[JL] That Riddle which all read, none understand.—[MS. erased.]

[JM]—— thou Sea which lavest Life's sand.—[MS. erased.]

[514] {392}["Fortune and victory sit on thy helm."—Richard III., act v, sc. 3, line 79.]

[515] ["Catherine had been handsome in her youth, and she preserved a gracefulness and majesty to the last period of her life. She was of a moderate stature, but well proportioned; and as she carried her head very high, she appeared rather tall. She had an open front, an aquiline nose, an agreeable mouth, and her chin, though long, was not mis-shapen. Her hair was auburn, her eyebrows black and rather thick, and her blue eyes had a gentleness which was often affected, but oftener still a mixture of pride. Her physiognomy was not deficient in expression; but this expression never discovered what was passing in the soul of Catherine, or rather it served her the better to disguise it."—Life of Catherine II., by W. Tooke, iii. 381 (translated from Vie de Catherine II. (J.H. Castéra), 1797, ii. 450).]

[516] {393}["His fortune swells him: 'Tis rank, he's married."—Sir Giles Overreach, in Massinger's New Way to pay Old Debts, act v. sc. 1.]

[517] {394}[Hamlet, act iii. sc. iv. lines 58, 59.]

[518] {395}

["Not Cæsar's empress would I deign to prove;

No! make me mistress to the man I love."

Pope, Eloisa to Abelard, lines 87, 88.]

[JN]

O'er whom an Empress her Crown-jewels scattering

Was wed with something better than a ring.—[MS. erased.]

[519] ["Several persons who lived at the court affirm that Catherine had very blue eyes, and not brown, as M. Rulhières has stated."—Life of Catherine II., by W. Tooke, 1800, iii. 382.]

[520] {396}[The historic Catherine (æt. 62) was past her meridian in the spring of 1791.]

[JO] Her figure, and her vigour, and her rigour.—[MS. erased.]

[JP] In its sincere beginning, or dull end.—[MS. erased.]

[JQ] {397}For such all women are just then, no doubt.—[MS.]

[JR]

Of such sensations, in the drowsy drear

After—which shadows the, say—second year.—[MS.]

Of that sad heavy, drowsy, doubly drear

After, which shadows the first—say, year.—[MS. erased.]

[521] [Stanza lxxvi. is not in the MS.]

[522] {398}A Russian estate is always valued by the number of the slaves upon it.

[523] {399}[The "Protassova" (born 1744) was a cousin of the Orlofs. She survived Catherine by many years, and was, writes M. Waliszewski (The Story of a Throne, 1895, ii. 193), "present at the Congress of Vienna, covered with diamonds like a reliquary, and claiming precedence of every one." She is named l'éprouveuse in a note to the Mémoires Secrets, 1800, i. 148.]

[JS] And not be dazzled by its early glare.—[MS. erased.]

[524] End of Canto 9th, Augt. Sept., 1822. B.

Canto X

I

When Newton saw an apple fall, he found
In that slight startle from his contemplation—
’T is said (for I’ll not answer above ground
For any sage’s creed or calculation)—
A mode of proving that the Earth turned round
In a most natural whirl, called “gravitation;”
And this is the sole mortal who could grapple,[804]
Since Adam—with a fall—or with an apple.[805][806]

II

Man fell with apples, and with apples rose,
If this be true; for we must deem the mode
In which Sir Isaac Newton could disclose
Through the then unpaved stars the turnpike road,[807]
A thing to counterbalance human woes:[808]
For ever since immortal man hath glowed
With all kinds of mechanics, and full soon
Steam-engines will conduct him to the moon.

III

And wherefore this exordium?—Why, just now,
In taking up this paltry sheet of paper,
My bosom underwent a glorious glow,
And my internal spirit cut a caper:
And though so much inferior, as I know,
To those who, by the dint of glass and vapour,
Discover stars, and sail in the wind’s eye,
I wish to do as much by Poesy.

IV

In the wind’s eye I have sailed, and sail; but for
The stars, I own my telescope is dim;
But at the least I have shunned the common shore,
And leaving land far out of sight, would skim
The Ocean of Eternity:[809] the roar
Of breakers has not daunted my slight, trim,
But still sea-worthy skiff; and she may float
Where ships have foundered, as doth many a boat.

V

We left our hero, Juan, in the bloom
Of favouritism, but not yet in the blush;—
And far be it from my Muses to presume
(For I have more than one Muse at a push),
To follow him beyond the drawing-room:
It is enough that Fortune found him flush
Of Youth, and Vigour, Beauty, and those things
Which for an instant clip Enjoyment’s wings.

VI

But soon they grow again and leave their nest.
“Oh!” saith the Psalmist, “that I had a dove’s
Pinions to flee away, and be at rest!”
And who that recollects young years and loves—
Though hoary now, and with a withering breast,
And palsied Fancy, which no longer roves
Beyond its dimmed eye’s sphere—but would much rather
Sigh like his son, than cough like his grandfather?

VII

But sighs subside, and tears (even widows’) shrink,
Like Arno[810] in the summer, to a shallow,
So narrow as to shame their wintry brink,
Which threatens inundations deep and yellow!
Such difference doth a few months make. You’d think
Grief a rich field which never would lie fallow;
No more it doth—its ploughs but change their boys,
Who furrow some new soil to sow for joys.

VIII

But coughs will come when sighs depart—and now
And then before sighs cease; for oft the one
Will bring the other, ere the lake-like brow
Is ruffled by a wrinkle, or the Sun
Of Life reached ten o’clock: and while a glow,
Hectic and brief as summer’s day nigh done,
O’erspreads the cheek which seems too pure for clay,
Thousands blaze, love, hope, die—how happy they!—

IX

But Juan was not meant to die so soon:—
We left him in the focus of such glory
As may be won by favour of the moon
Or ladies’ fancies—rather transitory
Perhaps; but who would scorn the month of June,
Because December, with his breath so hoary,
Must come? Much rather should he court the ray,
To hoard up warmth against a wintry day.

X

Besides, he had some qualities which fix
Middle-aged ladies even more than young:
The former know what’s what; while new-fledged chicks
Know little more of Love than what is sung
In rhymes, or dreamt (for Fancy will play tricks)
In visions of those skies from whence Love sprung.
Some reckon women by their suns or years,
I rather think the Moon should date the dears.

XI

And why? because she’s changeable and chaste:
I know no other reason, whatsoe’er
Suspicious people, who find fault in haste,[811]
May choose to tax me with; which is not fair,
Nor flattering to “their temper or their taste,”
As my friend Jeffrey writes with such an air:[812]
However, I forgive him, and I trust
He will forgive himself;—if not, I must.

XII

Old enemies who have become new friends
Should so continue—’t is a point of honour;
And I know nothing which could make amends
For a return to Hatred: I would shun her
Like garlic, howsoever she extends
Her hundred arms and legs, and fain outrun her.
Old flames, new wives, become our bitterest foes—
Converted foes should scorn to join with those.

XIII

This were the worst desertion:—renegadoes,
Even shuffling Southey, that incarnate lie,[813]
Would scarcely join again the “reformadoes,”[814]
Whom he forsook to fill the Laureate’s sty;
And honest men from Iceland to Barbadoes,
Whether in Caledon or Italy,
Should not veer round with every breath, nor seize
To pain, the moment when you cease to please.

XIV

The lawyer and the critic but behold
The baser sides of literature and life,
And nought remains unseen, but much untold,
By those who scour those double vales of strife.
While common men grow ignorantly old,
The lawyer’s brief is like the surgeon’s knife,
Dissecting the whole inside of a question,
And with it all the process of digestion.

XV[815]

A legal broom’s a moral chimney-sweeper,
And that’s the reason he himself’s so dirty;
The endless soot[816] bestows a tint far deeper
Than can be hid by altering his shirt; he
Retains the sable stains of the dark creeper,
At least some twenty-nine do out of thirty,
In all their habits;—not so you, I own;
As Cæsar wore his robe you wear your gown.[817]

XVI

And all our little feuds, at least all mine,
Dear Jeffrey, once my most redoubted foe
(As far as rhyme and criticism combine
To make such puppets of us things below),
Are over: Here’s a health to “Auld Lang Syne!”
I do not know you, and may never know
Your face—but you have acted on the whole
Most nobly, and I own it from my soul.

XVII

And when I use the phrase of “Auld Lang Syne!”
’T is not addressed to you—the more’s the pity
For me, for I would rather take my wine
With you, than aught (save Scott) in your proud city:
But somehow—it may seem a schoolboy’s whine,
And yet I seek not to be grand nor witty,
But I am half a Scot by birth, and bred
A whole one, and my heart flies to my head—[818]

XVIII

As “Auld Lang Syne” brings Scotland, one and all,[819]
Scotch plaids, Scotch snoods, the blue hills, and clear streams,
The Dee—the Don—Balgounie’s brig’s black wall—[820]
All my boy feelings, all my gentler dreams
Of what I then dreamt, clothed in their own pall—
Like Banquo’s offspring—floating past me seems
My childhood, in this childishness of mine:—
I care not—’t is a glimpse of “Auld Lang Syne.”

XIX

And though, as you remember, in a fit
Of wrath and rhyme, when juvenile and curly,
I railed at Scots to show my wrath and wit,
Which must be owned was sensitive and surly,
Yet ’t is in vain such sallies to permit,
They cannot quench young feelings fresh and early:
I “scotched not killed” the Scotchman in my blood,
And love the land of “mountain and of flood.”[821]

XX

Don Juan, who was real, or ideal—
For both are much the same, since what men think
Exists when the once thinkers are less real
Than what they thought, for Mind can never sink,
And ’gainst the Body makes a strong appeal;
And yet ’t is very puzzling on the brink
Of what is called Eternity to stare,
And know no more of what is here, than there;—

XXI

Don Juan grew a very polished Russian—
How we won’t mention, why we need not say:
Few youthful minds can stand the strong concussion
Of any slight temptation in their way;
But his just now were spread as is a cushion
Smoothed for a Monarch’s seat of honour: gay
Damsels, and dances, revels, ready money,
Made ice seem Paradise, and winter sunny.

XXII

The favour of the Empress was agreeable;
And though the duty waxed a little hard,
Young people at his time of life should be able
To come off handsomely in that regard.
He was now growing up like a green tree, able
For Love, War, or Ambition, which reward
Their luckier votaries, till old Age’s tedium
Make some prefer the circulating medium.

XXIII

About this time, as might have been anticipated,
Seduced by Youth and dangerous examples,
Don Juan grew, I fear, a little dissipated;
Which is a sad thing, and not only tramples
On our fresh feelings, but—as being participated
With all kinds of incorrigible samples
Of frail humanity—must make us selfish,
And shut our souls up in us like a shell-fish.

XXIV

This we pass over. We will also pass
The usual progress of intrigues between
Unequal matches, such as are, alas!
A young Lieutenant’s with a not old Queen,
But one who is not so youthful as she was
In all the royalty of sweet seventeen.[822]
Sovereigns may sway materials, but not matter,
And wrinkles, the d⸺d democrats! won’t flatter.

XXV

And Death, the Sovereign’s Sovereign, though the great
Gracchus of all mortality, who levels,
With his Agrarian laws,[823] the high estate
Of him who feasts, and fights, and roars, and revels,
To one small grass-grown patch (which must await
Corruption for its crop) with the poor devils
Who never had a foot of land till now—
Death’s a reformer—all men must allow.

XXVI

He lived (not Death, but Juan) in a hurry
Of waste, and haste, and glare, and gloss, and glitter,
In this gay clime of bear-skins black and furry—
Which (though I hate to say a thing that’s bitter)
Peep out sometimes, when things are in a flurry,
Through all the “purple and fine linen,” fitter
For Babylon’s than Russia’s royal harlot—
And neutralise her outward show of scarlet.

XXVII

And this same state we won’t describe: we would
Perhaps from hearsay, or from recollection:
But getting nigh grim Dante’s “obscure wood,”[824]
That horrid equinox, that hateful section
Of human years—that half-way house—that rude
Hut, whence wise travellers drive with circumspection[825]
Life’s sad post-horses o’er the dreary frontier
Of Age, and looking back to Youth, give one tear;—

XXVIII

I won’t describe—that is, if I can help
Description; and I won’t reflect—that is,
If I can stave off thought, which—as a whelp
Clings to its teat—sticks to me through the abyss
Of this odd labyrinth; or as the kelp
Holds by the rock; or as a lover’s kiss
Drains its first draught of lips:—but, as I said,
I won’t philosophise, and will be read.

XXIX

Juan, instead of courting courts, was courted—
A thing which happens rarely: this he owed
Much to his youth, and much to his reported
Valour; much also to the blood he showed,
Like a race-horse; much to each dress he sported,
Which set the beauty off in which he glowed,
As purple clouds befringe the sun; but most
He owed to an old woman and his post.

XXX

He wrote to Spain;—and all his near relations,
Perceiving he was in a handsome way
Of getting on himself, and finding stations
For cousins also, answered the same day.
Several prepared themselves for emigrations;
And eating ices, were o’erheard to say,
That with the addition of a slight pelisse,
Madrid’s and Moscow’s climes were of a piece.

XXXI

His mother, Donna Inez, finding, too,
That in the lieu of drawing on his banker,
Where his assets were waxing rather few,
He had brought his spending to a handsome anchor—
Replied, “that she was glad to see him through
Those pleasures after which wild youth will hanker;
As the sole sign of Man’s being in his senses
Is—learning to reduce his past expenses.[826]

XXXII

“She also recommended him to God,
And no less to God’s Son, as well as Mother,
Warned him against Greek worship, which looks odd
In Catholic eyes; but told him, too, to smother
Outward dislike, which don’t look well abroad;
Informed him that he had a little brother
Born in a second wedlock; and above
All, praised the Empress’s maternal love.

XXXIII

“She could not too much give her approbation
Unto an Empress, who preferred young men
Whose age, and what was better still, whose nation
And climate, stopped all scandal (now and then);—
At home it might have given her some vexation;
But where thermometers sink down to ten,
Or five, or one, or zero, she could never
Believe that Virtue thawed before the river.”[827]

XXXIV

Oh for a forty-parson power[828]—to chant
Thy praise, Hypocrisy! Oh for a hymn
Loud as the virtues thou dost loudly vaunt,
Not practise! Oh for trump of Cherubim!
Or the ear-trumpet of my good old aunt,[829]
Who, though her spectacles at last grew dim,
Drew quiet consolation through its hint,
When she no more could read the pious print.

XXXV

She was no Hypocrite at least, poor soul,
But went to heaven in as sincere a way
As anybody on the elected roll,
Which portions out upon the Judgment Day
Heaven’s freeholds, in a sort of Doomsday scroll,
Such as the conqueror William did repay
His knights with, lotting others’ properties
Into some sixty thousand new knights’ fees.

XXXVI

I can’t complain, whose ancestors are there,
Erneis, Radulphus—eight-and-forty manors
(If that my memory doth not greatly err)
Were their reward for following Billy’s banners:[830]
And though I can’t help thinking ’t was scarce fair
To strip the Saxons of their hydes[831] like tanners;
Yet as they founded churches with the produce,
You’ll deem, no doubt, they put it to a good use.[832]

XXXVII

The gentle Juan flourished, though at times
He felt like other plants called sensitive,
Which shrink from touch, as Monarchs do from rhymes,
Save such as Southey can afford to give.
Perhaps he longed in bitter frosts for climes
In which the Neva’s ice would cease to live
Before May-day: perhaps, despite his duty,
In Royalty’s vast arms he sighed for Beauty:

XXXVIII

Perhaps—but, sans perhaps, we need not seek[833]
For causes young or old: the canker-worm
Will feed upon the fairest, freshest cheek,
As well as further drain the withered form:
Care, like a housekeeper, brings every week
His bills in, and however we may storm,
They must be paid: though six days smoothly run,
The seventh will bring blue devils or a dun.

XXXIX

I don’t know how it was, but he grew sick:
The Empress was alarmed, and her physician
(The same who physicked Peter) found the tick
Of his fierce pulse betoken a condition
Which augured of the dead, however quick
Itself, and showed a feverish disposition;
At which the whole Court was extremely troubled,
The Sovereign shocked, and all his medicines doubled.

XL

Low were the whispers, manifold the rumours:
Some said he had been poisoned by Potemkin;
Others talked learnedly of certain tumours,
Exhaustion, or disorders of the same kin;[834]
Some said ’t was a concoction of the humours,
Which with the blood too readily will claim kin:
Others again were ready to maintain,
“ ’T was only the fatigue of last campaign.”

XLI

But here is one prescription out of many:
“Sodae sulphat. ʒvj. ʒfs. Mannae optim.
Aq. fervent. f. ℥ ifs. ʒij. tinct. Sennae
Haustus” (And here the surgeon came and cupped him)
“℞ Pulv. Com. gr. iij. Ipecacuanhæ”
(With more beside if Juan had not stopped ’em).
“Bolus Potassae Sulphuret. sumendus,
Et haustus ter in die capiendus.”

XLII

This is the way physicians mend or end us,
Secundum artem: but although we sneer
In health—when ill, we call them to attend us,
Without the least propensity to jeer;
While that “hiatus maxime deflendus”
To be filled up by spade or mattock’s near,
Instead of gliding graciously down Lethe,
We tease mild Baillie,[835] or soft Abernethy.

XLIII

Juan demurred at this first notice to
Quit; and though Death had threatened an ejection,
His youth and constitution bore him through,
And sent the doctors in a new direction.
But still his state was delicate: the hue
Of health but flickered with a faint reflection
Along his wasted cheek, and seemed to gravel
The faculty—who said that he must travel.

XLIV

The climate was too cold, they said, for him,
Meridian-born, to bloom in. This opinion
Made the chaste Catherine look a little grim,
Who did not like at first to lose her minion:
But when she saw his dazzling eye wax dim,
And drooping like an eagle’s with clipt pinion,
She then resolved to send him on a mission,
But in a style becoming his condition.

XLV

There was just then a kind of a discussion,
A sort of treaty or negotiation,
Between the British cabinet and Russian,
Maintained with all the due prevarication
With which great states such things are apt to push on;
Something about the Baltic’s navigation,
Hides, train-oil, tallow, and the rights of Thetis,
Which Britons deem their uti possidetis.

XLVI

So Catherine, who had a handsome way
Of fitting out her favourites, conferred
This secret charge on Juan, to display
At once her royal splendour, and reward
His services. He kissed hands the next day,
Received instructions how to play his card,
Was laden with all kinds of gifts and honours,
Which showed what great discernment was the donor’s.

XLVII

But she was lucky, and luck’s all. Your Queens
Are generally prosperous in reigning—
Which puzzles us to know what Fortune means:—
But to continue—though her years were waning,
Her climacteric teased her like her teens;
And though her dignity brooked no complaining,
So much did Juan’s setting off distress her,
She could not find at first a fit successor.

XLVIII

But Time, the comforter, will come at last;
And four-and-twenty hours, and twice that number
Of candidates requesting to be placed,
Made Catherine taste next night a quiet slumber:—
Not that she meant to fix again in haste,
Nor did she find the quantity encumber,
But always choosing with deliberation,
Kept the place open for their emulation.

XLIX

While this high post of honour’s in abeyance,
For one or two days, reader, we request
You’ll mount with our young hero the conveyance
Which wafted him from Petersburgh: the best
Barouche, which had the glory to display once
The fair Czarina’s autocratic crest,
When, a new Iphigene, she went to Tauris,
Was given to her favourite,[836] and now bore his.

L

A bull-dog, and a bullfinch, and an ermine,
All private favourites of Don Juan;—for
(Let deeper sages the true cause determine)
He had a kind of inclination, or
Weakness, for what most people deem mere vermin,
Live animals: an old maid of threescore
For cats and birds more penchant ne’er displayed,
Although he was not old, nor even a maid;—

LI

The animals aforesaid occupied
Their station: there were valets, secretaries,
In other vehicles; but at his side
Sat little Leila, who survived the parries
He made ’gainst Cossacque sabres in the wide
Slaughter of Ismail. Though my wild Muse varies
Her note, she don’t forget the infant girl
Whom he preserved, a pure and living pearl.

LII

Poor little thing! She was as fair as docile,
And with that gentle, serious character,
As rare in living beings as a fossile
Man, ’midst thy mouldy mammoths, “grand Cuvier!”[837]
Ill fitted was her ignorance to jostle
With this o’erwhelming world, where all must err:
But she was yet but ten years old, and therefore
Was tranquil, though she knew not why or wherefore.

LIII

Don Juan loved her, and she loved him, as
Nor brother, father, sister, daughter love.—
I cannot tell exactly what it was;
He was not yet quite old enough to prove
Parental feelings, and the other class,
Called brotherly affection, could not move
His bosom—for he never had a sister:
Ah! if he had—how much he would have missed her!

LIV

And still less was it sensual; for besides
That he was not an ancient debauchee,
(Who like sour fruit, to stir their veins’ salt tides,
As acids rouse a dormant alkali,)[838]
Although (’t will happen as our planet guides)
His youth was not the chastest that might be,
There was the purest Platonism at bottom
Of all his feelings—only he forgot ’em.

LV

Just now there was no peril of temptation;
He loved the infant orphan he had saved,
As patriots (now and then) may love a nation;
His pride, too, felt that she was not enslaved
Owing to him;—as also her salvation
Through his means and the Church’s might be paved.
But one thing’s odd, which here must be inserted,
The little Turk refused to be converted.

LVI

’T was strange enough she should retain the impression
Through such a scene of change, and dread, and slaughter;
But though three Bishops told her the transgression,
She showed a great dislike to holy water;
She also had no passion for confession;
Perhaps she had nothing to confess:—no matter,
Whate’er the cause, the Church made little of it—
She still held out that Mahomet was a prophet.

LVII

In fact, the only Christian she could bear
Was Juan; whom she seemed to have selected
In place of what her home and friends once were.
He naturally loved what he protected:
And thus they formed a rather curious pair,
A guardian green in years, a ward connected
In neither clime, time, blood, with her defender;
And yet this want of ties made theirs more tender.

LVIII

They journeyed on through Poland and through Warsaw,
Famous for mines of salt and yokes of iron:
Through Courland also, which that famous farce saw
Which gave her dukes the graceless name of “Biron.”[839]
’T is the same landscape which the modern Mars saw,
Who marched to Moscow, led by Fame, the Siren!
To lose by one month’s frost some twenty years
Of conquest, and his guard of Grenadiers.

LIX

Let this not seem an anti-climax:—“Oh!
My guard! my old guard!”[840] exclaimed that god of clay.
Think of the Thunderer’s falling down below
Carotid-artery-cutting Castlereagh![841]
Alas! that glory should be chilled by snow!
But should we wish to warm us on our way
Through Poland, there is Kosciusko’s name
Might scatter fire through ice, like Hecla’s flame.

LX

From Poland they came on through Prussia Proper,
And Königsberg, the capital, whose vaunt,
Besides some veins of iron, lead, or copper,
Has lately been the great Professor Kant.[842]
Juan, who cared not a tobacco-stopper
About philosophy, pursued his jaunt
To Germany, whose somewhat tardy millions
Have princes who spur more than their postilions.

LXI

And thence through Berlin, Dresden, and the like,
Until he reached the castellated Rhine:—
Ye glorious Gothic scenes! how much ye strike
All phantasies, not even excepting mine!
A grey wall, a green ruin, rusty pike,
Make my soul pass the equinoctial line
Between the present and past worlds, and hover
Upon their airy confines, half-seas-over.

LXII

But Juan posted on through Mannheim, Bonn,
Which Drachenfels[843] frowns over like a spectre
Of the good feudal times for ever gone,
On which I have not time just now to lecture.
From thence he was drawn onwards to Cologne,
A city which presents to the inspector
Eleven thousand maiden heads of bone.
The greatest number flesh hath ever known.[844]

LXIII

From thence to Holland’s Hague and Helvoetsluys,
That water-land of Dutchmen and of ditches,
Where juniper expresses its best juice,
The poor man’s sparkling substitute for riches.
Senates and sages have condemned its use—
But to deny the mob a cordial, which is
Too often all the clothing, meat, or fuel,
Good government has left them, seems but cruel.

LXIV

Here he embarked, and with a flowing sail
Went bounding for the Island of the free,
Towards which the impatient wind blew half a gale;
High dashed the spray, the bows dipped in the sea,
And sea-sick passengers turned somewhat pale;
But Juan, seasoned, as he well might be,
By former voyages, stood to watch the skiffs
Which passed, or catch the first glimpse of the cliffs.

LXV

At length they rose, like a white wall along
The blue sea’s border; and Don Juan felt—
What even young strangers feel a little strong
At the first sight of Albion’s chalky belt—
A kind of pride that he should be among
Those haughty shopkeepers, who sternly dealt
Their goods and edicts out from pole to pole,
And made the very billows pay them toll.

LXVI

I’ve no great cause to love that spot of earth,
Which holds what might have been the noblest nation;
But though I owe it little but my birth,
I feel a mixed regret and veneration
For its decaying fame and former worth.
Seven years (the usual term of transportation)
Of absence lay one’s old resentments level,
When a man’s country’s going to the devil.

LXVII

Alas! could she but fully, truly, know
How her great name is now throughout abhorred;
How eager all the Earth is for the blow
Which shall lay bare her bosom to the sword;
How all the nations deem her their worst foe,
That worse than worst of foes, the once adored
False friend, who held out Freedom to Mankind,
And now would chain them—to the very mind;—

LXVIII

Would she be proud, or boast herself the free,
Who is but first of slaves? The nations are
In prison—but the gaoler, what is he?
No less a victim to the bolt and bar.
Is the poor privilege to turn the key
Upon the captive, Freedom? He’s as far
From the enjoyment of the earth and air
Who watches o’er the chain, as they who wear.

LXIX

Don Juan now saw Albion’s earliest beauties,
Thy cliffs, dear Dover! harbour, and hotel;
Thy custom-house, with all its delicate duties;
Thy waiters running mucks at every bell;
Thy packets, all whose passengers are booties
To those who upon land or water dwell;
And last, not least, to strangers uninstructed,
Thy long, long bills, whence nothing is deducted.

LXX

Juan, though careless, young, and magnifique,
And rich in rubles, diamonds, cash, and credit,
Who did not limit much his bills per week,
Yet stared at this a little, though he paid it—
(His Maggior Duomo, a smart, subtle Greek,
Before him summed the awful scroll and read it):
But, doubtless, as the air—though seldom sunny—
Is free, the respiration’s worth the money.

LXXI

On with the horses! Off to Canterbury!
Tramp, tramp o’er pebble, and splash, splash through puddle;
Hurrah! how swiftly speeds the post so merry!
Not like slow Germany, wherein they muddle
Along the road,[845] as if they went to bury
Their fare; and also pause besides, to fuddle
With “schnapps”—sad dogs! whom “Hundsfot,” or “Verflucter,”[846]
Affect no more than lightning a conductor.[847]

LXXII

Now there is nothing gives a man such spirits,
Leavening his blood as cayenne doth a curry,
As going at full speed—no matter where its
Direction be, so ’t is but in a hurry,
And merely for the sake of its own merits;
For the less cause there is for all this flurry,
The greater is the pleasure in arriving
At the great end of travel—which is driving.

LXXIII

They saw at Canterbury the cathedral;
Black Edward’s helm, and Becket’s bloody stone,
Were pointed out as usual by the bedral,
In the same quaint, uninterested tone:—
There’s glory again for you, gentle reader! All
Ends in a rusty casque and dubious bone,[848]
Half-solved into these sodas or magnesias,
Which form that bitter draught, the human species.

LXXIV

The effect on Juan was of course sublime:
He breathed a thousand Cressys, as he saw
That casque, which never stooped except to Time.
Even the bold Churchman’s tomb excited awe,
Who died in the then great attempt to climb
O’er Kings, who now at least must talk of Law
Before they butcher. Little Leila gazed,
And asked why such a structure had been raised:

LXXV

And being told it was “God’s House,” she said
He was well lodged, but only wondered how
He suffered Infidels in his homestead,
The cruel Nazarenes, who had laid low
His holy temples in the lands which bred
The True Believers;—and her infant brow
Was bent with grief that Mahomet should resign
A mosque so noble, flung like pearls to swine.

LXXVI

On! on! through meadows, managed like a garden,
A paradise of hops and high production;
For, after years of travel by a bard in
Countries of greater heat, but lesser suction,
A green field is a sight which makes him pardon
The absence of that more sublime construction,
Which mixes up vines—olives—precipices—
Glaciers—volcanoes—oranges and ices.

LXXVII

And when I think upon a pot of beer—
But I won’t weep!—and so drive on, postilions!
As the smart boys spurred fast in their career,
Juan admired these highways of free millions—
A country in all senses the most dear
To foreigner or native, save some silly ones,
Who “kick against the pricks” just at this juncture,
And for their pains get only a fresh puncture.[849]

LXXVIII

What a delightful thing’s a turnpike road!
So smooth, so level, such a mode of shaving
The Earth, as scarce the eagle in the broad
Air can accomplish, with his wide wings waving.
Had such been cut in Phaeton’s time, the god
Had told his son to satisfy his craving
With the York mail;—but onward as we roll,
Surgit amari aliquid—the toll![850]

LXXIX

Alas! how deeply painful is all payment!
Take lives—take wives—take aught except men’s purses:
As Machiavel shows those in purple raiment,
Such is the shortest way to general curses.[851]
They hate a murderer much less than a claimant
On that sweet ore which everybody nurses.—
Kill a man’s family, and he may brook it,
But keep your hands out of his breeches’ pocket:

LXXX

So said the Florentine: ye monarchs, hearken
To your instructor. Juan now was borne,
Just as the day began to wane and darken,
O’er the high hill, which looks with pride or scorn
Toward the great city.—Ye who have a spark in
Your veins of Cockney spirit, smile or mourn
According as you take things well or ill;—
Bold Britons, we are now on Shooter’s Hill!

LXXXI

The Sun went down, the smoke rose up, as from
A half-unquenched volcano, o’er a space
Which well beseemed the “Devil’s drawing-room,”
As some have qualified that wondrous place:
But Juan felt, though not approaching Home,
As one who, though he were not of the race,
Revered the soil, of those true sons the mother,
Who butchered half the earth, and bullied t’ other.[852]

LXXXII

A mighty mass of brick, and smoke, and shipping,
Dirty and dusky, but as wide as eye
Could reach, with here and there a sail just skipping
In sight, then lost amidst the forestry
Of masts; a wilderness of steeples peeping
On tiptoe through their sea-coal canopy;
A huge, dun Cupola, like a foolscap crown
On a fool’s head—and there is London Town!

LXXXIII

But Juan saw not this: each wreath of smoke
Appeared to him but as the magic vapour
Of some alchymic furnace, from whence broke
The wealth of worlds (a wealth of tax and paper):
The gloomy clouds, which o’er it as a yoke
Are bowed, and put the Sun out like a taper,
Were nothing but the natural atmosphere,
Extremely wholesome, though but rarely clear.

LXXXIV

He paused—and so will I; as doth a crew
Before they give their broadside. By and by,
My gentle countrymen, we will renew
Our old acquaintance; and at least I’ll try
To tell you truths you will not take as true,
Because they are so;—a male Mrs. Fry,[853]
With a soft besom will I sweep your halls,
And brush a web or two from off the walls.

LXXXV

Oh Mrs. Fry! Why go to Newgate? Why
Preach to poor rogues? And wherefore not begin
With Carlton, or with other houses? Try
Your hand at hardened and imperial Sin.
To mend the People’s an absurdity,
A jargon, a mere philanthropic din,
Unless you make their betters better:—Fie!
I thought you had more religion, Mrs. Fry.

LXXXVI

Teach them the decencies of good threescore;
Cure them of tours, hussar and highland dresses;
Tell them that youth once gone returns no more,
That hired huzzas redeem no land’s distresses;
Tell them Sir William Curtis[854] is a bore,
Too dull even for the dullest of excesses—
The witless Falstaff of a hoary Hal,
A fool whose bells have ceased to ring at all.

LXXXVII

Tell them, though it may be, perhaps, too late—
On Life’s worn confine, jaded, bloated, sated—
To set up vain pretence of being great,
’T is not so to be good; and, be it stated,
The worthiest kings have ever loved least state:
And tell them—But you won’t, and I have prated
Just now enough; but, by and by, I’ll prattle
Like Roland’s horn[855] in Roncesvalles’ battle.[856][857]

Canto XI

I.

When Bishop Berkeley said "there was no matter,"[562]

And proved it—'t was no matter what he said:

They say his system 't is in vain to batter,

Too subtle for the airiest human head;

And yet who can believe it? I would shatter

Gladly all matters down to stone or lead,

Or adamant, to find the World a spirit,

And wear my head, denying that I wear it.

II.

What a sublime discovery 't was to make the

Universe universal egotism,

That all's ideal—all ourselves!—I'll stake the

World (be it what you will) that that's no schism.

Oh Doubt!—if thou be'st Doubt, for which some take thee,

But which I doubt extremely—thou sole prism

Of the Truth's rays, spoil not my draught of spirit!

Heaven's brandy, though our brain can hardly bear it.

III.

For ever and anon comes Indigestion

(Not the most "dainty Ariel"),[563] and perplexes

Our soarings with another sort of question:

And that which after all my spirit vexes,

Is, that I find no spot where Man can rest eye on,

Without confusion of the sorts and sexes,

Of Beings, Stars, and this unriddled wonder,

The World, which at the worst's a glorious blunder—

IV.

If it be chance—or, if it be according

To the old text, still better:—lest it should

Turn out so, we 'll say nothing 'gainst the wording,

As several people think such hazards rude.

They're right; our days are too brief for affording

Space to dispute what no one ever could

Decide, and everybody one day will

Know very clearly—or at least lie still.

V.

And therefore will I leave off metaphysical

Discussion, which is neither here nor there:

If I agree that what is, is; then this I call

Being quite perspicuous and extremely fair;

The truth is, I've grown lately rather phthisical:[564]

I don't know what the reason is—the air

Perhaps; but as I suffer from the shocks

Of illness, I grow much more orthodox.

VI.

The first attack at once proved the Divinity

(But that I never doubted, nor the Devil);

The next, the Virgin's mystical virginity;

The third, the usual Origin of Evil;

The fourth at once established the whole Trinity

On so uncontrovertible a level,

That I devoutly wished the three were four—

On purpose to believe so much the more.

VII.

To our theme.—The man who has stood on the Acropolis,

And looked down over Attica; or he

Who has sailed where picturesque Constantinople is,

Or seen Timbuctoo, or hath taken tea

In small-eyed China's crockery-ware metropolis,

Or sat amidst the bricks of Nineveh,[KK]

May not think much of London's first appearance—

But ask him what he thinks of it a year hence!

VIII.

Don Juan had got out on Shooter's Hill;

Sunset the time, the place the same declivity

Which looks along that vale of Good and Ill

Where London streets ferment in full activity,

While everything around was calm and still,

Except the creak of wheels, which on their pivot he

Heard,—and that bee-like, bubbling, busy hum

Of cities, that boil over with their scum:—

IX.

I say, Don Juan, wrapped in contemplation,

Walked on behind his carriage, o'er the summit,

And lost in wonder of so great a nation,

Gave way to 't, since he could not overcome it.

"And here," he cried, "is Freedom's chosen station;

Here peals the People's voice, nor can entomb it

Racks—prisons—inquisitions; Resurrection

Awaits it, each new meeting or election.

X.

"Here are chaste wives, pure lives; here people pay

But what they please; and if that things be dear,

'T is only that they love to throw away

Their cash, to show how much they have a-year.

Here laws are all inviolate—none lay

Traps for the traveller—every highway's clear—

Here"—he was interrupted by a knife,

With—"Damn your eyes! your money or your life!"—

XI.

These free-born sounds proceeded from four pads

In ambush laid, who had perceived him loiter

Behind his carriage; and, like handy lads,

Had seized the lucky hour to reconnoitre,

In which the heedless gentleman who gads

Upon the road, unless he prove a fighter,

May find himself within that isle of riches

Exposed to lose his life as well as breeches.

XII.

Juan, who did not understand a word

Of English, save their shibboleth, "God damn!"[565]

And even that he had so rarely heard,

He sometimes thought 't was only their "Salām,"

Or "God be with you!"—and 't is not absurd

To think so,—for half English as I am

(To my misfortune), never can I say

I heard them wish "God with you," save that way;—

XIII.

Juan yet quickly understood their gesture,

And being somewhat choleric and sudden,

Drew forth a pocket pistol from his vesture,

And fired it into one assailant's pudding—

Who fell, as rolls an ox o'er in his pasture,

And roared out, as he writhed his native mud in,

Unto his nearest follower or henchman,

"Oh Jack! I'm floored by that 'ere bloody Frenchman!"

XIV.

On which Jack and his train set off at speed,

And Juan's suite, late scattered at a distance,

Came up, all marvelling at such a deed,

And offering, as usual, late assistance.

Juan, who saw the moon's late minion[566] bleed

As if his veins would pour out his existence,

Stood calling out for bandages and lint,

And wished he had been less hasty with his flint.

XV.

"Perhaps," thought he, "it is the country's wont

To welcome foreigners in this way: now

I recollect some innkeepers who don't

Differ, except in robbing with a bow,

In lieu of a bare blade and brazen front—

But what is to be done? I can't allow

The fellow to lie groaning on the road:

So take him up—I'll help you with the load."

XVI.

But ere they could perform this pious duty,

The dying man cried, "Hold! I've got my gruel!

Oh! for a glass of max![567] We've missed our booty;

Let me die where I am!" And as the fuel

Of Life shrunk in his heart, and thick and sooty

The drops fell from his death-wound, and he drew ill

His breath,—he from his swelling throat untied

A kerchief, crying, "Give Sal that!"—and died.

XVII.

The cravat stained with bloody drops fell down

Before Don Juan's feet: he could not tell

Exactly why it was before him thrown,

Nor what the meaning of the man's farewell.

Poor Tom was once a kiddy upon town,

A thorough varmint, and a real swell,

Full flash,[568] all fancy, until fairly diddled,

His pockets first and then his body riddled.

XVIII.

Don Juan, having done the best he could

In all the circumstances of the case,

As soon as "Crowner's quest"[569] allowed, pursued

His travels to the capital apace;—

Esteeming it a little hard he should

In twelve hours' time, and very little space,

Have been obliged to slay a free-born native

In self-defence: this made him meditative.

XIX.

He from the world had cut off a great man,

Who in his time had made heroic bustle.

Who in a row like Tom could lead the van,

Booze in the ken, or at the spellken hustle?

Who queer a flat?[570] Who (spite of Bow-street's ban)

On the high toby-spice so flash the muzzle?

Who on a lark with black-eyed Sal (his blowing),

So prime—so swell—so nutty—and so knowing?[KL][571]

XX.

But Tom's no more—and so no more of Tom.

Heroes must die; and by God's blessing 't is

Not long before the most of them go home.

Hail! Thamis, hail! Upon thy verge it is

That Juan's chariot, rolling like a drum

In thunder, holds the way it can't well miss,

Through Kennington and all the other "tons,"

Which make us wish ourselves in town at once;—

XXI.

Through Groves, so called as being void of trees,

(Like lucus from no light); through prospects named

Mount Pleasant, as containing nought to please,

Nor much to climb; through little boxes framed

Of bricks, to let the dust in at your ease,

With "To be let," upon their doors proclaimed;

Through "Rows" most modestly called "Paradise,"[572]

Which Eve might quit without much sacrifice;—[KM]

XXII.

Through coaches, drays, choked turnpikes, and a whirl

Of wheels, and roar of voices, and confusion;

Here taverns wooing to a pint of "purl,"[573]

There mails fast flying off like a delusion;

There barbers' blocks with periwigs in curl

In windows; here the lamplighter's infusion

Slowly distilled into the glimmering glass

(For in those days we had not got to gas—);[KN][574]

XXIII.

Through this, and much, and more, is the approach

Of travellers to mighty Babylon:

Whether they come by horse, or chaise, or coach,

With slight exceptions, all the ways seem one.

I could say more, but do not choose to encroach

Upon the Guide-book's privilege. The Sun

Had set some time, and night was on the ridge

Of twilight, as the party crossed the bridge.

XXIV.

That's rather fine, the gentle sound of Thamis—

Who vindicates a moment, too, his stream—

Though hardly heard through multifarious "damme's:"

The lamps of Westminster's more regular gleam,

The breadth of pavement, and yon shrine where Fame is

A spectral resident—whose pallid beam

In shape of moonshine hovers o'er the pile—

Make this a sacred part of Albion's isle.

XXV.

The Druids' groves are gone—so much the better:

Stonehenge is not—but what the devil is it?—

But Bedlam still exists with its sage fetter,

That madmen may not bite you on a visit;

The Bench too seats or suits full many a debtor;

The Mansion House,[575] too (though some people quiz it),

To me appears a stiff yet grand erection;

But then the Abbey's worth the whole collection.

XXVI.

The line of lights,[576] too, up to Charing Cross,

Pall Mall, and so forth, have a coruscation

Like gold as in comparison to dross,

Matched with the Continent's illumination,

Whose cities Night by no means deigns to gloss.

The French were not yet a lamp-lighting nation,

And when they grew so—on their new-found lantern,

Instead of wicks, they made a wicked man turn.[577]

XXVII.

A row of Gentlemen along the streets

Suspended may illuminate mankind,

As also bonfires made of country seats;

But the old way is best for the purblind:

The other looks like phosphorus on sheets,

A sort of ignis fatuus to the mind,

Which, though 't is certain to perplex and frighten,

Must burn more mildly ere it can enlighten.

XXVIII.

But London's so well lit, that if Diogenes

Could recommence to hunt his honest man,

And found him not amidst the various progenies

Of this enormous City's spreading span,

'T were not for want of lamps to aid his dodging his

Yet undiscovered treasure. What I can,

I've done to find the same throughout Life's journey,

But see the World is only one attorney.

XXIX.

Over the stones still rattling, up Pall Mall,

Through crowds and carriages, but waxing thinner

As thundered knockers broke the long sealed spell

Of doors 'gainst duns, and to an early dinner

Admitted a small party as night fell,—

Don Juan, our young diplomatic sinner,

Pursued his path, and drove past some hotels,

St. James's Palace, and St. James's "Hells."[578]

XXX.

They reached the hotel: forth streamed from the front door[KO]

A tide of well-clad waiters, and around

The mob stood, and as usual several score

Of those pedestrian Paphians who abound

In decent London when the daylight's o'er;

Commodious but immoral, they are found

Useful, like Malthus, in promoting marriage.—

But Juan now is stepping from his carriage

XXXI.

Into one of the sweetest of hotels,[KP][579]

Especially for foreigners—and mostly

For those whom favour or whom Fortune swells,

And cannot find a bill's small items costly.

There many an envoy either dwelt or dwells

(The den of many a diplomatic lost lie),

Until to some conspicuous square they pass,

And blazon o'er the door their names in brass.

XXXII.

Juan, whose was a delicate commission,

Private, though publicly important, bore

No title to point out with due precision

The exact affair on which he was sent o'er.

'T was merely known, that on a secret mission

A foreigner of rank had graced our shore,

Young, handsome, and accomplished, who was said

(In whispers) to have turned his Sovereign's head.

XXXIII.

Some rumour also of some strange adventures

Had gone before him, and his wars and loves;

And as romantic heads are pretty painters,

And, above all, an Englishwoman's roves[KQ]

Into the excursive, breaking the indentures

Of sober reason, wheresoe'er it moves,

He found himself extremely in the fashion,

Which serves our thinking people for a passion.

XXXIV.

I don't mean that they are passionless, but quite

The contrary; but then 't is in the head;

Yet as the consequences are as bright

As if they acted with the heart instead,

What after all can signify the site

Of ladies' lucubrations? So they lead

In safety to the place for which you start,

What matters if the road be head or heart?

XXXV.

Juan presented in the proper place,

To proper placemen, every Russ credential;

And was received with all the due grimace

By those who govern in the mood potential,

Who, seeing a handsome stripling with smooth face,

Thought (what in state affairs is most essential),

That they as easily might do the youngster,

As hawks may pounce upon a woodland songster.

XXXVI.

They erred, as agéd men will do; but by

And by we'll talk of that; and if we don't,

'T will be because our notion is not high

Of politicians and their double front,

Who live by lies, yet dare not boldly lie:—

Now what I love in women is, they won't

Or can't do otherwise than lie—but do it

So well, the very Truth seems falsehood to it.

XXXVII.

And, after all, what is a lie? 'T is but

The truth in masquerade; and I defy[KR]

Historians—heroes—lawyers—priests, to put

A fact without some leaven of a lie.

The very shadow of true Truth would shut

Up annals—revelations—poesy,

And prophecy—except it should be dated

Some years before the incidents related.

XXXVIII.

Praised be all liars and all lies! Who now

Can tax my mild Muse with misanthropy?

She rings the World's "Te Deum," and her brow

Blushes for those who will not:—but to sigh

Is idle; let us like most others bow,

Kiss hands—feet—any part of Majesty,

After the good example of "Green Erin,"[580]

Whose shamrock now seems rather worse for wearing.[KS]

XXXIX.

Don Juan was presented, and his dress

And mien excited general admiration—

I don't know which was more admired or less:

One monstrous diamond drew much observation,

Which Catherine in a moment of "ivresse"

(In Love or Brandy's fervent fermentation),

Bestowed upon him, as the public learned;

And, to say truth, it had been fairly earned.

XL.

Besides the ministers and underlings,

Who must be courteous to the accredited

Diplomatists of rather wavering Kings,

Until their royal riddle's fully read,

The very clerks,—those somewhat dirty springs

Of Office, or the House of Office, fed

By foul corruption into streams,—even they

Were hardly rude enough to earn their pay:

XLI.

And insolence no doubt is what they are

Employed for, since it is their daily labour,

In the dear offices of Peace or War;

And should you doubt, pray ask of your next neighbour,

When for a passport, or some other bar

To freedom, he applied (a grief and a bore),

If he found not this spawn of tax-born riches,

Like lap-dogs, the least civil sons of b——- s.

XLII.

But Juan was received with much "empressement:"—

These phrases of refinement I must borrow

From our next neighbours' land, where, like a chessman,

There is a move set down for joy or sorrow,

Not only in mere talking, but the press. Man

In Islands is, it seems, downright and thorough,

More than on Continents—as if the Sea

(See Billingsgate) made even the tongue more free.

XLIII.

And yet the British "Damme"'s rather Attic,

Your continental oaths are but incontinent,

And turn on things which no aristocratic

Spirit would name, and therefore even I won't anent[581]

This subject quote; as it would be schismatic

In politesse, and have a sound affronting in't;—

But "Damme"'s quite ethereal, though too daring—

Platonic blasphemy—the soul of swearing.[KT]

XLIV.

For downright rudeness, ye may stay at home;

For true or false politeness (and scarce that

Now) you may cross the blue deep and white foam—

The first the emblem (rarely though) of what

You leave behind, the next of much you come

To meet. However, 't is no time to chat

On general topics: poems must confine

Themselves to unity, like this of mine.[KU]

XLV.

In the great world,—which, being interpreted,

Meaneth the West or worst end of a city,

And about twice two thousand people bred

By no means to be very wise or witty,

But to sit up while others lie in bed,

And look down on the Universe with pity,—

Juan, as an inveterate patrician,

Was well received by persons of condition.

XLVI.

He was a bachelor, which is a matter

Of import both to virgin and to bride,

The former's hymeneal hopes to flatter;

And (should she not hold fast by Love or Pride)

'T is also of some moment to the latter:

A rib's a thorn in a wed gallant's side,

Requires decorum, and is apt to double

The horrid sin—and what's still worse, the trouble.

XLVII.

But Juan was a bachelor—of arts,

And parts, and hearts: he danced and sung, and had

An air as sentimental as Mozart's

Softest of melodies; and could be sad

Or cheerful, without any "flaws or starts,"[582]

Just at the proper time: and though a lad,

Had seen the world—which is a curious sight,

And very much unlike what people write.

XLVIII.

Fair virgins blushed upon him; wedded dames

Bloomed also in less transitory hues;[KV]

For both commodities dwell by the Thames,

The painting and the painted; Youth, Ceruse,[KW]

Against his heart preferred their usual claims,

Such as no gentleman can quite refuse:

Daughters admired his dress, and pious mothers

Inquired his income, and if he had brothers.

XLIX.

The milliners who furnish "drapery Misses"[583]

Throughout the season, upon speculation

Of payment ere the Honeymoon's last kisses

Have waned into a crescent's coruscation,

Thought such an opportunity as this is,

Of a rich foreigner's initiation,

Not to be overlooked—and gave such credit,

That future bridegrooms swore, and sighed, and paid it.

L.

The Blues, that tender tribe, who sigh o'er sonnets,

And with the pages of the last Review

Line the interior of their heads or bonnets,

Advanced in all their azure's highest hue:

They talked bad French or Spanish, and upon its

Late authors asked him for a hint or two;

And which was softest, Russian or Castilian?

And whether in his travels he saw Ilion?

LI.

Juan, who was a little superficial,

And not in literature a great Drawcansir,[584]

Examined by this learnéd and especial

Jury of matrons, scarce knew what to answer:

His duties warlike, loving or official,

His steady application as a dancer,

Had kept him from the brink of Hippocrene,

Which now he found was blue instead of green.

LII.

However, he replied at hazard, with

A modest confidence and calm assurance,

Which lent his learnéd lucubrations pith,

And passed for arguments of good endurance.

That prodigy, Miss Araminta Smith

(Who at sixteen translated "Hercules Furens"

Into as furious English), with her best look,

Set down his sayings in her common-place book.

LIII.

Juan knew several languages—as well

He might—and brought them up with skill, in time

To save his fame with each accomplished belle,

Who still regretted that he did not rhyme.

There wanted but this requisite to swell

His qualities (with them) into sublime:

Lady Fitz-Frisky, and Miss Maevia Mannish,

Both longed extremely to be sung in Spanish.

LIV.

However, he did pretty well, and was

Admitted as an aspirant to all

The coteries, and, as in Banquo's glass,

At great assemblies or in parties small,

He saw ten thousand living authors pass,

That being about their average numeral;

Also the eighty "greatest living poets,"[585]

As every paltry magazine can show it's.

LV.

In twice five years the "greatest living poet,"

Like to the champion in the fisty ring,

Is called on to support his claim, or show it,

Although 't is an imaginary thing.

Even I—albeit I'm sure I did not know it,

Nor sought of foolscap subjects to be king,—

Was reckoned, a considerable time,

The grand Napoleon of the realms of rhyme.[KX]

LVI.

But Juan was my Moscow, and Faliero

My Leipsic, and my Mont Saint Jean seems Cain:[586]

La Belle Alliance of dunces down at zero,

Now that the Lion's fallen, may rise again:

But I will fall at least as fell my Hero;

Nor reign at all, or as a monarch reign;

Or to some lonely isle of gaolers go,

With turncoat Southey for my turnkey Lowe.[KY]

LVII.

Sir Walter reigned before me; Moore and Campbell

Before and after; but now grown more holy,

The Muses upon Sion's hill must ramble

With poets almost clergymen, or wholly;

And Pegasus has a psalmodic amble

Beneath the very Reverend Rowley Powley,[KZ][587]

Who shoes the glorious animal with stilts,

A modern Ancient Pistol—"by these hilts!"[588]

LVIII.

Still he excels that artificial hard

Labourer in the same vineyard, though the vine

Yields him but vinegar for his reward.—

That neutralised dull Dorus of the Nine;

That swarthy Sporus, neither man nor bard;

That ox of verse, who ploughs for every line:—

Cambyses' roaring Romans beat at least

The howling Hebrews of Cybele's priest.—[589]

LIX.

Then there's my gentle Euphues,—who, they say,[LA]

Sets up for being a sort of moral me;[590]

He'll find it rather difficult some day

To turn out both, or either, it may be.

Some persons think that Coleridge hath the sway;

And Wordsworth has supporters, two or three;

And that deep-mouthed Boeotian "Savage Landor"[591]

Has taken for a swan rogue Southey's gander.

LX.

John Keats, who was killed off by one critique,

Just as he really promised something great,

If not intelligible, without Greek

Contrived to talk about the gods of late,

Much as they might have been supposed to speak.[592]

Poor fellow! His was an untoward fate;

'T is strange the mind, that very fiery particle,[LB][593]

Should let itself be snuffed out by an article.

LXI.

The list grows long of live and dead pretenders

To that which none will gain—or none will know

The conqueror at least; who, ere Time renders

His last award, will have the long grass grow

Above his burnt-out brain, and sapless cinders.

If I might augur, I should rate but low

Their chances;—they're too numerous, like the thirty[594]

Mock tyrants, when Rome's annals waxed but dirty.

LXII.

This is the literary lower empire,

Where the praetorian bands take up the matter;—

A "dreadful trade," like his who "gathers samphire,"[595]

The insolent soldiery to soothe and flatter,

With the same feelings as you'd coax a vampire.

Now, were I once at home, and in good satire,

I'd try conclusions with those Janizaries,

And show them what an intellectual war is.

LXIII.

I think I know a trick or two, would turn

Their flanks;—but it is hardly worth my while,

With such small gear to give myself concern:

Indeed I've not the necessary bile;

My natural temper's really aught but stern,

And even my Muse's worst reproof's a smile;

And then she drops a brief and modern curtsy,

And glides away, assured she never hurts ye.

LXIV.

My Juan, whom I left in deadly peril

Amongst live poets and blue ladies, passed

With some small profit through that field so sterile,

Being tired in time—and, neither least nor last,

Left it before he had been treated very ill;

And henceforth found himself more gaily classed

Amongst the higher spirits of the day,

The Sun's true son, no vapour, but a ray.

LXV.

His morns he passed in business—which dissected,

Was, like all business, a laborious nothing

That leads to lassitude, the most infected

And Centaur Nessus garb of mortal clothing,[596]

And on our sofas makes us lie dejected,

And talk in tender horrors of our loathing

All kinds of toil, save for our country's good—

Which grows no better, though 't is time it should.

LXVI.

His afternoons he passed in visits, luncheons,

Lounging and boxing; and the twilight hour

In riding round those vegetable puncheons

Called "Parks," where there is neither fruit nor flower

Enough to gratify a bee's slight munchings;

But after all it is the only "bower"[597]

(In Moore's phrase) where the fashionable fair

Can form a slight acquaintance with fresh air.

LXVII.

Then dress, then dinner, then awakes the world!

Then glare the lamps, then whirl the wheels, then roar

Through street and square fast flashing chariots hurled

Like harnessed meteors; then along the floor

Chalk mimics painting; then festoons are twirled;

Then roll the brazen thunders of the door,

Which opens to the thousand happy few

An earthly Paradise of Or Molu.

LXVIII.

There stands the noble hostess, nor shall sink

With the three-thousandth curtsy; there the waltz,

The only dance which teaches girls to think,[598]

Makes one in love even with its very faults.

Saloon, room, hall, o'erflow beyond their brink,

And long the latest of arrivals halts,

'Midst royal dukes and dames condemned to climb,

And gain an inch of staircase at a time.

LXIX.

Thrice happy he who, after a survey

Of the good company, can win a corner,

A door that's in or boudoir out of the way,

Where he may fix himself like small "Jack Horner,"

And let the Babel round run as it may,

And look on as a mourner, or a scorner,

Or an approver, or a mere spectator,

Yawning a little as the night grows later.

LXX.

But this won't do, save by and by; and he

Who, like Don Juan, takes an active share,

Must steer with care through all that glittering sea

Of gems and plumes and pearls and silks, to where

He deems it is his proper place to be;

Dissolving in the waltz to some soft air,

Or proudlier prancing with mercurial skill,

Where Science marshals forth her own quadrille.

LXXI.

Or, if he dance not, but hath higher views

Upon an heiress or his neighbour's bride,

Let him take care that that which he pursues

Is not at once too palpably descried:

Full many an eager gentleman oft rues

His haste; Impatience is a blundering guide

Amongst a people famous for reflection,

Who like to play the fool with circumspection.

LXXII.

But, if you can contrive, get next at supper;

Or, if forestalled, get opposite and ogle:—

Oh, ye ambrosial moments! always upper

In mind, a sort of sentimental bogle,[599]

Which sits for ever upon Memory's crupper,

The ghost of vanished pleasures once in vogue! Ill

Can tender souls relate the rise and fall

Of hopes and fears which shake a single ball.

LXXIII.

But these precautionary hints can touch

Only the common run, who must pursue,

And watch and ward; whose plans a word too much

Or little overturns; and not the few

Or many (for the number's sometimes such)

Whom a good mien, especially if new,

Or fame—or name—for Wit, War, Sense, or Nonsense,

Permits whate'er they please,—or did not long since.

LXXIV.

Our Hero—as a hero—young and handsome,

Noble, rich, celebrated, and a stranger,

Like other slaves of course must pay his ransom,

Before he can escape from so much danger

As will environ a conspicuous man. Some

Talk about poetry, and "rack and manger,"

And ugliness, disease, as toil and trouble;—

I wish they knew the life of a young noble.

LXXV.

They are young, but know not Youth—it is anticipated;

Handsome but wasted, rich without a sou;[LC]

Their vigour in a thousand arms is dissipated;

Their cash comes from, their wealth goes to a Jew;

Both senates see their nightly votes participated

Between the Tyrant's and the Tribunes' crew;

And having voted, dined, drunk, gamed, and whored,

The family vault receives another Lord.

LXXVI.

"Where is the World?" cries Young, at eighty[600]—"Where

The World in which a man was born?" Alas!

Where is the world of eight years past? 'T was there—

I look for it—'t is gone, a globe of glass!

Cracked, shivered, vanished, scarcely gazed on, ere[LD]

A silent change dissolves the glittering mass.

Statesmen, Chiefs, Orators, Queens, Patriots, Kings,

And Dandies—all are gone on the Wind's wings.

LXXVII.

Where is Napoleon the Grand? God knows!

Where little Castlereagh? The devil can tell!

Where Grattan, Curran, Sheridan—all those

Who bound the Bar or Senate in their spell?

Where is the unhappy Queen, with all her woes?

And where the Daughter, whom the Isles loved well?

Where are those martyred saints the Five per Cents?[LE][601]

And where—oh, where the devil are the Rents?

LXXVIII.

Where's Brummell? Dished. Where's Long Pole Wellesley?[602] Diddled.

Where's Whitbread? Romilly? Where's George the Third?

Where is his will?[603] (That's not so soon unriddled.)

And where is "Fum" the Fourth, our "royal bird?"[604]

Gone down, it seems, to Scotland to be fiddled

Unto by Sawney's violin, we have heard:

"Caw me, caw thee"—for six months hath been hatching

This scene of royal itch and loyal scratching.

LXXIX.

Where is Lord This? And where my Lady That?

The Honourable Mistresses and Misses?

Some laid aside like an old Opera hat,

Married, unmarried, and remarried: (this is

An evolution oft performed of late).

Where are the Dublin shouts—and London hisses?

Where are the Grenvilles? Turned as usual. Where

My friends the Whigs? Exactly where they were.

LXXX.

Where are the Lady Carolines and Franceses?[605]

Divorced or doing thereanent. Ye annals

So brilliant, where the list of routs and dances is,—

Thou Morning Post, sole record of the panels

Broken in carriages, and all the phantasies

Of fashion,—say what streams now fill those channels?

Some die, some fly, some languish on the Continent,

Because the times have hardly left them one tenant.

LXXXI.

Some who once set their caps at cautious dukes,[LF]

Have taken up at length with younger brothers:

Some heiresses have bit at sharpers' hooks:

Some maids have been made wives, some merely mothers:

Others have lost their fresh and fairy looks:

In short, the list of alterations bothers.

There's little strange in this, but something strange is

The unusual quickness of these common changes.

LXXXII.

Talk not of seventy years as age; in seven

I have seen more changes, down from monarchs to

The humblest individuals under Heaven,

Than might suffice a moderate century through.

I knew that nought was lasting, but now even

Change grows too changeable, without being new:

Nought's permanent among the human race,

Except the Whigs not getting into place.

LXXXIII.

I have seen Napoleon, who seemed quite a Jupiter,

Shrink to a Saturn. I have seen a Duke

(No matter which) turn politician stupider,

If that can well be, than his wooden look.

But it is time that I should hoist my "blue Peter,"

And sail for a new theme:—I have seen—and shook

To see it—the King hissed, and then caressed;

But don't pretend to settle which was best.

LXXXIV.

I have seen the Landholders without a rap—

I have seen Joanna Southcote—I have seen

The House of Commons turned to a tax-trap—

I have seen that sad affair of the late Queen—

I have seen crowns worn instead of a fool's cap—

I have seen a Congress[606] doing all that's mean—

I have seen some nations, like o'erloaded asses,

Kick off their burthens—meaning the high classes.

LXXXV.

I have seen small poets, and great prosers, and

Interminable—not eternal—speakers—

I have seen the funds at war with house and land—

I have seen the country gentlemen turn squeakers—

I have seen the people ridden o'er like sand

By slaves on horseback—I have seen malt liquors

Exchanged for "thin potations"[607] by John Bull—

I have seen John half detect himself a fool.—

LXXXVI.

But "carpe diem," Juan, "carpe, carpe!"[608]

To-morrow sees another race as gay

And transient, and devoured by the same harpy.

"Life's a poor player,"[609]—then "play out the play,[610]

Ye villains!" and above all keep a sharp eye

Much less on what you do than what you say:

Be hypocritical, be cautious, be

Not what you seem, but always what you see.

LXXXVII.

But how shall I relate in other cantos

Of what befell our hero in the land,

Which 't is the common cry and lie to vaunt as

A moral country? But I hold my hand—

For I disdain to write an Atalantis;[611]

But 't is as well at once to understand,

You are not a moral people, and you know it,

Without the aid of too sincere a poet.

LXXXVIII.

What Juan saw and underwent shall be

My topic, with of course the due restriction

Which is required by proper courtesy;

And recollect the work is only fiction,

And that I sing of neither mine nor me,

Though every scribe, in some slight turn of diction,

Will hint allusions never meant. Ne'er doubt

This—when I speak, I don't hint, but speak out.

LXXXIX.

Whether he married with the third or fourth

Offspring of some sage husband-hunting countess,

Or whether with some virgin of more worth

(I mean in Fortune's matrimonial bounties),

He took to regularly peopling Earth,

Of which your lawful, awful wedlock fount is,—

Or whether he was taken in for damages,

For being too excursive in his homages,—

XC.

Is yet within the unread events of Time.

Thus far, go forth, thou Lay, which I will back

Against the same given quantity of rhyme,

For being as much the subject of attack

As ever yet was any work sublime,

By those who love to say that white is black.

So much the better!—I may stand alone,

But would not change my free thoughts for a throne.[612]

FOOTNOTES:

[562] {427}[Berkeley did not deny the reality of existence, but the reality of matter as an abstract conception. "It is plain," he says (On the Principles of Human Knowledge, sect. ix.), "that the very notion of what is called matter or corporeal substance, involves a contradiction in it." Again, "It were a mistake to think that what is here said derogates in the least from the reality of things." His contention was that this reality depended, not on an abstraction called matter, "an inert, extended unperceiving substance," but on "those unextended, indivisible substances or spirits, which act, and think, and perceive them [unthinking beings]."—Ibid., sect. xci., The Works of George Berkeley, D.D., 1820, i. 27, 69, 70.]

[563] {428}[Tempest, act v. sc. i, line 95.]

[564] ["I have been very unwell—four days confined to my bed in 'the worst inn's worst room' at Lerici, with a violent rheumatic and bilious attack, constipation, and the devil knows what."—Letter to Murray, October 9, 1822, Letters, 1901, vi. 121. The same letter contains an announcement that he had "a fifth [Canto of Don Juan] (the 10th) finished, but not transcribed yet; and the eleventh begun."]

[KK] {429}Or Rome, or Tiber—Naples or the sea.—[MS. erased.]

[565] {430}[Vide ante, Canto I. stanza xiv. lines 7, 8.]

[566] {431}["Falstaff. Let us be Diana's foresters, gentlemen of the shade, minions of the moon: and let men say, we be men of good government; being governed, as the sea is, by our noble and chaste mistress the moon, under whose countenance we—steal."-I Henry IV., act i. sc. 2, lines 24-28.]

[567] [Gin. Hence the antithesis of "All Max" in the East to Almack's in the West. (See Life in London, by Pierce Egan, 1823, pp. 284-290.)]

[568] [According to the Vocabulary of the Flash Language, compiled by James Hardy Vaux, in 1812, and published at the end of his Memoirs, 1819, ii. 149-227, a kiddy, or "flash-kiddy," is a thief of the lower orders, who, when he is breeched by a course of successful depredation dresses in the extreme of vulgar gentility, and affects a knowingness in his air and conversation. A "swell" or "rank swell" ("real swell" appears in Egan's Life in London) is the more recent "toff;" and "flash" is "fly," "down," or "awake," i.e. knowing, not easily imposed upon.]

[569] {432}[Hamlet, act v. sc. 1, line 21.]

[570] ["Ken" is a house, s.c. a thieves' lodging-house; "spellken," a play-house; "high toby-spice" is robbery on horseback, as distinguished from "spice," i.e. footpad robbery; to "flash the muzzle" is to show off the face, to swagger openly; "blowing" or "blowen" is a doxy or trull; and "nutty" is, conjointly, amorous and fascinating.]

[KL]

Poor Tom was once a knowing one in town.

Not a mere kiddy, but a real one.—[MS. erased.]

[571] The advance of science and of language has rendered it unnecessary to translate the above good and true English, spoken in its original purity by the select mobility and their patrons. The following is a stanza of a song which was very popular at least in my early days:—

"On the high toby-spice flash the muzzle,

In spite of each gallows old scout;

If you at the spellken can't hustle,

You'll be hobbled in making a clout.

Then your blowing will wax gallows haughty,

When she hears of your scaly mistake,

She'll surely turn snitch for the forty—

That her Jack may be regular weight."

If there be any gemman so ignorant as to require a traduction, I refer him to my old friend and corporeal pastor and master, John Jackson, Esq., Professor of Pugilism; who, I trust, still retains the strength and symmetry of his model of a form, together with his good humour, and athletic as well as mental accomplishments.

[Gentleman Jackson was of good renown. "Servility," says Egan (Life in London, 1823, p. 217), "is not known to him. Flattery he detests. Integrity, impartiality, good-nature, and manliness, are the corner-stones of his understanding." Byron once said of him that "his manners were infinitely superior to those of the Fellows of the College whom I meet at the high table" (J.W. Clark, Cambridge, 1890, p. 140). (See, too, letter to John Jackson, September 18, 1808, Letters, 1898, i. 189, note 2; Hints from Horace, line 638, Poetical Works, 1898, i. 433, note 3.) As to the stanza quoted by Egan (Anecdotes of the Turf, 1827, p. 44), but not traduced or interpreted, "To be hobbled for making a clout" is to be taken into custody for stealing a handkerchief, to "turn snitch" is to inform, and the "forty" is the £40 offered for the detection of a capital crime, and shared by the police or Bow Street runners. Dangerous characters were let alone and tacitly encouraged to continue their career of crime, until the measure of their iniquity was full, and they "weighed forty." If Jack was clumsy enough to be detected in a trifling theft, his "blowen" would go over to the enemy, and betray him for the sake of the Government reward (see Classical Dictionary of the Vulgar Tongue, by Francis Grose, 1823, art. "Weigh forty").]

[572] {433}[Don Juan must have driven by Pleasant Row, and passed within hail of Paradise Row, on the way from Kennington to Westminster Bridge. (See Cary's New Pocket Plan of London, Westminster, and Southwark, 1819.) But, perhaps, there is more in the names of streets and places than meets the eye. Here, as elsewhere, there is, or there may be, "a paltering with us in a double sense."]

[KM]

Through rows called "Paradise," by way of showing

Good Christians that to which they all are going.—[MS. erased.]

[573] {434}[Compare Childe Harold, Canto 1. stanza lxix. line 8, var. ii., Poetical Works, 1899, ii. 66, note 2.]

[KN]—— distilling into the re-kindling glass.—[MS.]

[574] [The streets of London were first regularly lighted with gas in 1812.]

[575] {435}[Thomas Pennant, in Some Account of London, 1793, p. 444, writes down the Mansion House (1739-1752) as "damned ... to everlasting fame."]

[576] [Fifty years ago "the lights of Piccadilly" were still regarded as one of the "sights" of London. Byron must often have looked at them from his house in Piccadilly Terrace.]

[577] [Joseph François Foulon, army commissioner, provoked the penalty of the "lantern" (i.e. an improvised gallows on the yard of a lamp-post at the corner of the Rue de la Vannerie) by his heartless sneer, "Eh bien! si cette canaille n'a pas de pain, elle mangera du foin." He was hanged, July 22, 1789. See The Tale of Two Cities, by Charles Dickens, cap. xxii.; see, too, Carlyle's French Revolution, 1839, i. 253: "With wild yells, Sansculottism clutches him, in its hundred hands: he is whirled ... to the 'Lanterne,' ... pleading bitterly for life,—to the deaf winds. Only with the third rope (for two ropes broke, and the quavering voice still pleaded), can he be so much as got hanged! His Body is dragged through the streets; his Head goes aloft on a pike, the mouth filled with grass: amid sounds as of Tophet, from a grass-eating people."]

[578] {436}"Hells," gaming-houses. What their number may now be in this life, I know not. Before I was of age I knew them pretty accurately, both "gold" and "silver." I was once nearly called out by an acquaintance, because when he asked me where I thought that his soul would be found hereafter, I answered, "In Silver Hell."

[KO]

At length the boys drew up before a door,

From whence poured forth a tribe of well-clad waiters;

(While on the pavement many a hungry w—re

With which the moralest of cities caters

For gentlemen whose passions may boil o'er,

Stood as the unpacking gathered more spectators,)

And Juan found himself in an extensive

Apartment;—fashionable but expensive.—[MS.]

[KP] {437}'Twas one of the delightfullest hotels.—[MS.]

[579] [Perhaps Grillion's Hotel (afterwards Grillion's Club) in Albemarle Street. In 1822 diplomats patronized more than one hotel in and near St. James's Street, but among the "Departures from Grillion's Hotel," recorded in the Morning Chronicle of September, 17, 1822, appositely enough, is that of H.E. Don Juan Garcia, del Rio.]

[KQ]

—— of his loves and wars;

And as romantic heads are pretty painters,

And ladies like a little spice of Mars.—[MS. erased.]

[KR] {438}The false attempt at Truth——.—[MS.]

[580] {439}[Compare—

"Lo! Erin, thy Lord!

Kiss his foot with thy blessing"——

The Irish Avatar, stanza 14, Poetical Works, 1901, iv. 558.]

[KS]

Kiss hands—or feet—or what Man by and by

Will kiss, not in sad metaphor—but earnest,

Unless on Tyrants' sterns—we turn the sternest.—[MS.]

[581] {440}"Anent" was a Scotch phrase meaning "concerning"—"with regard to: "it has been made English by the Scotch novels; and, as the Frenchman said, "If it be not, ought to be English." [See, for instance, The Abbot, chap. xvii. 132.]

[KT]

But "Damme's" simple—dashing—free and daring

The purest blasphemy——.—[MS.]

[KU]

About such general matters—but particular

A poem's progress should be perpendicular.—[MS.]

[582] {441}[Macbeth, act iii. sc. 4, line 63.]

[KV] Blushed, too, but it was hidden by their rouge.—[MS. erased.]

[KW] The natural and the prepared ceruse.—[MS. erased.]

[583] {442}"Drapery Misses."—This term is probably anything now but a mystery. It was, however, almost so to me when I first returned from the East in 1811-1812. It means a pretty, a high-born, a fashionable young female, well instructed by her friends, and furnished by her milliner with a wardrobe upon credit, to be repaid, when married, by the husband. The riddle was first read to me by a young and pretty heiress, on my praising the "drapery" of the "untochered" but "pretty virginities" (like Mrs. Anne Page) of the then day, which has now been some years yesterday: she assured me that the thing was common in London; and as her own thousands, and blooming looks, and rich simplicity of array, put any suspicion in her own case out of the question, I confess I gave some credit to the allegation. If necessary, authorities might be cited; in which case I could quote both "drapery" and the wearers. Let us hope, however, that it is now obsolete.

[584] [Compare Hints from Horace, line 173, Poetical Works, 1898, i. 401, note 1.]

[585] {443}[In his so-called "Dedication" of Marino Faliero to Goethe, Byron makes fun of the "nineteen hundred and eighty-seven poets," whose names were to be found in A Biographical Dictionary of Living Authors, etc. (See Introduction to Marino Faliero, Poetical Works, 1901, iv. 340, 341, note 1.)]

[KX] {444}A paper potentate——.—[MS. erased.]

[586] [See "Introduction to Cain," Poetical Works, 1901, v. 204.]

[KY] With turnkey Southey for my Hudson Lowe.—[MS.]

[KZ] Beneath the reverend Cambyses Croly.—[MS.]

[587] [The Reverend George Croly, D.D. (1780-1860), began his literary career as dramatic critic of the Times. "Croly," says H.C. Robinson (Diary, 1869, i. 412), "is a fierce-looking Irishman, very lively in conversation, and certainly has considerable talents as a writer; his eloquence, like his person, is rather energetic than eloquent" (hence the epithet "Cambyses," i.e. "King Cambyses' vein" in var. iii.). "He wrote tragedies, comedies, and novels; and, at last, settled down as a preacher, with the rank of doctor, but of what faculty I do not know" (ibid., footnote, H.C.R., 1847). He wrote, inter alia, Paris in 1815, a poem; Catiline, A Tragedy, 1822; and Salathiel, a novel, 1827. In lines 7, 8, Byron seems to refer to The Angel of the World, An Arabian Poem, published in 1820.]

[588] [I Henry IV., act ii. sc. 4, line 197.]

[589] {445}[Stanza lviii. was first published in 1837. The reference is to Henry Hart Milman (1791-1868). Byron was under the impression that Milman had influenced Murray against continuing the publication of Don Juan. Added to this surmise, was the mistaken belief that it was Milman who had written the article in the Quarterly, which "killed John Keats." Hence the virulence of the attack.

"Dull Dorus" is obscure, but compare Propertius, Eleg. III. vii. 44, where Callimachus is addressed as "Dore poeta." He is the "ox of verse," because he had been recently appointed to the Professorship of Poetry at Oxford. The "roaring Romans" are "The soldiery" who shout "All, All," in Croly's Catiline, act v. sc. 2.]

[LA] Then there's my gentle Barry—who they say.—[MS.]

[590] [Jeffrey, in his review of A Sicilian Story, etc., Bryan Waller Procter (Barry Cornwall), 1787-1874 (Edinburgh Review, January, 1820, vol. 33, pp. 144-155), compares Diego de Montilla, a poem in ottava rima, with Don Juan, favourably and unfavourably: "There is no profligacy and no horror ... no mocking of virtue and honour, and no strong mixtures of buffoonery and grandeur." But it may fairly match with Byron and his Italian models "as to the better qualities of elegance, delicacy, and tenderness." See, too, Blackwood's Edinburgh Magazine, March, 1820, vol. vi. pp. 153, 647.]

[591] [See Preface to the Vision of Judgment, Poetical Works, 1901, iv. 484, note 3.]

[592] [Croker's article in the Quarterly (April, 1818 [pub. September], vol. xix. pp. 204-208) did not "kill John Keats." See letter to George and Georgiana Keats, October, 1818 (Letters, etc., 1895, p. 215). Byron adopts Shelley's belief that the Reviewer, "miserable man," "one of the meanest," had "wantonly defaced one of the noblest specimens of the workmanship of God." See Preface to Adonais, and stanzas xxxvi., xxxvii.]

[LB] {446}

And weakly mind, to let that all celestial Particle.—[MS. erased.]

or, 'T is strange the mind should let such phrases quell its

Chief Impulse with a few, frail, paper pellets.—[MS. erased.]

[593] "Divinæ particulam auræ" [Hor., Sat. ii. 2. 79]

[594] [For "the crowd of usurpers" who started up in the reign of Gallienus, and were dignified with the honoured appellation of "the thirty tyrants," see Gibbon's Decline and Fall, 1825, i. 164.]

[595] [King Lear, act iv. sc. 6, line 15.]

[596] {447}["Illita Nesseo misi tibi texta veneno."

Ovid., Heroid. Epist. ix. 163.]

[597] [A "bower," in Moore's phrase, signifies a solitude à deux; e.g. "Here's the Bower she lov'd so much."

"Come to me, love, the twilight star

Shall guide thee to my bower."

Moore.]

[598] {448}[Compare The Waltz, lines 220-229, et passim, Poetical Works, 1898, i. 501.]

[599] {449}Scotch for goblin.

[LC] Handsome but blasé——— [MS.]

[600] {450}[The sentiment is reiterated in The Night Thoughts, and is the theme of Resignation, which was written and published when Young was more than eighty years old. ]

[LD] And fresher, since without a breath of air.—[MS.]

[LE] Where are the thousand lovely innocents?—[MS.]

[601] ["I have ... written ... to express my willingness to accept the, or almost any mortgage, any thing to get out of the tremulous Funds of these oscillating times. There will be a war somewhere, no doubt—and whatever it may be, the Funds will be affected more or less; so pray get us out of them with all proper expedition. It has been the burthen of my song to you three years and better, and about as useful as better counsels."—Letter of Byron to Kinnaird, January 18, 1823, Letters, 1901, vi. 162, 163.]

[602] {451}[For William Pole Tylney Long Wellesley (1788-1857), see The Waltz, line 21, Poetical Works, 1898, i. 484, note 1. He was only on the way to being "diddled" in 1822, but the prophecy (suggested, no doubt, by the announcement of the sale of furniture, etc., at Wanstead House, in the Morning Chronicle, July 8, 1822) was ultimately fulfilled. Samuel Whitbread, born 1758, committed suicide July 6, 1815. Sir Samuel Romilly, born 1758, committed suicide November 2, 1818.]

[603] [According to Charles Greville, George the Third made two wills—the first in 1770, the second, which he never signed, in 1810. By the first will he left "all he had to the Queen for her life, Buckingham House to the Duke of Clarence," etc., and as Buckingham House had been twice sold, and the other legatees were dead, a question arose between the King and the Duke of York as to the right of inheritance of their father's personal property. George IV. conceived that it devolved upon him personally, and not on the Crown, and "consequently appropriated to himself the whole of the money and the jewels." It is possible that this difference between the brothers was noised abroad, and that old stories of the destruction of royal wills were revived to the new king's discredit. (See The Greville Memoirs, 1875, i. 64, 65.)]

[604] [See Moore's Fum and Hum, the Two Birds of Royalty, appended to his Fudge Family.]

[605] [Lady Caroline Lamb and Lady Frances Wedderburn Webster.]

[LF] {452}—— their caps and curls at Dukes.—[MS.]

[606] {453}[The Congress at Verona, in 1822. See the Introduction to The Age of Bronze, Poetical Works, 1891, v. 537-540.]

[607] [2 Henry IV., act iv. sc. 3, line 117.]

[608] [Hor., Od. I. xi. line 8.]

[609] [Macbeth, act v. sc. 5, line 24.]

[610] [1 Henry IV., act ii. sc. 4, line 463.]

[611] [See the Secret Memoirs and Manners of several Persons of Quality, of Both Sexes, from the New Atalantis, 1709, a work in which the authoress, Mrs. Manley, satirizes the distinguished characters of her day. Warburton (Works of Pope, ed. 1751, i. 244) calls it "a famous book.... full of court and party scandal, and in a loose effeminacy of style and sentiment, which well suited the debauched taste of the better vulgar." Pope also alludes to it in the Rape of the Lock, iii. 165, 166—

"As long as Atalantis shall be read,

Or the small pillow grace a lady's bed."

And Swift, in his ballad on "Corinna" (stanza 8)—

"Her common-place book all gallant is,

Of scandal now a cornucopia,

She pours it out in Atalantis,

Or memoirs of the New Utopia."

Works, 1824, xii. 302.]

[612] {454}[Oct. 17, 1822.—MS.]

Canto XIII[653]

I.

I now mean to be serious;—it is time,

Since Laughter now-a-days is deemed too serious;

A jest at Vice by Virtue's called a crime,

And critically held as deleterious:

Besides, the sad's a source of the sublime,

Although, when long, a little apt to weary us;

And therefore shall my lay soar high and solemn,

As an old temple dwindled to a column.

II.

The Lady Adeline Amundeville

('T is an old Norman name, and to be found

In pedigrees, by those who wander still

Along the last fields of that Gothic ground)

Was high-born, wealthy by her father's will,

And beauteous, even where beauties most abound,

In Britain—which, of course, true patriots find

The goodliest soil of Body and of Mind.

III.

I'll not gainsay them; it is not my cue;

I'll leave them to their taste, no doubt the best;

An eye's an eye, and whether black or blue,

Is no great matter, so 't is in request;

'T is nonsense to dispute about a hue—

The kindest may be taken as a test.

The fair sex should be always fair; and no man,

Till thirty, should perceive there's a plain woman.

IV.

And after that serene and somewhat dull

Epoch, that awkward corner turned for days

More quiet, when our moon's no more at full,

We may presume to criticise or praise;

Because Indifference begins to lull

Our passions, and we walk in Wisdom's ways;

Also because the figure and the face

Hint, that 't is time to give the younger place.

V.

I know that some would fain postpone this era,

Reluctant as all placemen to resign

Their post; but theirs is merely a chimera,

For they have passed Life's equinoctial line:

But then they have their claret and Madeira,

To irrigate the dryness of decline;

And County meetings, and the Parliament,

And debt—and what not, for their solace sent.

VI.

And is there not Religion, and Reform,

Peace, War, the taxes, and what's called the "Nation"?

The struggle to be pilots in a storm?[654]

The landed and the monied speculation?

The joys of mutual hate to keep them warm,

Instead of Love, that mere hallucination?

Now Hatred is by far the longest pleasure;

Men love in haste, but they detest at leisure.

VII.

Rough Johnson, the great moralist, professed,

Right honestly, "he liked an honest hater!"[655]—

The only truth that yet has been confessed

Within these latest thousand years or later.

Perhaps the fine old fellow spoke in jest:—

For my part, I am but a mere spectator,

And gaze where'er the palace or the hovel is,

Much in the mode of Goethe's Mephistopheles;

VIII.

But neither love nor hate in much excess;

Though 't was not once so. If I sneer sometimes,

It is because I cannot well do less,

And now and then it also suits my rhymes.

I should be very willing to redress

Men's wrongs, and rather check than punish crimes,

Had not Cervantes, in that too true tale

Of Quixote, shown how all such efforts fail.

IX.[656]

Of all tales 't is the saddest—and more sad,

Because it makes us smile: his hero's right,

And still pursues the right;—to curb the bad

His only object, and 'gainst odds to fight

His guerdon: 't is his virtue makes him mad!

But his adventures form a sorry sight;—

A sorrier still is the great moral taught

By that real Epic unto all who have thought.[LX]

X.

Redressing injury, revenging wrong,

To aid the damsel and destroy the caitiff;

Opposing singly the united strong,

From foreign yoke to free the helpless native:—

Alas! must noblest views, like an old song,

Be for mere Fancy's sport a theme creative,

A jest, a riddle, Fame through thin and thick sought!

And Socrates himself but Wisdom's Quixote?

XI.

Cervantes smiled Spain's chivalry away;

A single laugh demolished the right arm

Of his own country;—seldom since that day

Has Spain had heroes. While Romance could charm,

The World gave ground before her bright array;

And therefore have his volumes done such harm,

That all their glory, as a composition,

Was dearly purchased by his land's perdition.

XII.

I'm "at my old lunes"[657]—digression, and forget

The Lady Adeline Amundeville;

The fair most fatal Juan ever met,

Although she was not evil nor meant ill;

But Destiny and Passion spread the net

(Fate is a good excuse for our own will),

And caught them;—what do they not catch, methinks?

But I'm not Oedipus, and Life's a Sphinx.

XIII.

I tell the tale as it is told, nor dare

To venture a solution: "Davus sum!"[658]

And now I will proceed upon the pair.

Sweet Adeline, amidst the gay World's hum,

Was the Queen-Bee, the glass of all that's fair;

Whose charms made all men speak, and women dumb.

The last's a miracle, and such was reckoned,

And since that time there has not been a second.

XIV.

Chaste was she, to Detraction's desperation,

And wedded unto one she had loved well—

A man known in the councils of the Nation,

Cool, and quite English, imperturbable,

Though apt to act with fire upon occasion,

Proud of himself and her: the World could tell

Nought against either, and both seemed secure—

She in her virtue, he in his hauteur.

XV.

It chanced some diplomatical relations,

Arising out of business, often brought

Himself and Juan in their mutual stations

Into close contact. Though reserved, nor caught

By specious seeming, Juan's youth, and patience,

And talent, on his haughty spirit wrought,

And formed a basis of esteem, which ends

In making men what Courtesy calls friends.

XVI.

And thus Lord Henry, who was cautious as

Reserve and Pride could make him, and full slow

In judging men—when once his judgment was

Determined, right or wrong, on friend or foe,

Had all the pertinacity Pride has,

Which knows no ebb to its imperious flow,

And loves or hates, disdaining to be guided,

Because its own good pleasure hath decided.

XVII.

His friendships, therefore, and no less aversions,

Though oft well founded, which confirmed but more

His prepossessions, like the laws of Persians

And Medes, would ne'er revoke what went before.

His feelings had not those strange fits, like tertians,

Of common likings, which make some deplore

What they should laugh at—the mere ague still

Of men's regard, the fever or the chill.

XVIII.

"'T is not in mortals to command success:"[659]

But do you more, Sempronius—don't deserve it,

And take my word, you won't have any less.

Be wary, watch the time, and always serve it;

Give gently way, when there's too great a press;

And for your conscience, only learn to nerve it;

For, like a racer, or a boxer training,

'T will make, if proved, vast efforts without paining.

XIX.

Lord Henry also liked to be superior,

As most men do, the little or the great;

The very lowest find out an inferior,

At least they think so, to exert their state

Upon: for there are very few things wearier

Than solitary Pride's oppressive weight,

Which mortals generously would divide,

By bidding others carry while they ride.

XX.

In birth, in rank, in fortune likewise equal,

O'er Juan he could no distinction claim;

In years he had the advantage of Time's sequel;

And, as he thought, in country much the same—

Because bold Britons have a tongue and free quill,

At which all modern nations vainly aim;

And the Lord Henry was a great debater,

So that few Members kept the House up later.

XXI.

These were advantages: and then he thought—

It was his foible, but by no means sinister—

That few or none more than himself had caught

Court mysteries, having been himself a minister:

He liked to teach that which he had been taught,

And greatly shone whenever there had been a stir;

And reconciled all qualities which grace man,

Always a patriot—and, sometimes, a placeman.

XXII.

He liked the gentle Spaniard for his gravity;

He almost honoured him for his docility;

Because, though young, he acquiesced with suavity,

Or contradicted but with proud humility.

He knew the World, and would not see depravity

In faults which sometimes show the soil's fertility,

If that the weeds o'erlive not the first crop—

For then they are very difficult to stop.

XXIII.

And then he talked with him about Madrid,

Constantinople, and such distant places;

Where people always did as they were bid,

Or did what they should not with foreign graces.

Of coursers also spake they: Henry rid

Well, like most Englishmen, and loved the races;

And Juan, like a true-born Andalusian,

Could back[660] a horse, as Despots ride a Russian.

XXIV.

And thus acquaintance grew, at noble routs,

And diplomatic dinners, or at other—

For Juan stood well both with Ins and Outs,

As in freemasonry a higher brother.

Upon his talent Henry had no doubts;

His manner showed him sprung from a high mother,

And all men like to show their hospitality

To him whose breeding matches with his quality.

XXV.

At Blank-Blank Square;—for we will break no squares[661]

By naming streets: since men are so censorious,

And apt to sow an author's wheat with tares,

Reaping allusions private and inglorious,

Where none were dreamt of, unto Love's affairs,

Which were, or are, or are to be notorious,

That therefore do I previously declare,

Lord Henry's mansion was in Blank-Blank Square.

XXVI.

Also there bin[662] another pious reason

For making squares and streets anonymous;

Which is, that there is scarce a single season

Which doth not shake some very splendid house

With some slight heart-quake of domestic treason—

A topic Scandal doth delight to rouse:

Such I might stumble over unawares,

Unless I knew the very chastest squares.

XXVII.

'T is true, I might have chosen Piccadilly,[663]

A place where peccadillos are unknown;

But I have motives, whether wise or silly,

For letting that pure sanctuary alone.

Therefore I name not square, street, place, until I

Find one where nothing naughty can be shown,

A vestal shrine of Innocence of Heart:

Such are—but I have lost the London Chart.

XXVIII.

At Henry's mansion then, in Blank-Blank Square,

Was Juan a recherché, welcome guest,

As many other noble scions were;

And some who had but Talent for their crest;

Or Wealth, which is a passport everywhere;

Or even mere Fashion, which indeed's the best

Recommendation; and to be well dressed

Will very often supersede the rest.

XXIX.

And since "there's safety in a multitude

Of counsellors," as Solomon has said,

Or some one for him, in some sage, grave mood;—

Indeed we see the daily proof displayed

In Senates, at the Bar, in wordy feud,

Where'er collective wisdom can parade,

Which is the only cause that we can guess

Of Britain's present wealth and happiness;—

XXX.

But as "there's safety" grafted in the number

"Of counsellors," for men,—thus for the sex

A large acquaintance lets not Virtue slumber;

Or should it shake, the choice will more perplex—

Variety itself will more encumber.[LY]

'Midst many rocks we guard more against wrecks—

And thus with women: howsoe'er it shocks some's

Self-love, there's safety in a crowd of coxcombs.

XXXI.

But Adeline had not the least occasion

For such a shield, which leaves but little merit

To Virtue proper, or good education.

Her chief resource was in her own high spirit,

Which judged Mankind at their due estimation;

And for coquetry, she disdained to wear it—

Secure of admiration: its impression

Was faint—as of an every-day possession.

XXXII.

To all she was polite without parade;

To some she showed attention of that kind

Which flatters, but is flattery conveyed

In such a sort as cannot leave behind

A trace unworthy either wife or maid;—

A gentle, genial courtesy of mind,[LZ]

To those who were, or passed for meritorious,

Just to console sad Glory for being glorious;

XXXIII.

Which is in all respects, save now and then,

A dull and desolate appendage. Gaze

Upon the shades of those distinguished men

Who were or are the puppet-shows of praise,

The praise of persecution. Gaze again

On the most favoured; and amidst the blaze

Of sunset halos o'er the laurel-browed,

What can ye recognise?—a gilded cloud.

XXXIV.

There also was of course in Adeline

That calm patrician polish in the address,

Which ne'er can pass the equinoctial line

Of anything which Nature would express;

Just as a Mandarin finds nothing fine,—

At least his manner suffers not to guess,

That anything he views can greatly please:

Perhaps we have borrowed this from the Chinese—[MA]

XXXV.

Perhaps from Horace: his "Nil admirari"

Was what he called the "Art of Happiness"—

An art on which the artists greatly vary,

And have not yet attained to much success.

However, 't is expedient to be wary:

Indifference, certes, don't produce distress;

And rash Enthusiasm in good society

Were nothing but a moral inebriety.

XXXVI.

But Adeline was not indifferent: for

(Now for a common-place!) beneath the snow,

As a Volcano holds the lava more

Within—et cætera. Shall I go on?—No!

I hate to hunt down a tired metaphor,

So let the often-used Volcano go.

Poor thing! How frequently, by me and others,

It hath been stirred up till its smoke quite smothers!

XXXVII.

I'll have another figure in a trice:—

What say you to a bottle of champagne?

Frozen into a very vinous ice,

Which leaves few drops of that immortal rain,

Yet in the very centre, past all price,

About a liquid glassful will remain;

And this is stronger than the strongest grape

Could e'er express in its expanded shape:

XXXVIII.

'T is the whole spirit brought to a quintessence;

And thus the chilliest aspects may concentre

A hidden nectar under a cold presence.[MB]

And such are many—though I only meant her

From whom I now deduce these moral lessons,

On which the Muse has always sought to enter.

And your cold people are beyond all price,

When once you've broken their confounded ice.

XXXIX.

But after all they are a North-West Passage

Unto the glowing India of the soul;

And as the good ships sent upon that message

Have not exactly ascertained the Pole

(Though Parry's efforts look a lucky presage),[MC]

Thus gentlemen may run upon a shoal;

For if the Pole's not open, but all frost

(A chance still), 't is a voyage or vessel lost.

XL.

And young beginners may as well commence

With quiet cruising o'er the ocean, Woman;

While those who are not beginners should have sense

Enough to make for port, ere Time shall summon

With his grey signal-flag; and the past tense,

The dreary Fuimus of all things human,

Must be declined, while Life's thin thread's spun out

Between the gaping heir and gnawing gout.

XLI.

But Heaven must be diverted; its diversion

Is sometimes truculent—but never mind:

The World upon the whole is worth the assertion

(If but for comfort) that all things are kind:

And that same devilish doctrine of the Persian,[664]

Of the "Two Principles," but leaves behind

As many doubts as any other doctrine

Has ever puzzled Faith withal, or yoked her in.

XLII.

The English winter—ending in July,

To recommence in August—now was done.

'T is the postilion's paradise: wheels fly;

On roads, East, South, North, West, there is a run.

But for post-horses who finds sympathy?

Man's pity's for himself, or for his son,

Always premising that said son at college

Has not contracted much more debt than knowledge.

XLIII.

The London winter's ended in July—

Sometimes a little later. I don't err

In this: whatever other blunders lie

Upon my shoulders, here I must aver

My Muse a glass of Weatherology;

For Parliament is our barometer:

Let Radicals its other acts attack,

Its sessions form our only almanack.

XLIV.

When its quicksilver's down at zero,—lo!

Coach, chariot, luggage, baggage, equipage!

Wheels whirl from Carlton Palace to Soho,

And happiest they who horses can engage;

The turnpikes glow with dust; and Rotten Row

Sleeps from the chivalry of this bright age;

And tradesmen, with long bills and longer faces,

Sigh—as the postboys fasten on the traces.

XLV.

They and their bills, "Arcadians both,"[665] are left

To the Greek Kalends of another session.

Alas! to them of ready cash bereft,

What hope remains? Of hope the full possession,

Or generous draft, conceded as a gift,

At a long date—till they can get a fresh one—

Hawked about at a discount, small or large;

Also the solace of an overcharge.

XLVI.

But these are trifles. Downward flies my Lord,

Nodding beside my Lady in his carriage.

Away! away! "Fresh horses!" are the word,

And changed as quickly as hearts after marriage;

The obsequious landlord hath the change restored;

The postboys have no reason to disparage

Their fee; but ere the watered wheels may hiss hence,

The ostler pleads too for a reminiscence.

XLVII.

'T is granted; and the valet mounts the dickey—

That gentleman of Lords and Gentlemen;

Also my Lady's gentlewoman, tricky,

Tricked out, but modest more than poet's pen

Can paint,—"Cosi viaggino i Ricchi!"[666]

(Excuse a foreign slipslop now and then,

If but to show I've travelled: and what's Travel,

Unless it teaches one to quote and cavil?)

XLVIII.

The London winter and the country summer

Were well nigh over. 'T is perhaps a pity,

When Nature wears the gown that doth become her,

To lose those best months in a sweaty city,

And wait until the nightingale grows dumber,

Listening debates not very wise or witty,

Ere patriots their true country can remember;—

But there's no shooting (save grouse) till September.

XLIX.

I've done with my tirade. The World was gone;

The twice two thousand, for whom Earth was made,

Were vanished to be what they call alone—

That is, with thirty servants for parade,

As many guests, or more; before whom groan

As many covers, duly, daily laid.

Let none accuse old England's hospitality—

Its quantity is but condensed to quality.

L.

Lord Henry and the Lady Adeline

Departed like the rest of their compeers,

The peerage, to a mansion very fine;

The Gothic Babel of a thousand years.

None than themselves could boast a longer line,

Where Time through heroes and through beauties steers;

And oaks as olden as their pedigree

Told of their Sires—a tomb in every tree.

LI.

A paragraph in every paper told

Of their departure—such is modern fame:

'T is pity that it takes no further hold

Than an advertisement, or much the same;

When, ere the ink be dry, the sound grows cold.

The Morning Post was foremost to proclaim—

"Departure, for his country seat, to-day,

Lord H. Amundeville and Lady A.

LII.

"We understand the splendid host intends[MD]

To entertain, this autumn, a select

And numerous party of his noble friends;

'Midst whom we have heard, from sources quite correct,

The Duke of D—— the shooting season spends,

With many more by rank and fashion decked;

Also a foreigner of high condition,

The envoy of the secret Russian mission."

LIII.

And thus we see—who doubts the Morning Post?

(Whose articles are like the "Thirty-nine,"

Which those most swear to who believe them most)—

Our gay Russ Spaniard was ordained to shine,

Decked by the rays reflected from his host,

With those who, Pope says, "greatly daring dine."—[667]

'T is odd, but true,—last war the News abounded

More with these dinners than the killed or wounded;—

LIV.

As thus: "On Thursday there was a grand dinner;

Present, Lords A.B.C."—- Earls, dukes, by name

Announced with no less pomp than Victory's winner:

Then underneath, and in the very same

Column: date, "Falmouth. There has lately been here

The Slap-dash regiment, so well known to Fame,

Whose loss in the late action we regret:

The vacancies are filled up—see Gazette."

LV.

To Norman Abbey[668] whirled the noble pair,—

An old, old Monastery once, and now

Still older mansion—of a rich and rare

Mixed Gothic, such as artists all allow

Few specimens yet left us can compare

Withal: it lies, perhaps, a little low,

Because the monks preferred a hill behind,

To shelter their devotion from the wind.

LVI.

It stood embosomed in a happy valley,

Crowned by high woodlands, where the Druid oak[669]

Stood like Caractacus, in act to rally

His host, with broad arms 'gainst the thunder-stroke;

And from beneath his boughs were seen to sally

The dappled foresters; as Day awoke,

The branching stag swept down with all his herd,

To quaff a brook which murmured like a bird.

LVII.

Before the mansion lay a lucid Lake,[670]

Broad as transparent, deep, and freshly fed

By a river, which its softened way did take

In currents through the calmer water spread

Around: the wildfowl nestled in the brake

And sedges, brooding in their liquid bed:

The woods[671] sloped downwards to its brink, and stood

With their green faces fixed upon the flood.

LVIII.

Its outlet dashed into a deep cascade,

Sparkling with foam, until again subsiding,

Its shriller echoes—like an infant made[ME]

Quiet—sank into softer ripples, gliding

Into a rivulet; and thus allayed,

Pursued its course, now gleaming, and now hiding

Its windings through the woods; now clear, now blue,

According as the skies their shadows threw.

LIX.

A glorious remnant of the Gothic pile

(While yet the Church was Rome's) stood half apart

In a grand Arch, which once screened many an aisle.

These last had disappeared—a loss to Art:

The first yet frowned superbly o'er the soil,

And kindled feelings in the roughest heart,

Which mourned the power of Time's or Tempest's march,

In gazing on that venerable Arch.[MF]

LX.

Within a niche, nigh to its pinnacle,

Twelve Saints had once stood sanctified in stone;

But these had fallen, not when the friars fell,

But in the war which struck Charles from his throne,

When each house was a fortalice—as tell

The annals of full many a line undone,—

The gallant Cavaliers,[672] who fought in vain

For those who knew not to resign or reign.

LXI.

But in a higher niche, alone, but crowned,

The Virgin-Mother of the God-born Child,

With her Son in her blesséd arms, looked round,

Spared by some chance when all beside was spoiled:

She made the earth below seem holy ground.

This may be superstition, weak or wild;

But even the faintest relics of a shrine

Of any worship wake some thoughts divine.

LXII.

A mighty window, hollow in the centre,

Shorn of its glass of thousand colourings,

Through which the deepened glories once could enter,

Streaming from off the Sun like Seraph's wings,

Now yawns all desolate: now loud, now fainter,

The gale sweeps through its fretwork, and oft sings

The owl his anthem, where the silenced quire

Lie with their Hallelujahs quenched like fire.

LXIII.

But in the noontide of the moon, and when[MG]

The wind is wingéd from one point of heaven,

There moans a strange unearthly sound, which then

Is musical—a dying accent driven

Through the huge Arch, which soars and sinks again.

Some deem it but the distant echo given

Back to the night wind by the waterfall,

And harmonised by the old choral wall:

LXIV.

Others, that some original shape, or form

Shaped by decay perchance, hath given the power

(Though less than that of Memnon's statue,[673] warm

In Egypt's rays, to harp at a fixed hour)

To this grey ruin: with a voice to charm,

Sad, but serene, it sweeps o'er tree or tower;

The cause I know not, nor can solve; but such

The fact:—I've heard it,—once perhaps too much.[674]

LXV.

Amidst the court a Gothic fountain played,

Symmetrical, but decked with carvings quaint—

Strange faces, like to men in masquerade,

And here perhaps a monster, there a saint:

The spring gushed through grim mouths of granite made,

And sparkled into basins, where it spent

Its little torrent in a thousand bubbles,

Like man's vain Glory, and his vainer troubles.

LXVI.

The Mansion's self was vast and venerable,

With more of the monastic than has been

Elsewhere preserved: the cloisters still were stable,

The cells, too, and Refectory, I ween:

An exquisite small chapel had been able,

Still unimpaired, to decorate the scene;

The rest had been reformed, replaced, or sunk,

And spoke more of the baron than the monk.

LXVII.

Huge halls, long galleries, spacious chambers, joined

By no quite lawful marriage of the arts,

Might shock a connoisseur; but when combined,

Formed a whole which, irregular in parts,

Yet left a grand impression on the mind,

At least of those whose eyes are in their hearts:

We gaze upon a giant for his stature,

Nor judge at first if all be true to nature.

LXVIII.

Steel Barons, molten the next generation

To silken rows of gay and gartered Earls,

Glanced from the walls in goodly preservation:

And Lady Marys blooming into girls,

With fair long locks, had also kept their station:

And Countesses mature in robes and pearls:

Also some beauties of Sir Peter Lely,

Whose drapery hints we may admire them freely.

LXIX.

Judges in very formidable ermine

Were there, with brows that did not much invite

The accused to think their lordships would determine

His cause by leaning much from might to right:

Bishops, who had not left a single sermon;

Attorneys-general, awful to the sight,

As hinting more (unless our judgments warp us)

Of the "Star Chamber" than of "Habeas Corpus."

LXX.

Generals, some all in armour, of the old

And iron time, ere lead had ta'en the lead;

Others in wigs of Marlborough's martial fold,

Huger than twelve of our degenerate breed:[MH]

Lordlings, with staves of white or keys of gold:

Nimrods, whose canvas scarce contained the steed;

And, here and there, some stern high patriot stood,

Who could not get the place for which he sued.

LXXI.

But ever and anon, to soothe your vision,

Fatigued with these hereditary glories,

There rose a Carlo Dolce or a Titian,

Or wilder group of savage Salvatore's:[675]

Here danced Albano's boys, and here the sea shone

In Vernet's ocean lights; and there the stories

Of martyrs awed, as Spagnoletto tainted

His brush with all the blood of all the sainted.

LXXII.

Here sweetly spread a landscape of Lorraine;

There Rembrandt made his darkness equal light,

Or gloomy Caravaggio's gloomier stain

Bronzed o'er some lean and stoic anchorite:—

But, lo! a Teniers woos, and not in vain,

Your eyes to revel in a livelier sight:

His bell-mouthed goblet makes me feel quite Danish[676]

Or Dutch with thirst—What, ho! a flask of Rhenish.[MI]

LXXIII.

Oh, reader! if that thou canst read,—and know,

'T is not enough to spell, or even to read,

To constitute a reader—there must go

Virtues of which both you and I have need;—

Firstly, begin with the beginning—(though

That clause is hard); and secondly, proceed:

Thirdly, commence not with the end—or, sinning

In this sort, end at last with the beginning.

LXXIV.

But, reader, thou hast patient been of late,

While I, without remorse of rhyme, or fear,

Have built and laid out ground at such a rate,

Dan Phoebus takes me for an auctioneer.

That Poets were so from their earliest date,

By Homer's "Catalogue of ships" is clear;

But a mere modern must be moderate—

I spare you then the furniture and plate.

LXXV.

The mellow Autumn came, and with it came

The promised party, to enjoy its sweets.

The corn is cut, the manor full of game;

The pointer ranges, and the sportsman beats

In russet jacket:—lynx-like in his aim;

Full grows his bag, and wonderful his feats.

Ah, nutbrown partridges! Ah, brilliant pheasants!

And ah, ye poachers!—'T is no sport for peasants.

LXXVI.

An English Autumn, though it hath no vines,

Blushing with Bacchant coronals along

The paths o'er which the far festoon entwines

The red grape in the sunny lands of song,

Hath yet a purchased choice of choicest wines;[MJ]

The Claret light, and the Madeira strong.

If Britain mourn her bleakness, we can tell her,

The very best of vineyards is the cellar.

LXXVII.

Then, if she hath not that serene decline

Which makes the southern Autumn's day appear

As if 't would to a second Spring resign

The season, rather than to Winter drear,—

Of in-door comforts still she hath a mine,—

The sea-coal fires,[677] the "earliest of the year;"[678]

Without doors, too, she may compete in mellow,

As what is lost in green is gained in yellow.

LXXVIII.

And for the effeminate villeggialura—

Rife with more horns than hounds—she hath the chase,

So animated that it might allure a

Saint from his beads to join the jocund race:

Even Nimrod's self might leave the plains of Dura,[679]

And wear the Melton jacket for a space:

If she hath no wild boars, she hath a tame

Preserve of bores, who ought to be made game.[MK]

LXXIX.

The noble guests,[680] assembled at the Abbey,

Consisted of—we give the sex the pas—

The Duchess of Fitz-Fulke; the Countess Crabby;[ML][681]

The Ladies Scilly, Busey;—Miss Eclat,

Miss Bombazeen, Miss Mackstay, Miss O'Tabby,

And Mrs. Rabbi,[682] the rich banker's squaw;

Also the honourable Mrs. Sleep,

Who looked a white lamb, yet was a black sheep:

LXXX.

With other Countesses of Blank—but rank;

At once the "lie"[683] and the élite of crowds;

Who pass like water filtered in a tank,

All purged and pious from their native clouds;

Or paper turned to money by the Bank:

No matter how or why, the passport shrouds

The passée and the past; for good society

Is no less famed for tolerance than piety,—

LXXXI.

That is, up to a certain point; which point

Forms the most difficult in punctuation.

Appearances appear to form the joint

On which it hinges in a higher station;

And so that no explosion cry "Aroint

Thee, witch!"[684] or each Medea has her Jason;

Or (to the point with Horace and with Pulci)[MM]

"Omne tulit punctum, quæ miscuit utile dulci."[685]

LXXXII.

I can't exactly trace their rule of right,

Which hath a little leaning to a lottery.

I've seen a virtuous woman put down quite

By the mere combination of a coterie;

Also a so-so matron boldly fight

Her way back to the world by dint of plottery,[MN]

And shine the very Siria,[686] of the spheres,

Escaping with a few slight, scarless sneers.

LXXXIII.

I have seen more than I'll say:—but we will see[MO]

How our "villeggiatura" will get on.

The party might consist of thirty-three

Of highest caste—the Brahmins of the ton.

I have named a few, not foremost in degree,

But ta'en at hazard as the rhyme may run.

By way of sprinkling, scattered amongst these,

There also were some Irish absentees.

LXXXIV.

There was Parolles,[687] too, the legal bully,[MP]

Who limits all his battles to the Bar

And Senate: when invited elsewhere, truly,

He shows more appetite for words than war.

There was the young bard Rackrhyme, who had newly

Come out and glimmered as a six weeks' star.

There was Lord Pyrrho, too, the great freethinker;

And Sir John Pottledeep, the mighty drinker.

LXXXV.

There was the Duke of Dash,[688] who was a—duke,

"Aye, every inch a" duke; there were twelve peers

Like Charlemagne's—and all such peers in look

And intellect, that neither eyes nor ears

For commoners had ever them mistook.

There were the six Miss Rawbolds—pretty dears!

All song and sentiment; whose hearts were set

Less on a convent than a coronet.

LXXXVI.

There were four Honourable Misters, whose

Honour was more before their names than after;

There was the preux Chevalier de la Ruse,[689]

Whom France and Fortune lately deigned to waft here,

Whose chiefly harmless talent was to amuse;

But the clubs found it rather serious laughter,

Because—such was his magic power to please—

The dice seemed charmed, too, with his repartees.

LXXXVII.

There was Dick Dubious,[690] the metaphysician,

Who loved philosophy and a good dinner;

Angle, the soi-disant mathematician;

Sir Henry Silvercup, the great race-winner.

There was the Reverend Rodomont Precisian,

Who did not hate so much the sin as sinner:

And Lord Augustus Fitz-Plantagenet,

Good at all things, but better at a bet.

LXXXVIII.

There was Jack Jargon, the gigantic guardsman;[691]

And General Fireface,[692] famous in the field,

A great tactician, and no less a swordsman,

Who ate, last war, more Yankees than he killed.

There was the waggish Welsh Judge, Jefferies Hardsman,

In his grave office so completely skilled,

That when a culprit came for condemnation,

He had his Judge's joke for consolation.[693]

LXXXIX.

Good company's a chess-board—there are kings,

Queens, bishops, knights, rooks, pawns; the World's a game;

Save that the puppets pull at their own strings,

Methinks gay Punch hath something of the same.

My Muse, the butterfly hath but her wings,

Not stings, and flits through ether without aim,

Alighting rarely:—were she but a hornet,

Perhaps there might be vices which would mourn it.

XC.

I had forgotten—but must not forget—

An orator, the latest of the session,

Who had delivered well a very set

Smooth speech, his first and maidenly transgression

Upon debate: the papers echoed yet

With his début, which made a strong impression,

And ranked with what is every day displayed—

"The best first speech that ever yet was made."

XCI.

Proud of his "Hear hims!" proud, too, of his vote,

And lost virginity of oratory,

Proud of his learning (just enough to quote),

He revelled in his Ciceronian glory:

With memory excellent to get by rote,

With wit to hatch a pun or tell a story,

Graced with some merit, and with more effrontery,[MQ]

"His country's pride," he came down to the country.

XCII.

There also were two wits by acclamation,

Longbow from Ireland,[694] Strongbow from the Tweed[695]—Both

lawyers and both men of education—

But Strongbow's wit was of more polished breed;

Longbow was rich in an imagination

As beautiful and bounding as a steed,

But sometimes stumbling over a potato,—

While Strongbow's best things might have come from Cato.

XCIII.

Strongbow was like a new-tuned harpsichord;

But Longbow wild as an Æolian harp,

With which the Winds of heaven can claim accord,

And make a music, whether flat or sharp.

Of Strongbow's talk you would not change a word:

At Longbow's phrases you might sometimes carp:

Both wits—one born so, and the other bred—

This by his heart—his rival by his head.

XCIV.

If all these seem an heterogeneous mass

To be assembled at a country seat,

Yet think, a specimen of every class

Is better than a humdrum tête-à-tête.

The days of Comedy are gone, alas!

When Congreve's fool could vie with Molière's bête:

Society is smoothed to that excess,

That manners hardly differ more than dress.

XCV.

Our ridicules are kept in the back-ground—

Ridiculous enough, but also dull;

Professions, too, are no more to be found

Professional; and there is nought to cull[MR]

Of Folly's fruit; for though your fools abound,

They're barren, and not worth the pains to pull.

Society is now one polished horde,

Formed of two mighty tribes, the Bores and Bored.

XCVI.

But from being farmers, we turn gleaners, gleaning

The scanty but right-well threshed ears of Truth;

And, gentle reader! when you gather meaning,

You may be Boaz, and I—modest Ruth.

Further I'd quote, but Scripture intervening

Forbids. A great impression in my youth

Was made by Mrs. Adams, where she cries,

"That Scriptures out of church are blasphemies."[696]

XCVII.

But what we can we glean in this vile age[MS]

Of chaff, although our gleanings be not grist.

I must not quite omit the talking sage,

Kit-Cat, the famous Conversationist,[697]

Who, in his common-place book, had a page

Prepared each morn for evenings. "List, oh list!"

"Alas, poor ghost!"[698]—What unexpected woes

Await those who have studied their bons-mots!

XCVIII.

Firstly, they must allure the conversation,

By many windings to their clever clinch;

And secondly, must let slip no occasion,

Nor bate (abate) their hearers of an inch,[MT]

But take an ell—and make a great sensation,

If possible; and thirdly, never flinch

When some smart talker puts them to the test,

But seize the last word, which no doubt's the best.

XCIX.

Lord Henry and his lady were the hosts;

The party we have touched on were the guests.

Their table was a board to tempt even ghosts

To pass the Styx for more substantial feasts.

I will not dwell upon ragoûts or roasts,

Albeit all human history attests

That happiness for Man—the hungry sinner!—

Since Eve ate apples, much depends on dinner.

C.

Witness the lands which "flowed with milk and honey,"

Held out unto the hungry Israelites:

To this we have added since, the love of money,

The only sort of pleasure which requites.

Youth fades, and leaves our days no longer sunny;

We tire of mistresses and parasites;

But oh, ambrosial cash! Ah! who would lose thee?

When we no more can use, or even abuse thee!

CI.

The gentlemen got up betimes to shoot,

Or hunt: the young, because they liked the sport—

The first thing boys like after play and fruit;

The middle-aged, to make the day more short;

For ennui[699] is a growth of English root,

Though nameless in our language:—we retort

The fact for words, and let the French translate

That awful yawn which sleep can not abate.

CII.

The elderly walked through the library,

And tumbled books, or criticised the pictures,

Or sauntered through the gardens piteously,

And made upon the hot-house several strictures,

Or rode a nag which trotted not too high,

Or on the morning papers read their lectures,

Or on the watch their longing eyes would fix,

Longing at sixty for the hour of six.

CIII.

But none were gêné: the great hour of union

Was rung by dinner's knell; till then all were

Masters of their own time—or in communion,

Or solitary, as they chose to bear

The hours, which how to pass is but to few known.

Each rose up at his own, and had to spare

What time he chose for dress, and broke his fast

When, where, and how he chose for that repast.

CIV.

The ladies—some rouged, some a little pale—

Met the morn as they might. If fine, they rode,

Or walked; if foul, they read, or told a tale,

Sung, or rehearsed the last dance from abroad;

Discussed the fashion which might next prevail,

And settled bonnets by the newest code,

Or crammed twelve sheets into one little letter,

To make each correspondent a new debtor.

CV.

For some had absent lovers, all had friends;

The earth has nothing like a she epistle,

And hardly Heaven—because it never ends—

I love the mystery of a female missal,

Which, like a creed, ne'er says all it intends,

But full of cunning as Ulysses' whistle,[MU]

When he allured poor Dolon:[700]—you had better

Take care what you reply to such a letter.

CVI.

Then there were billiards; cards, too, but no dice;—

Save in the clubs no man of honour plays;—

Boats when 't was water, skating when 't was ice,

And the hard frost destroyed the scenting days:

And angling, too, that solitary vice,

Whatever Izaak Walton sings or says:

The quaint, old, cruel coxcomb, in his gullet

Should have a hook, and a small trout to pull it.[701]

CVII.

With evening came the banquet and the wine;

The conversazione—the duet

Attuned by voices more or less divine

(My heart or head aches with the memory yet).

The four Miss Rawbolds in a glee would shine;

But the two youngest loved more to be set

Down to the harp—because to Music's charms

They added graceful necks, white hands and arms.

CVIII.

Sometimes a dance (though rarely on field days,

For then the gentlemen were rather tired)

Displayed some sylph-like figures in its maze;

Then there was small-talk ready when required;

Flirtation—but decorous; the mere praise

Of charms that should or should not be admired.

The hunters fought their fox-hunt o'er again,

And then retreated soberly—at ten.

CIX.

The politicians, in a nook apart,

Discussed the World, and settled all the spheres:

The wits watched every loophole for their art,

To introduce a bon-mot head and ears;

Small is the rest of those who would be smart,

A moment's good thing may have cost them years

Before they find an hour to introduce it;

And then, even then, some bore may make them lose it.

CX.

But all was gentle and aristocratic

In this our party; polished, smooth, and cold,

As Phidian forms cut out of marble Attic.

There now are no Squire Westerns, as of old;

And our Sophias are not so emphatic,

But fair as then, or fairer to behold:

We have no accomplished blackguards, like Tom Jones,

But gentlemen in stays, as stiff as stones.

CXI.

They separated at an early hour;

That is, ere midnight—which is London's noon:

But in the country ladies seek their bower

A little earlier than the waning moon.

Peace to the slumbers of each folded flower—

May the rose call back its true colour soon!

Good hours of fair cheeks are the fairest tinters,

And lower the price of rouge—at least some winters.[702]

FOOTNOTES:

[653] Fy. 12th 1823.

[654] {482}[The allusion is to the refrain of Canning's verses on Pitt, "The Pilot that weathered the storm." Compare, too, "The daring pilot in extremity" (i.e. the Earl of Shaftesbury), who "sought the storms" (Dryden's Absalom and Achitophel, lines 159-161).]

[655] [Johnson loved "dear, dear Bathurst," because he was "a very good hater."—See Boswell's Johnson, 1876, p. 78 (Croker's footnote).]

[656] {483}[So, too, Charles Kingsley, in Westward Ho! ii. 299, 300, calls Don Quixote "the saddest of books in spite of all its wit."—Notes and Queries, Second Series, iii. 124.]

[LX] By that great Epic——.—[MS.]

[657] {484}["Your husband is in his old lunes again." Merry Wives of Windsor, act iv. sc. 2, lines 16, 17.]

[658] ["Davus sum, non Oedipus." Terence, Andria, act i. sc. 2, line 23.]

[659] {485}

["'T is not in mortals to command success,

But we'll do more, Sempronius—we'll deserve it."

Addison's Cato, act i. sc. 2, ed. 1777, ii. 77.]

[660] {487}[Compare—"The colt that's backed and burthened being young." Venus and Adonis, lxx. line 5.]

[661] [To "break square," or "squares," is to interrupt the regular order, as in the proverbial phrase, "It breaks no squares," i.e. does no harm—does not matter. Compare Sterne, Tristram Shandy (1802), ii. v. 152, "This fault in Trim broke no squares with them" (N. Engl. Dict., art. "Break," No. 46). The origin of the phrase is uncertain, but it may, perhaps, refer to military tactics. Shakespeare (Henry V., act iv. sc. 2, line 28) speaks of "squares of battle."]

[662]

"With every thing that pretty bin,

My lady sweet, arise."

Cymbeline, act ii. sc. 3, lines, 25, 26.

[So Warburton and Hanmer. The folio reads "that pretty is." See Knight's Shakespeare, Pictorial Edition, Tragedies, i. 203.]

[663] {488}[The house which Byron occupied, 1815-1816, No. 13, Piccadilly Terrace, was the property of Elizabeth, Duchess of Devonshire.]

[LY] {489}

The slightest obstacle which may encumber

The path downhill is something grand.—[MS. erased.]

[LZ] Not even in fools who howsoever blind.—[MS. erased.]

[MA] {490}

That anything is new to a Chinese;

And such is Europe's fashionable ease.—[MS. erased.]

[MB] {491}A hidden wine beneath an icy presence.—[MS. erased.]

[MC] Though this we hope has been reserved for this age.—[MS. erased.]

[664] ["For the creed of Zoroaster," see Sir Walter Scott, Letters on Demonology and Witchcraft, 1830, pp. 87, 88. (See, too, Cain, act ii. sc. 2, line 404, Poetical Works, 1901, v. 254, note 2.)]

[665] {492}"Arcades ambo." [Virgil, Bucol., Ecl. vii. 4.]

[666] {493}[So travel the rich.]

[MD] {494}—the noble host intends.—[MS. erased.]

[667] ["Judicious drank, and greatly-daring dined." Pope, Dunciad, iv. 318.]

[668] {495}[Byron's description of the place of his inheritance, which was to know him no more, is sketched from memory, but it unites the charm of a picture with the accuracy of a ground-plan. Eight years had gone by since he had looked his last on "venerable arch" and "lucid lake" (see "Epistle to Augusta," stanza viii. lines 7, 8), but he had not forgotten, he could not forget, that enchanted and enchanting scene.

Newstead Abbey or Priory was founded by Henry II., by way of deodand or expiation for the murder of Thomas Becket. Lands which bordered the valley of the Leen, and which had formed part of Sherwood Forest, were assigned for the use and endowment of a chapter of "black canons regular of the order of St. Augustine," and on a site, by the river-side to the south of the forest uplands (stanza lv. lines 5-8) the new stede, or place, or station, arose. It was a "Norman Abbey" (stanza lv. line 1) which the Black Canons dedicated to Our Lady, and, here and there, in the cloisters, traces of Norman architecture remain, but the enlargement and completion of the monastery was carried out in successive stages and "transition periods," in a style or styles which, perhaps, more by hap than by cunning, Byron rightly named "mixed Gothic" (stanza lv. line 4). To work their mills, and perhaps to drain the marshy valley, the monks dammed the Leen and excavated a chain of lakes—the largest to the north-west, Byron's "lucid lake;" a second to the south of the Abbey; and a third, now surrounded with woods, and overlooked by the "wicked lord's" "ragged rock" below the Abbey, half a mile to the south-east. The "cascade," which flows over and through a stone-work sluice, and forms a rocky water-fall, issues from the upper lake, and is in full view of the west front of the Abbey. Almost at right angles to these lakes are three ponds: the Forest Pond to the north of the stone wall, which divides the garden from the forest; the square "Eagle" Pond in the Monks' Garden; and the narrow stew-pond, bordered on either side with overhanging yews, which drains into the second or Garden Lake. Byron does not enlarge on this double chain of lakes and ponds, and, perhaps for the sake of pictorial unity, converts the second (if a second then existed) and third lakes into a river.

The Abbey, which, at the dissolution of monasteries in 1539, was handed over by Henry VIII. to Sir John Byron, "steward and warden of the forest of Shirewood," was converted, here and there, more or less, into a baronial "mansion" (stanza lxvi.). It is, roughly speaking, a square block of buildings, flanking the sides of a grassy quadrangle. Surrounding the quadrangle are two-storied cloisters, and in the centre a "Gothic fountain" (stanza lxv. line 1) of composite workmanship. The upper portion of the stonework is hexagonal, and is ornamented with a double row of gargoyles (all "monsters" and no "saints," recalling, perhaps identical with, the "seven deadly sins" gargoyles, still in situ in the quadrangle of Magdalen College, Oxford); the lower half, which belongs to the seventeenth or eighteenth century, is hollowed into niches of a Roman or classical design. (In Byron's time the fountain stood in a courtyard in front of the Abbey, but before he composed this canto it had been restored by Colonel Wildman to its original place within the quadrangle. Byron was acquainted with the change, and writes accordingly.) When the Byrons took possession of the Abbey the upper stories of the cloisters were converted, on three sides of the quadrangle, into galleries, and on the fourth, the north side, into a library. Abutting on the cloisters are the monastic buildings proper, in part transformed, but with "much of the monastic" preserved. On the west, the front of the Abbey, the ground floor consists of the entrance hall and Monks' Parlour, and, above, the Guests' Refectory or Banqueting-hall, and the Prior's Parlour. On the south, the Xenodochium or Guesten Hall, and, above, the Monks' Refectory, or Grand Drawing-room; on the south and east, on the ground floor, the Prior's Lodgings, the Chapter House ("the exquisite small chapel," stanza lxvi. line 5), the "slype" or passage between church and Chapter House; and in the upper story, the state bedrooms, named after the kings, Edward III., Henry VII., etc., who, by the terms of the grant of land to the Prior and Canons, were entitled to free quarters in the Abbey. During Byron's brief tenure of Newstead, and for long years before, these "huge halls, long galleries, and spacious chambers" (stanza lxxvii. line 1) were half dismantled, and in a more or less ruinous condition. A few pictures remained on the walls of the Great Drawing-room, of the Prior's Parlour, and in the apartments of the south-east wing or annexe, which dates from the seventeenth century (see the account of a visit to Newstead in 1812, in Beauties of England and Wales, 1813, xii. 401-405). There are and were portraits, by Lely (stanza lxviii. line 7), of a Lady Byron, of Fanny Jennings, Duchess of Tyrconnel, "loveliness personified," of Mrs. Hughes, and of Nell Gwynne; by Sir Godfrey Kneller, of William and Mary; by unnamed artists, of George I. and George II.; and by Ramsay, of George III. There are portraits of a fat Prior, William Sandall, with a jewelled reliquary; of "Sir John the Little with the Great Beard," who ruled in the Prior's stead; and there is the portrait, a votive tablet of penitence and remorse, "of that Lord Arundel Who struck in heat the child he loved so well" (see "A Picture at Newstead," by Matthew Arnold, Poetical Works, 1890, p. 177); but of portraits of judges or bishops, or of pictures by old masters, there is neither trace nor record.

But the characteristic feature of Newstead Abbey, so familiar that description seems unnecessary, and, yet, never quite accurately described, is the west front of the Priory Church, which is in line with the west front of the Abbey. "Half apart," the southern portion of this front, which abuts on the windows of the Prior's Parlour, and the room above, where Byron slept, flanks and conceals the west end of the north cloisters and library; but, with this exception, it is a screen, and nothing more. In the centre is the "mighty window" (stanza lxii. line 1), shorn of glass and tracery; above are six lancet windows (which Byron seems to have regarded as niches), and, above again, in a "higher niche" (stanza lxi. line 1), is the crowned Virgin with the Babe in her arms, which escaped, as by a miracle, the "fiery darts"—the shot and cannon-balls of the Cromwellian troopers. On either side of the central window are "two blank windows containing tracery ['geometrical decorated'] ... carved [in relief] on the solid ashlar;" on either side of the window, and at the northern and southern extremities of the front, are buttresses with canopied niches, in each of which a saint or apostle must once have stood. Over the west door there is the mutilated figure of (?) the Saviour, but of twelve saints or twelve niches there is no trace. The "grand arch" is an ivy-clad screen, and nothing more. Behind and beyond, in place of vanished nave, of aisle and transept, is the smooth green turf; and at the east end, on the site of the high altar, stands the urn-crowned masonry of Boatswain's tomb.

Newstead Abbey was sold by Lord Byron to his old schoolfellow, Colonel Thomas Wildman, in November, 1817. The house and property were resold in 1861, by his widow, to William Frederick Webb, Esq., a traveller in many lands, the friend and host of David Livingstone. At his death the estate was inherited by his daughter, Miss Geraldine Webb, who was married to General Sir Herbert Charles Chermside, G.C.M.G., etc., Governor of Queensland, in 1899.

For Newstead Abbey, see Beauties of England and Wales, 1813, xii. Part I. 401-405 (often reprinted without acknowledgment); Abbotsford and Newstead Abbey, by Washington Irving, 1835; Journal of the Archaeological Association (papers by T.J. Pettigrew, F.R.S., and Arthur Ashpitel, F.S.A.), 1854, vol. ix. pp. 14-39; and A Souvenir of Newstead Abbey (illustrated by a series of admirable photographs), by Richard Allen, Nottingham, 1874, etc., etc.]

[669] {497}[The woodlands were sacrificed to the needs or fancies of Byron's great-uncle, the "wicked Lord." One splendid oak, known as the "Pilgrim's Oak," which stood and stands near the north lodge of the park, near the "Hut," was bought in by the neighbouring gentry, and made over to the estate. Perhaps by the Druid oak Byron meant to celebrate this "last of the clan," which, in his day, before the woods were replanted, must have stood out in solitary grandeur.]

[670] {498}[Compare "Epistle to Augusta," stanza x. line 1, Poetical Works, 1901, iv. 68.]

[671] [The little wood which Byron planted at the south-east corner of the upper or "Stable" Lake, known as "Poet's Corner," still slopes to the water's brink. Nor have the wild-fowl diminished. The lower of the three lakes is specially reserved as a breeding-place.]

[ME] Its shriller echo——.—[MS.]

[MF]

Which sympathized with Time's and Tempest's march,

In gazing on that high and haughty Arch.—[MS.]

[672] {499}[See lines "On Leaving Newstead Abbey," stanza 5, Poetical Works, 1898, i. 3, note 1.]

[MG] But in the stillness of the moon——.—[MS.]

[673] {500}[Vide ante, The Deformed Transformed, Part I. line 532, Poetical Works, 1901, v. 497.]

[674] This is not a frolic invention: it is useless to specify the spot, or in what county, but I have heard it both alone and in company with those who will never hear it more. It can, of course, be accounted for by some natural or accidental cause, but it was a strange sound, and unlike any other I have ever heard (and I have heard many above and below the surface of the earth produced in ruins, etc., etc., or caverns).—[MS.]

["The unearthly sound" may still be heard at rare intervals, but it is difficult to believe that the "huge arch" can act as an Æolian harp. Perhaps the smaller lancet windows may vocalize the wind.]

[MH] {501}Prouder of such a toy than of their breed.—[MS. erased.]

[675] {502}Salvator Rosa. The wicked necessity of rhyming obliges me to adapt the name to the verse.—[MS.]

[Compare—

"Whate'er Lorraine light touch'd with softening hue,

Or savage Rosa dash'd, or learned Poussin drew."

Thomson's Castle of Indolence, Canto I. stanza xxxviii. lines 8, 9.]

[676] If I err not, "your Dane" is one of Iago's catalogue of nations "exquisite in their drinking."

["Your Dane, your German, and your swag-bellied Hollander—drink hoa! are nothing to your English." "Is your Englishman so exquisite in his drinking?" (So Collier and Knight. The Quarto reads "expert").—Othello, act ii. sc. 3, lines 71-74.]

[MI]

His bell-mouthed goblet—and his laughing group

Provoke my thirst—what ho! a flask of Rhenish.—[MS. erased.]

[MJ] {503}Hath yet at night the very best of wines.—[MS.]

[677] ["Sea-coal" (i.e. Newcastle coal), as distinguished from "charcoal" and "earth-coal." But the qualification must have been unusual and old-fashioned in 1822. "Earth-coal" is found in large quantities on the Newstead estate, and the Abbey, far below its foundations, is tunnelled by a coal-drift.]

[678] [See Gray's omitted stanza—

"'Here scatter'd oft, the earliest of the year,

By hands unseen, are showers of violets found;

The red-breast loves to build and warble here,

And little footsteps lightly print the ground.'

As fine ... as any in his Elegy. I wonder that he could have the heart to omit it."—"Extracts from a Diary," February 27, 1821, Letters, 1901, v. 210. The stanza originally preceded the Epitaph.]

[679] {504}In Assyria. [See Daniel iii. 1.]

[MK]

—— she hath the tame

Preserved within doors—why not make them Game?—[MS.]

[680] [It is difficult, if not impossible, to furnish a clue to the names of all the guests at Norman Abbey. Some who are included in this ghostly "house-party" seem to be, and, perhaps, were meant to be, nomina umbrarum; and others are, undoubtedly, contemporary celebrities, under a more or less transparent disguise. A few of these shadows have been substantiated (vide infra, et post), but the greater part decline to be materialized or verified.]

[ML]—— the Countess Squabby.—[MS.]

[681] [Perhaps Mary, widow of the eighth Earl of Cork and Orrery: "Dowager Cork," "Old Corky," of Joseph Jekyll's Correspondence, 1894, pp. 83, 275.]

[682] [Mrs. Rabbi may be Mrs. Coutts, the Mrs. Million of Vivian Grey (1826, i. 183), who arrived at "Château Desir in a crimson silk pelisse, hat and feathers, with diamond ear-rings, and a rope of gold round her neck."]

[683] {505}[Lie, lye, or ley, is a solution of potassium salts obtained by bleaching wood-ashes. Byron seems to have confused "lie" with "lee," i.e. dregs, sediment.]

[684] ["Aroint thee, witch! the rump-fed ronyon cries." Macbeth, act ii. sc. 3, line 6.]

[MM] Or (to come to the point, like my friend Pulci).—[MS. erased.]

[685] [Hor., Epist. Ad Pisones, line 343.]

[MN]—— by fear or flattery.—[MS. erased.]

[686] Siria, i.e. bitch-star.

[MO] I have seen—no matter what—we now shall see.—[MS. erased.]

[687] {506}[Parolles [see All's Well that Ends Well, passim] is Brougham (vide ante, the suppressed stanzas, Canto I. pp. 67-69). It is possible that this stanza was written after the Canto as a whole was finished. But, if not, an incident which took place in the House of Commons, April 17, 1823, during a debate on Catholic Emancipation, may be quoted in corroboration of Brougham's unreadiness with regard to the point of honour. In the course of his speech he accused Canning of "monstrous truckling for the purpose of obtaining office," and Canning, without waiting for Brougham to finish, gave him the lie: "I rise to say that that is false" (Parl. Deb., N.S. vol. 8, p. 1091).

There was a "scene," which ended in an exchange of explanations and quasi-apologies, and henceforth, as a rule, parliamentary insults were given and received without recourse to duelling. Byron was not aware that the "old order" had passed or was passing. Compare Hazlitt, in The Spirit of the Age, 1825, pp. 302, 303: "He [Brougham] is adventurous, but easily panic-struck, and sacrifices the vanity of self-opinion to the necessity of self-preservation ... himself the first to get out of harm's way and escape from the danger;" and Mr. Parthenopex Puff (W. Stewart Rose), in Vivian Grey (1826, i. 186, 187), "Oh! he's a prodigious fellow! What do you think Booby says? he says, that Foaming Fudge [Brougham] can do more than any man in Great Britain; that he had one day to plead in the King's Bench, spout at a tavern, speak in the House, and fight a duel—and that he found time for everything but the last."]

[MP] There was, too, Henry B——.—[MS. erased.]

[688] [In his Journal for December 5, 1813, Byron writes: "The Duke of —— called.... His Grace is a good, noble, ducal person" (Letters, 1898, ii. 361). Possibly the earlier "Duke of Dash" was William Spencer, sixth Duke of Devonshire, an old schoolfellow of Byron's, who was eager to renew the acquaintance (Letters, 1899, iii. 98, note 2); and, if so, he may be reckoned as one of the guests of "Norman Abbey."]

[689] {507}[Gronow (Reminiscences, 1889, i. 234-240) identifies the Chevalier de la Ruse with Casimir Comte de Montrond (1768-1843), back-stairs diplomatist, wit, gambler, and man of fashion. He was the lifelong companion, if not friend, of Talleyrand, who pleaded for him: "Qui est-ce qui ne l'aimerait pas, il est si vicieux!" At one time in the pay of Napoleon, he fell under his displeasure, and, to avoid arrest, spent two years of exile (1812-14) in England. "He was not," says Gronow, "a great talker, nor did he swagger ... or laugh at his own bons-mots. He was demure, sleek, sly, and dangerous.... In the London clubs he went by the name of Old French." He was a constant guest of the Duke of York's at Oatlands, "and won much at his whist-table" (English Whist, by W.P. Courtney, 1894, p. 181). For his second residence in England, and for a sketch by D'Orsay, see A Portion of the Journal, etc., by Thomas Raikes, 1857, frontispiece to vol. iv., et vols. i.-iv. passim. See, for biographical notice, L'Ami de M. de Talleyrand, par Henri Welschinger, La Revue de Paris, 1895, Fev., tom. i. pp. 640-654.]

[690] [Perhaps Sir James Mackintosh—a frequent guest at Holland House.]

[691] {508}[Possibly Colonel (afterwards Sir James) Macdonell [d. 1857], "a man of colossal stature," who occupied and defended the Château of Hougoumont on the night before the battle of Waterloo. (See Gronow, Reminiscences, 1889, i. 76, 77.)]

[692] [Sir George Prevost (1767-1816), the Governor-General of British North America, and nominally Commander-in-chief of the Army in the second American War, contributed, by his excess of caution, supineness, and delay, to the humiliation of the British forces. The particular allusion is to his alleged inaction at a critical moment in the engagement of September 11, 1814, between Commodore Macdonough and Captain Downie in Plattsburg Bay. "A letter was sent to Capt. Downie, strongly urging him to come on, as the army had long been waiting for his co-operation.... The brave Downie replied that he required no urging to do his duty.... He was as good as his word. The guns were scaled when he got under way, upon hearing which Sir George issued an order for the troops to cook, instead of that of instant co-operation."—To Editor of the Montreal Herald, May 23, 1815, Letters of Veritas, 1815, pp. 116, 117. See, too, The Quarterly Review, July, 1822, vol. xxvii. p. 446.]

[693] [George Hardinge (1744-1816), who was returned M.P. for Old Sarum in 1784, was appointed, in 1787, Senior Justice of the Counties of Brecon, Glamorgan, and Radnor. According to the Gentleman's Magazine, 1816 (vol. lxxxvi. p. 563), "In conversation he had few equals.... He delighted in pleasantries, and always afforded to his auditors abundance of mirth and entertainment as well as information." Byron seems to have supposed that these "pleasantries" found their way into his addresses to condemned prisoners, but if the charges printed in his Miscellaneous Works, edited by John Nichols in 1818, are reported in full, he was entirely mistaken. They are tedious, but the "waggery" is conspicuous by its absence.]

[MQ] {509}With all his laurels growing upon one tree.—[MS. erased.]

[694] [John Philpot Curran (1750-1817). "Did you know Curran?" asked Byron of Lady Blessington (Conversations, 1834, p. 176); "he was the most wonderful person I ever saw. In him was combined an imagination the most brilliant and profound, with a flexibility and wit that would have justified the observation applied to——that his heart was in his head." (See, too, Detached Thoughts, No. 24, Letters, 1901, v. 421.)]

[695] [For Thomas Lord Erskine (1750-1823), see Letters, 1898, ii. 390, note 5. See, too, Detached Thoughts, No. 93, Letters, 1901, v. 455, 456. In his Spirit of the Age, 1825, pp. 297, 298, Hazlitt contrasts "the impassioned appeals and flashes of wit of a Curran ... the golden tide of wisdom, eloquence, and fancy of a Burke," with the "dashing and graceful manner" which concealed the poverty and "deadness" of the matter of Erskine's speeches.]

[MR] {510}

—— all classes mostly pull

At the same oar——.—[MS. erased.]

[696] {511}["Mrs. Adams answered Mr. Adams, that it was blasphemous to talk of Scripture out of church." This dogma was broached to her husband—the best Christian in any book.—See The History of the Adventures of Joseph Andrews, Bk. IV. chap. xi. ed. 1876, p. 324.]

[MS] —— in the ripe age.—[MS.]

[697] [Probably Richard Sharp (1759-1835), known as "Conversation Sharp." Byron frequently met him in society in 1813-14, and in "Extracts from a Diary," January 9, 1821, Letters, 1901, v. 161, describes him as "the Conversationist." He visited Byron at the Villa Diodati in the autumn of 1816 (Life, p. 323).]

[698] [Hamlet, act i. sc. 5, line 22.]

[MT] Nor bate (read bait)——.—[MS.]

[699] {512}[See letters to the Earl of Blessington, April 5, 1823, Letters, 1891, vi. 187.]

[MU] {513}

But full of wisdom——.—[MS.]

A sort of rose entwining with a thistle.—[MS. erased.]

[700] [Iliad, x. 341, sq.]

[701] It would have taught him humanity at least. This sentimental savage, whom it is a mode to quote (amongst the novelists) to show their sympathy for innocent sports and old songs, teaches how to sew up frogs, and break their legs by way of experiment, in addition to the art of angling,—the cruelest, the coldest, and the stupidest of pretended sports. They may talk about the beauties of nature, but the angler merely thinks of his dish of fish; he has no leisure to take his eyes from off the streams, and a single bite is worth to him more than all the scenery around. Besides, some fish bite best on a rainy day. The whale, the shark, and the tunny fishery have somewhat of noble and perilous in them; even net fishing, trawling, etc., are more humane and useful. But angling!—no angler can be a good man.

"One of the best men I ever knew,—as humane, delicate-minded, generous, and excellent a creature as any in the world,—was an angler: true, he angled with painted flies, and would have been incapable of the extravagancies of I. Walton."

The above addition was made by a friend in reading over the MS.—"Audi alteram partem."—I leave it to counter-balance my own observation.

[702] {515}B. Fy. 19th 1823.—[MS.]

Canto XVI[768]

I.

The antique Persians taught three useful things,

To draw the bow, to ride, and speak the truth,[769]

This was the mode of Cyrus, best of kings—

A mode adopted since by modern youth.

Bows have they, generally with two strings;

Horses they ride without remorse or ruth;

At speaking truth perhaps they are less clever,

But draw the long bow better now than ever.

II.

The cause of this effect, or this defect,—

"For this effect defective comes by cause,"—[770]

Is what I have not leisure to inspect;

But this I must say in my own applause,

Of all the Muses that I recollect,

Whate'er may be her follies or her flaws

In some things, mine's beyond all contradiction

The most sincere that ever dealt in fiction.

III.

And as she treats all things, and ne'er retreats

From anything, this Epic will contain

A wilderness of the most rare conceits,

Which you might elsewhere hope to find in vain.

'Tis true there be some bitters with the sweets,

Yet mixed so slightly, that you can't complain,

But wonder they so few are, since my tale is

"De rebus cunctis et quibusdam aliis."[771]

IV.

But of all truths which she has told, the most

True is that which she is about to tell.

I said it was a story of a ghost—

What then? I only know it so befell.

Have you explored the limits of the coast,

Where all the dwellers of the earth must dwell?

'Tis time to strike such puny doubters dumb as

The sceptics who would not believe Columbus.

V.

Some people would impose now with authority,

Turpin's or Monmouth Geoffry's Chronicle;

Men whose historical superiority

Is always greatest at a miracle.

But Saint Augustine has the great priority,

Who bids all men believe the impossible,

Because 'tis so. Who nibble, scribble, quibble, he

Quiets at once with "quia impossibile."[772]

VI.

And therefore, mortals, cavil not at all;

Believe:—if 'tis improbable, you must,

And if it is impossible, you shall:

'Tis always best to take things upon trust.

I do not speak profanely to recall

Those holier Mysteries which the wise and just

Receive as Gospel, and which grow more rooted,

As all truths must, the more they are disputed:

VII.

I merely mean to say what Johnson said,

That in the course of some six thousand years,

All nations have believed that from the dead

A visitant at intervals appears:[773]

And what is strangest upon this strange head,

Is, that whatever bar the reason rears

'Gainst such belief, there's something stronger still

In its behalf—let those deny who will.

VIII.

The dinner and the soirée too were done,

The supper too discussed, the dames admired,

The banqueteers had dropped off one by one—

The song was silent, and the dance expired:

The last thin petticoats were vanished, gone

Like fleecy clouds into the sky retired,

And nothing brighter gleamed through the saloon

Than dying tapers—and the peeping moon.

IX.

The evaporation of a joyous day

Is like the last glass of champagne, without

The foam which made its virgin bumper gay;

Or like a system coupled with a doubt;

Or like a soda bottle when its spray

Has sparkled and let half its spirit out;

Or like a billow left by storms behind,

Without the animation of the wind;

X.

Or like an opiate, which brings troubled rest,

Or none; or like—like nothing that I know

Except itself;—such is the human breast;

A thing, of which similitudes can show

No real likeness,—like the old Tyrian vest

Dyed purple, none at present can tell how,

If from a shell-fish or from cochineal.[774]

So perish every Tyrant's robe piece-meal!

XI.

But next to dressing for a rout or ball,

Undressing is a woe; our robe de chambre

May sit like that of Nessus,[775] and recall

Thoughts quite as yellow, but less clear than amber.

Titus exclaimed, "I've lost a day!"[776] Of all

The nights and days most people can remember,

(I have had of both, some not to be disdained,)

I wish they'd state how many they have gained.

XII.

And Juan, on retiring for the night,

Felt restless, and perplexed, and compromised:

He thought Aurora Raby's eyes more bright

Than Adeline (such is advice) advised;

If he had known exactly his own plight,

He probably would have philosophised:

A great resource to all, and ne'er denied

Till wanted; therefore Juan only sighed.

XIII.

He sighed;—the next resource is the full moon,

Where all sighs are deposited; and now

It happened luckily, the chaste orb shone

As clear as such a climate will allow;

And Juan's mind was in the proper tone

To hail her with the apostrophe—"O thou!"

Of amatory egotism the Tuism,[777]

Which further to explain would be a truism.

XIV.

But Lover, Poet, or Astronomer—

Shepherd, or swain—whoever may behold,

Feel some abstraction when they gaze on her;

Great thoughts we catch from thence (besides a cold

Sometimes, unless my feelings rather err);

Deep secrets to her rolling light are told;

The Ocean's tides and mortals' brains she sways,

And also hearts—if there be truth in lays.

XV.

Juan felt somewhat pensive, and disposed

For contemplation rather than his pillow:

The Gothic chamber, where he was enclosed,

Let in the rippling sound of the lake's billow,

With all the mystery by midnight caused:

Below his window waved (of course) willow;

And he stood gazing out on the cascade

That flashed and after darkened in the shade.

XVI.

Upon his table or his toilet,[778]—which

Of these is not exactly ascertained,—

(I state this, for I am cautious to a pitch

Of nicety, where a fact is to be gained,)

A lamp burned high, while he leant from a niche,

Where many a Gothic ornament remained,

In chiselled stone and painted glass, and all

That Time has left our fathers of their Hall.

XVII.

Then, as the night was clear though cold, he threw

His chamber door wide open[779]—and went forth

Into a gallery of a sombre hue,

Long, furnished with old pictures of great worth,

Of knights and dames heroic and chaste too,

As doubtless should be people of high birth;

But by dim lights the portraits of the dead

Have something ghastly, desolate, and dread.

XVIII.

The forms of the grim Knight and pictured Saint

Look living in the moon; and as you turn

Backward and forward to the echoes faint

Of your own footsteps—voices from the Urn

Appear to wake, and shadows wild and quaint

Start from the frames which fence their aspects stern,

As if to ask how you can dare to keep

A vigil there, where all but Death should sleep.

XIX.

And the pale smile of Beauties in the grave,

The charms of other days, in starlight gleams,

Glimmer on high; their buried locks still wave

Along the canvas; their eyes glance like dreams

On ours, or spars within some dusky cave,[780]

But Death is imaged in their shadowy beams.

A picture is the past; even ere its frame

Be gilt, who sate hath ceased to be the same.

XX.

As Juan mused on Mutability,

Or on his Mistress—terms synonymous—

No sound except the echo of his sigh

Or step ran sadly through that antique house;

When suddenly he heard, or thought so, nigh,

A supernatural agent—or a mouse,

Whose little nibbling rustle will embarrass

Most people as it plays along the arras.

XXI.

It was no mouse—but lo! a monk, arrayed[781]

In cowl and beads, and dusky garb, appeared,

Now in the moonlight, and now lapsed in shade,

With steps that trod as heavy, yet unheard;

His garments only a slight murmur made;

He moved as shadowy as the Sisters weird,[782]

But slowly; and as he passed Juan by,

Glanced, without pausing, on him a bright eye.

XXII.

Juan was petrified; he had heard a hint

Of such a Spirit in these halls of old,

But thought, like most men, that there was nothing in't

Beyond the rumour which such spots unfold,

Coined from surviving Superstition's mint,

Which passes ghosts in currency like gold,

But rarely seen, like gold compared with paper.

And did he see this? or was it a vapour?

XXIII.

Once, twice, thrice passed, repassed—the thing of air,

Or earth beneath, or Heaven, or t' other place;

And Juan gazed upon it with a stare,

Yet could not speak or move; but, on its base

As stands a statue, stood: he felt his hair

Twine like a knot of snakes around his face;

He taxed his tongue for words, which were not granted,

To ask the reverend person what he wanted.

XXIV.

The third time, after a still longer pause,

The shadow passed away—but where? the hall

Was long, and thus far there was no great cause

To think his vanishing unnatural:

Doors there were many, through which, by the laws

Of physics, bodies whether short or tall

Might come or go; but Juan could not state

Through which the Spectre seemed to evaporate.

XXV.

He stood—how long he knew not, but it seemed

An age—expectant, powerless, with his eyes

Strained on the spot where first the figure gleamed

Then by degrees recalled his energies,

And would have passed the whole off as a dream,

But could not wake; he was, he did surmise,

Waking already, and returned at length

Back to his chamber, shorn of half his strength.

XXVI.

All there was as he left it: still his taper

Burned, and not blue, as modest tapers use,

Receiving sprites with sympathetic vapour;

He rubbed his eyes, and they did not refuse

Their office: he took up an old newspaper;

The paper was right easy to peruse;

He read an article the King attacking,

And a long eulogy of "Patent Blacking."

XXVII.

This savoured of this world; but his hand shook:

He shut his door, and after having read

A paragraph, I think about Horne Tooke,

Undressed, and rather slowly went to bed.

There, couched all snugly on his pillow's nook,

With what he had seen his phantasy he fed;

And though it was no opiate, slumber crept

Upon him by degrees, and so he slept.

XXVIII.

He woke betimes; and, as may be supposed,

Pondered upon his visitant or vision,

And whether it ought not to be disclosed,

At risk of being quizzed for superstition.

The more he thought, the more his mind was posed:

In the mean time, his valet, whose precision

Was great, because his master brooked no less,

Knocked to inform him it was time to dress.

XXIX.

He dressed; and like young people he was wont

To take some trouble with his toilet, but

This morning rather spent less time upon't;

Aside his very mirror soon was put;

His curls fell negligently o'er his front,

His clothes were not curbed to their usual cut,

His very neckcloth's Gordian knot was tied

Almost an hair's breadth too much on one side.

XXX.

And when he walked down into the Saloon,

He sate him pensive o'er a dish of tea,

Which he perhaps had not discovered soon,

Had it not happened scalding hot to be,

Which made him have recourse unto his spoon;

So much distrait he was, that all could see

That something was the matter—Adeline

The first—but what she could not well divine.

XXXI.

She looked, and saw him pale, and turned as pale

Herself; then hastily looked down, and muttered

Something, but what's not stated in my tale.

Lord Henry said, his muffin was ill buttered;

The Duchess of Fitz-Fulke played with her veil,

And looked at Juan hard, but nothing uttered.

Aurora Raby with her large dark eyes

Surveyed him with a kind of calm surprise.

XXXII.

But seeing him all cold and silent still,

And everybody wondering more or less,

Fair Adeline inquired, "If he were ill?"

He started, and said, "Yes—no—rather—yes."

The family physician had great skill,

And being present, now began to express

His readiness to feel his pulse and tell

The cause, but Juan said, he was "quite well."

XXXIII.

"Quite well; yes,—no."—These answers were mysterious,

And yet his looks appeared to sanction both,

However they might savour of delirious;

Something like illness of a sudden growth

Weighed on his spirit, though by no means serious:

But for the rest, as he himself seemed both

To state the case, it might be ta'en for granted

It was not the physician that he wanted.

XXXIV.

Lord Henry, who had now discussed his chocolate,

Also the muffin whereof he complained,

Said, Juan had not got his usual look elate,

At which he marvelled, since it had not rained;

Then asked her Grace what news were of the Duke of late?

Her Grace replied, his Grace was rather pained

With some slight, light, hereditary twinges

Of gout, which rusts aristocratic hinges.

XXXV.

Then Henry turned to Juan, and addressed

A few words of condolence on his state:

"You look," quoth he, "as if you had had your rest

Broke in upon by the Black Friar of late."

"What Friar?" said Juan; and he did his best

To put the question with an air sedate,

Or careless; but the effort was not valid

To hinder him from growing still more pallid.

XXXVI.

"Oh! have you never heard of the Black Friar?

The Spirit of these walls?"—"In truth not I."

"Why Fame—but Fame you know's sometimes a liar—

Tells an odd story, of which by and by:

Whether with time the Spectre has grown shyer,

Or that our Sires had a more gifted eye

For such sights, though the tale is half believed,

The Friar of late has not been oft perceived.

XXXVII.

"The last time was——"—"I pray," said Adeline—

(Who watched the changes of Don Juan's brow,

And from its context thought she could divine

Connections stronger than he chose to avow

With this same legend)—"if you but design

To jest, you'll choose some other theme just now,

Because the present tale has oft been told,

And is not much improved by growing old."

XXXVIII.

"Jest!" quoth Milor; "why, Adeline, you know

That we ourselves—'twas in the honey moon

Saw——"—"Well, no matter, 'twas so long ago;

But, come, I'll set your story to a tune."

Graceful as Dian when she draws her bow,

She seized her harp, whose strings were kindled soon

As touched, and plaintively began to play

The air of "'Twas a Friar of Orders Gray."[NZ]

XXXIX.

"But add the words," cried Henry, "which you made;

For Adeline is half a poetess,"

Turning round to the rest, he smiling said.

Of course the others could not but express

In courtesy their wish to see displayed

By one three talents, for there were no less—

The voice, the words, the harper's skill, at once,

Could hardly be united by a dunce.

XL.

After some fascinating hesitation,—

The charming of these charmers, who seem bound,

I can't tell why, to this dissimulation,—

Fair Adeline, with eyes fixed on the ground

At first, then kindling into animation,

Added her sweet voice to the lyric sound,

And sang with much simplicity,—a merit

Not the less precious, that we seldom hear it.

1.

Beware! beware! of the Black Friar,

Who sitteth by Norman stone,

For he mutters his prayer in the midnight air,

And his mass of the days that are gone.

When the Lord of the Hill, Amundeville,

Made Norman Church his prey,

And expelled the friars, one friar still

Would not be driven away.

2.

Though he came in his might, with King Henry's right,

To turn church lands to lay,

With sword in hand, and torch to light

Their walls, if they said nay;

A monk remained, unchased, unchained,

And he did not seem formed of clay,

For he's seen in the porch, and he's seen in the church,

Though he is not seen by day.

3.

And whether for good, or whether for ill,

It is not mine to say;

But still with the house of Amundeville

He abideth night and day.

By the marriage-bed of their lords, 'tis said,

He flits on the bridal eve;

And 'tis held as faith, to their bed of Death[OA]

He comes—but not to grieve.

4.

When an heir is born, he's heard to mourn,

And when aught is to befall

That ancient line, in the pale moonshine

He walks from hall to hall.

His form you may trace, but not his face,

'Tis shadowed by his cowl;

But his eyes may be seen from the folds between,

And they seem of a parted soul.

5.

But beware! beware! of the Black Friar,

He still retains his sway,

For he is yet the Church's heir,

Whoever may be the lay.

Amundeville is Lord by day,

But the monk is Lord by night;

Nor wine nor wassail could raise a vassal

To question that Friar's right.

6.

Say nought to him as he walks the Hall,

And he'll say nought to you;

He sweeps along in his dusky pall,

As o'er the grass the dew.

Then grammercy! for the Black Friar;

Heaven sain him! fair or foul,—

And whatsoe'er may be his prayer,

Let ours be for his soul.

XLI.

The lady's voice ceased, and the thrilling wires

Died from the touch that kindled them to sound;

And the pause followed, which when song expires

Pervades a moment those who listen round;

And then of course the circle much admires,

Nor less applauds, as in politeness bound,

The tones, the feeling, and the execution,

To the performer's diffident confusion.

XLII.

Fair Adeline, though in a careless way,

As if she rated such accomplishment

As the mere pastime of an idle day,

Pursued an instant for her own content,

Would now and then as 'twere without display,

Yet with display in fact, at times relent

To such performances with haughty smile,

To show she could, if it were worth her while.

XLIII.

Now this (but we will whisper it aside)

Was—pardon the pedantic illustration—

Trampling on Plato's pride with greater pride,

As did the Cynic on some like occasion;

Deeming the sage would be much mortified,

Or thrown into a philosophic passion,

For a spoilt carpet—but the "Attic Bee"

Was much consoled by his own repartee.[783]

XLIV.

Thus Adeline would throw into the shade

(By doing easily, whene'er she chose,

What dilettanti do with vast parade)

Their sort of half profession; for it grows

To something like this when too oft displayed;

And that it is so, everybody knows,

Who have heard Miss That or This, or Lady T'other,

Show off—to please their company or mother.

XLV.

Oh! the long evenings of duets and trios!

The admirations and the speculations;

The "Mamma Mia's!" and the "Amor Mio's!"

The "Tanti palpiti's" on such occasions:

The "Lasciami's," and quavering "Addio's,"

Amongst our own most musical of nations!

With "Tu mi chamas's" from Portingale,[784]

To soothe our ears, lest Italy should fail.[785]

XLVI.

In Babylon's bravuras—as the Home-

Heart-Ballads of Green Erin or Grey Highlands,

That bring Lochaber back to eyes that roam

O'er far Atlantic continents or islands,

The calentures[786] of music which o'ercome

All mountaineers with dreams that they are nigh lands,

No more to be beheld but in such visions—

Was Adeline well versed, as compositions.

XLVII.

She also had a twilight tinge of "Blue,"

Could write rhymes, and compose more than she wrote,

Made epigrams occasionally too

Upon her friends, as everybody ought.

But still from that sublimer azure hue,[787]

So much the present dye, she was remote;

Was weak enough to deem Pope a great poet,

And what was worse, was not ashamed to show it.

XLVIII.

Aurora—since we are touching upon taste,

Which now-a-days is the thermometer

By whose degrees all characters are classed—

Was more Shakespearian, if I do not err.

The worlds beyond this World's perplexing waste

Had more of her existence, for in her

There was a depth of feeling to embrace

Thoughts, boundless, deep, but silent too as Space.

XLIX.

Not so her gracious, graceful, graceless Grace,

The full-grown Hebe of Fitz-Fulke, whose mind,

If she had any, was upon her face,

And that was of a fascinating kind.

A little turn for mischief you might trace

Also thereon,—but that's not much; we find

Few females without some such gentle leaven,

For fear we should suppose us quite in Heaven.

L.

I have not heard she was at all poetic,

Though once she was seen reading the Bath Guide,[788]

And Hayley's Triumphs,[789] which she deemed pathetic,

Because she said her temper had been tried

So much, the bard had really been prophetic

Of what she had gone through with—since a bride.

But of all verse, what most ensured her praise

Were sonnets to herself, or bouts rimés.

LI.

'Twere difficult to say what was the object

Of Adeline, in bringing this same lay

To bear on what appeared to her the subject

Of Juan's nervous feelings on that day.

Perhaps she merely had the simple project

To laugh him out of his supposed dismay;

Perhaps she might wish to confirm him in it,

Though why I cannot say—at least this minute.

LII.

But so far the immediate effect

Was to restore him to his self-propriety,

A thing quite necessary to the elect,

Who wish to take the tone of their society:

In which you cannot be too circumspect,

Whether the mode be persiflage or piety,

But wear the newest mantle of hypocrisy,

On pain of much displeasing the gynocracy.[790]

LIII.

And therefore Juan now began to rally

His spirits, and without more explanation

To jest upon such themes in many a sally.

Her Grace, too, also seized the same occasion,

With various similar remarks to tally,

But wished for a still more detailed narration

Of this same mystic friar's curious doings,

About the present family's deaths and wooings.

LIV.

Of these few could say more than has been said;

They passed as such things do, for superstition

With some, while others, who had more in dread

The theme, half credited the strange tradition;

And much was talked on all sides on that head:

But Juan, when cross-questioned on the vision,

Which some supposed (though he had not avowed it)

Had stirred him, answered in a way to cloud it.

LV.

And then, the mid-day having worn to one,

The company prepared to separate;

Some to their several pastimes, or to none,

Some wondering 'twas so early, some so late.

There was a goodly match too, to be run

Between some greyhounds on my Lord's estate,

And a young race-horse of old pedigree,

Matched for the spring, whom several went to see.

LVI.

There was a picture-dealer who had brought

A special Titian, warranted original,

So precious that it was not to be bought,

Though Princes the possessor were besieging all—

The King himself had cheapened it, but thought

The civil list he deigns to accept (obliging all

His subjects by his gracious acceptation)—

Too scanty, in these times of low taxation.

LVII.

But as Lord Henry was a connoisseur,—

The friend of Artists, if not Arts,—the owner,

With motives the most classical and pure,

So that he would have been the very donor,

Rather than seller, had his wants been fewer,

So much he deemed his patronage an honour,

Had brought the capo d'opera, not for sale,

But for his judgment—never known to fail.

LVIII.

There was a modern Goth, I mean a Gothic

Bricklayer of Babel, called an architect,[OB]

Brought to survey these grey walls which, though so thick,

Might have from Time acquired some slight defect;

Who, after rummaging the Abbey through thick

And thin, produced a plan whereby to erect

New buildings of correctest conformation,

And throw down old—which he called restoration.[791]

LIX.

The cost would be a trifle—an "old song,"

Set to some thousands ('tis the usual burden

Of that same tune, when people hum it long)—

The price would speedily repay its worth in

An edifice no less sublime than strong,

By which Lord Henry's good taste would go forth in

Its glory, through all ages shining sunny,

For Gothic daring shown in English money.[792]

LX.

There were two lawyers busy on a mortgage

Lord Henry wished to raise for a new purchase;

Also a lawsuit upon tenures burgage,[793]

And one on tithes, which sure as Discord's torches,

Kindling Religion till she throws down her gage,

"Untying" squires "to fight against the churches;"[794]

There was a prize ox, a prize pig, and ploughman,

For Henry was a sort of Sabine showman.

LXI.

There were two poachers caught in a steel trap,

Ready for gaol, their place of convalescence;

There was a country girl in a close cap

And scarlet cloak (I hate the sight to see, since—

Since—since—in youth, I had the sad mishap—

But luckily I have paid few parish fees since):[795]

That scarlet cloak, alas! unclosed with rigour,

Presents the problem of a double figure.

LXII.

A reel within a bottle is a mystery,

One can't tell how it e'er got in or out;

Therefore the present piece of natural history

I leave to those who are fond of solving doubt;

And merely state, though not for the Consistory,

Lord Henry was a Justice, and that Scout

The constable, beneath a warrant's banner,

Had bagged this poacher upon Nature's manor.

LXIII.

Now Justices of Peace must judge all pieces

Of mischief of all kinds, and keep the game

And morals of the country from caprices

Of those who have not a licence for the same;

And of all things, excepting tithes and leases,

Perhaps these are most difficult to tame:

Preserving partridges and pretty wenches

Are puzzles to the most precautious benches.

LXIV.

The present culprit was extremely pale,

Pale as if painted so; her cheek being red

By nature, as in higher dames less hale

'Tis white, at least when they just rise from bed.

Perhaps she was ashamed of seeming frail,

Poor soul! for she was country born and bred,

And knew no better in her immorality

Than to wax white—for blushes are for quality.

LXV.

Her black, bright, downcast, yet espiègle eye,

Had gathered a large tear into its corner,

Which the poor thing at times essayed to dry,

For she was not a sentimental mourner

Parading all her sensibility,

Nor insolent enough to scorn the scorner,

But stood in trembling, patient tribulation,

To be called up for her examination.

LXVI.

Of course these groups were scattered here and there,

Not nigh the gay saloon of ladies gent.[796]

The lawyers in the study; and in air

The prize pig, ploughman, poachers: the men sent

From town, viz. architect and dealer, were

Both busy (as a General in his tent

Writing despatches) in their several stations,

Exulting in their brilliant lucubrations.

LXVII.

But this poor girl was left in the great hall,

While Scout, the parish guardian of the frail,

Discussed (he hated beer yclept the "small")

A mighty mug of moral double ale.

She waited until Justice could recall

Its kind attentions to their proper pale,

To name a thing in nomenclature rather[OC]

Perplexing for most virgins—a child's father.

LXVIII.

You see here was enough of occupation

For the Lord Henry, linked with dogs and horses.

There was much bustle too, and preparation

Below stairs on the score of second courses;

Because, as suits their rank and situation,

Those who in counties have great land resources

Have "public days," when all men may carouse,

Though not exactly what's called "open house."

LXIX.

But once a week or fortnight, uninvited

(Thus we translate a general invitation)

All country gentlemen, esquired or knighted,

May drop in without cards, and take their station

At the full board, and sit alike delighted

With fashionable wines and conversation;

And, as the isthmus of the grand connection,

Talk o'er themselves the past and next election.

LXX.

Lord Henry was a great electioneerer,

Burrowing for boroughs like a rat or rabbit.

But county contests cost him rather dearer,

Because the neighbouring Scotch Earl of Giftgabbit

Had English influence, in the self-same sphere here;

His son, the Honourable Dick Dicedrabbit,

Was member for the "other interest" (meaning

The same self-interest, with a different leaning).

LXXI.

Courteous and cautious therefore in his county,

He was all things to all men, and dispensed

To some civility, to others bounty,

And promises to all—which last commenced

To gather to a somewhat large amount, he

Not calculating how much they condensed;

But what with keeping some, and breaking others,

His word had the same value as another's.

LXXII.

A friend to Freedom and freeholders—yet

No less a friend to Government—he held,

That he exactly the just medium hit

Twixt Place and Patriotism—albeit compelled,

Such was his Sovereign's pleasure, (though unfit,

He added modestly, when rebels railed,)

To hold some sinecures he wished abolished,

But that with them all Law would be demolished.

LXXIII.

He was "free to confess"—(whence comes this phrase?

Is 't English? No—'tis only parliamentary)

That Innovation's spirit now-a-days

Had made more progress than for the last century.

He would not tread a factious path to praise,

Though for the public weal disposed to venture high;

As for his place, he could but say this of it,

That the fatigue was greater than the profit.

LXXIV.

Heaven, and his friends, knew that a private life

Had ever been his sole and whole ambition;

But could he quit his King in times of strife,

Which threatened the whole country with perdition?

When demagogues would with a butcher's knife

Cut through and through (oh! damnable incision!)

The Gordian or the Geordi-an knot, whose strings

Have tied together Commons, Lords, and Kings.

LXXV.

Sooner "come Place into the Civil List

And champion him to the utmost[797]—" he would keep it,

Till duly disappointed or dismissed:

Profit he cared not for, let others reap it;

But should the day come when Place ceased to exist,

The country would have far more cause to weep it:

For how could it go on? Explain who can!

He gloried in the name of Englishman.

LXXVI.

He was as independent—aye, much more—

Than those who were not paid for independence,

As common soldiers, or a common——shore,

Have in their several arts or parts ascendance

O'er the irregulars in lust or gore,

Who do not give professional attendance.

Thus on the mob all statesmen are as eager

To prove their pride, as footmen to a beggar.

LXXVII.

All this (save the last stanza) Henry said,

And thought. I say no more—I've said too much;

For all of us have either heard or read—

Off—or upon the hustings—some slight such

Hints from the independent heart or head

Of the official candidate. I'll touch

No more on this—the dinner-bell hath rung,

And grace is said; the grace I should have sung—

LXXVIII.

But I'm too late, and therefore must make play.

'Twas a great banquet, such as Albion old

Was wont to boast—as if a glutton's tray

Were something very glorious to behold.

But 'twas a public feast and public day,—

Quite full—right dull—guests hot, and dishes cold,—

Great plenty, much formality, small cheer,—

And everybody out of their own sphere.

LXXIX.

The squires familiarly formal, and

My Lords and Ladies proudly condescending;

The very servants puzzling how to hand

Their plates—without it might be too much bending

From their high places by the sideboard's stand—

Yet, like their masters, fearful of offending;

For any deviation from the graces

Might cost both man and master too—their places.

LXXX.

There were some hunters bold, and coursers keen,

Whose hounds ne'er erred, nor greyhounds deigned to lurch;

Some deadly shots too, Septembrizers,[798] seen

Earliest to rise, and last to quit the search

Of the poor partridge through his stubble screen.

There were some massy members of the church,

Takers of tithes, and makers of good matches,

And several who sung fewer psalms than catches.

LXXXI.

There were some country wags too—and, alas!

Some exiles from the Town, who had been driven

To gaze, instead of pavement, upon grass,

And rise at nine in lieu of long eleven.

And lo! upon that day it came to pass,

I sate next that o'erwhelming son of Heaven,

The very powerful parson, Peter Pith,[799]

The loudest wit I e'er was deafened with.

LXXXII.

I knew him in his livelier London days,

A brilliant diner-out, though but a curate,

And not a joke he cut but earned its praise,

Until Preferment, coming at a sure rate,

(O Providence! how wondrous are thy ways!

Who would suppose thy gifts sometimes obdurate?)

Gave him, to lay the Devil who looks o'er Lincoln,[800]

A fat fen vicarage, and nought to think on.

LXXXIII.

His jokes were sermons, and his sermons jokes;

But both were thrown away amongst the fens;

For Wit hath no great friend in aguish folks.[OD]

No longer ready ears and short-hand pens

Imbibed the gay bon-mot, or happy hoax:[OE]

The poor priest was reduced to common sense,

Or to coarse efforts very loud and long,

To hammer a hoarse laugh from the thick throng.[OF]

LXXXIV.

There is a difference, says the song, "between

A beggar and a Queen,"[801] or was (of late

The latter worse used of the two we've seen—

But we 'll say nothing of affairs of state);

A difference "'twixt a Bishop and a Dean,"

A difference between crockery ware and plate,

As between English beef and Spartan broth—

And yet great heroes have been bred by both.

LXXXV.

But of all Nature's discrepancies, none

Upon the whole is greater than the difference

Beheld between the Country and the Town,

Of which the latter merits every preference

From those who have few resources of their own.

And only think, or act, or feel, with reference

To some small plan of interest or ambition—

Both which are limited to no condition.

LXXXVI.

But En avant! The light loves languish o'er

Long banquets and too many guests, although

A slight repast makes people love much more,

Bacchus and Ceres being, as we know,

Even from our grammar upwards, friends of yore

With vivifying Venus,[802] who doth owe

To these the invention of champagne and truffles:

Temperance delights her, but long fasting ruffles.

LXXXVII.

Dully passed o'er the dinner of the day;

And Juan took his place, he knew not where,

Confused, in the confusion, and distrait,

And sitting as if nailed upon his chair:

Though knives and forks clanked round as in a fray,

He seemed unconscious of all passing there,

Till some one, with a groan, expressed a wish

(Unheeded twice) to have a fin of fish.

LXXXVIII.

On which, at the third asking of the banns,

He started; and perceiving smiles around

Broadening to grins, he coloured more than once,

And hastily—as nothing can confound

A wise man more than laughter from a dunce—

Inflicted on the dish a deadly wound,

And with such hurry, that, ere he could curb it,

He had paid his neighbour's prayer with half a turbot.

LXXXIX.

This was no bad mistake, as it occurred,

The supplicator being an amateur;

But others, who were left with scarce a third,

Were angry—as they well might, to be sure,

They wondered how a young man so absurd

Lord Henry at his table should endure;

And this, and his not knowing how much oats

Had fallen last market, cost his host three votes.

XC.

They little knew, or might have sympathized,

That he the night before had seen a ghost,

A prologue which but slightly harmonized

With the substantial company engrossed

By matter, and so much materialised,

That one scarce knew at what to marvel most

Of two things—how (the question rather odd is)

Such bodies could have souls, or souls such bodies!

XCI.

But what confused him more than smile or stare

From all the 'squires and 'squiresses around,

Who wondered at the abstraction of his air,

Especially as he had been renowned

For some vivacity among the fair,

Even in the country circle's narrow bound—

(For little things upon my Lord's estate

Were good small talk for others still less great)—

XCII.

Was, that he caught Aurora's eye on his,

And something like a smile upon her cheek.

Now this he really rather took amiss;

In those who rarely smile, their smile bespeaks

A strong external motive; and in this

Smile of Aurora's there was nought to pique,

Or Hope, or Love—with any of the wiles

Which some pretend to trace in ladies' smiles.

XCIII.

'Twas a mere quiet smile of contemplation,

Indicative of some surprise and pity;

And Juan grew carnation with vexation,

Which was not very wise, and still less witty,

Since he had gained at least her observation,

A most important outwork of the city—

As Juan should have known, had not his senses

By last night's Ghost been driven from their defences.

XCIV.

But what was bad, she did not blush in turn,

Nor seem embarrassed—quite the contrary;

Her aspect was as usual, still—not stern—

And she withdrew, but cast not down, her eye,

Yet grew a little pale—with what? concern?

I know not; but her colour ne'er was high—

Though sometimes faintly flushed—and always clear,

As deep seas in a sunny atmosphere.

XCV.

But Adeline was occupied by fame

This day; and watching, witching, condescending

To the consumers of fish, fowl, and game,

And dignity with courtesy so blending,

As all must blend whose part it is to aim

(Especially as the sixth year is ending)

At their lord's, son's, or similar connection's

Safe conduct through the rocks of re-elections.

XCVI.

Though this was most expedient on the whole

And usual—Juan, when he cast a glance

On Adeline while playing her grand rôle,

Which she went through as though it were a dance,

Betraying only now and then her soul

By a look scarce perceptibly askance

(Of weariness or scorn), began to feel

Some doubt how much of Adeline was real;

XCVII.

So well she acted all and every part

By turns—with that vivacious versatility,

Which many people take for want of heart.

They err—'tis merely what is called mobility,[803]

A thing of temperament and not of art,

Though seeming so, from its supposed facility;

And false—though true; for, surely, they're sincerest

Who are strongly acted on by what is nearest.

XCVIII.

This makes your actors, artists, and romancers,

Heroes sometimes, though seldom—sages never:

But speakers, bards, diplomatists, and dancers,

Little that's great, but much of what is clever;

Most orators, but very few financiers,

Though all Exchequer Chancellors endeavour,

Of late years, to dispense with Cocker's rigours,[804]

And grow quite figurative with their figures.

XCIX.

The poets of Arithmetic are they

Who, though they prove not two and two to be

Five, as they might do in a modest way,

Have plainly made it out that four are three,

Judging by what they take, and what they pay:

The Sinking Fund's unfathomable sea,

That most unliquidating liquid, leaves

The debt unsunk, yet sinks all it receives.

C.

While Adeline dispensed her airs and graces,

The fair Fitz-Fulke seemed very much at ease;

Though too well bred to quiz men to their faces,

Her laughing blue eyes with a glance could seize

The ridicules of people in all places—

That honey of your fashionable bees—

And store it up for mischievous enjoyment;

And this at present was her kind employment.

CI.

However, the day closed, as days must close;

The evening also waned—and coffee came.

Each carriage was announced, and ladies rose,

And curtsying off, as curtsies country dame,

Retired: with most unfashionable bows

Their docile Esquires also did the same,

Delighted with their dinner and their Host,

But with the Lady Adeline the most.

CII.

Some praised her beauty: others her great grace;

The warmth of her politeness, whose sincerity

Was obvious in each feature of her face,

Whose traits were radiant with the rays of verity.

Yes; she was truly worthy her high place!

No one could envy her deserved prosperity.

And then her dress—what beautiful simplicity

Draperied her form with curious felicity![805]

CIII.

Meanwhile sweet Adeline deserved their praises,

By an impartial indemnification

For all her past exertion and soft phrases,

In a most edifying conversation,

Which turned upon their late guests' miens and faces,

Their families, even to the last relation;

Their hideous wives, their horrid selves and dresses,

And truculent distortion of their tresses.

CIV.

True, she said little—'twas the rest that broke

Forth into universal epigram;

But then 'twas to the purpose what she spoke:

Like Addison's "faint praise,"[806] so wont to damn,

Her own but served to set off every joke,

As music chimes in with a melodrame.

How sweet the task to shield an absent friend!

I ask but this of mine, to——not defend.

CV.

There were but two exceptions to this keen

Skirmish of wits o'er the departed; one,

Aurora, with her pure and placid mien;

And Juan, too, in general behind none

In gay remark on what he had heard or seen,

Sate silent now, his usual spirits gone:

In vain he heard the others rail or rally,

He would not join them in a single sally.

CVI.

'Tis true he saw Aurora look as though

She approved his silence; she perhaps mistook

Its motive for that charity we owe

But seldom pay the absent, nor would look

Farther—it might or it might not be so.

But Juan, sitting silent in his nook,

Observing little in his reverie,

Yet saw this much, which he was glad to see.

CVII.

The Ghost at least had done him this much good,

In making him as silent as a ghost,

If in the circumstances which ensued

He gained esteem where it was worth the most;

And, certainly, Aurora had renewed

In him some feelings he had lately lost,

Or hardened; feelings which, perhaps ideal,

Are so divine, that I must deem them real:—

CVIII.

The love of higher things and better days;

The unbounded hope, and heavenly ignorance

Of what is called the World, and the World's ways;

The moments when we gather from a glance

More joy than from all future pride or praise,

Which kindle manhood, but can ne'er entrance

The Heart in an existence of its own,

Of which another's bosom is the zone.

CIX.

Who would not sigh Αἴ αἴ τὰν Κυθέρειαν[807]

That hath a memory, or that had a heart?

Alas! her star must fade like that of Dian:

Ray fades on ray, as years on years depart.

Anacreon only had the soul to tie an

Unwithering myrtle round the unblunted dart

Of Eros: but though thou hast played us many tricks,

Still we respect thee, "Alma Venus Genetrix!"[808]

CX.

And full of sentiments, sublime as billows

Heaving between this World and Worlds beyond,

Don Juan, when the midnight hour of pillows

Arrived, retired to his; but to despond

Rather than rest. Instead of poppies, willows

Waved o'er his couch; he meditated, fond

Of those sweet bitter thoughts which banish sleep,

And make the worldling sneer, the youngling weep.

CXI.

The night was as before: he was undrest,

Saving his night-gown, which is an undress;

Completely sans culotte, and without vest;

In short, he hardly could be clothed with less:

But apprehensive of his spectral guest,

He sate with feelings awkward to express

(By those who have not had such visitations),

Expectant of the Ghost's fresh operations.

CXII.

And not in vain he listened;—Hush! what's that?

I see—I see—Ah, no!—'t is not—yet 't is—

Ye powers! it is the—the—the—Pooh! the cat!

The Devil may take that stealthy pace of his!

So like a spiritual pit-a-pat,

Or tiptoe of an amatory Miss,

Gliding the first time to a rendezvous,

And dreading the chaste echoes of her shoe.

CXIII.

Again—what is 't? The wind? No, no,—this time

It is the sable Friar as before,

With awful footsteps regular as rhyme,

Or (as rhymes may be in these days) much more.

Again through shadows of the night sublime,

When deep sleep fell on men,[809] and the World wore

The starry darkness round her like a girdle

Spangled with gems—the Monk made his blood curdle.

CXIV.

A noise like to wet fingers drawn on glass,[810]

Which sets the teeth on edge; and a slight clatter,

Like showers which on the midnight gusts will pass,

Sounding like very supernatural water,

Came over Juan's ear, which throbbed, alas!

For Immaterialism's a serious matter;

So that even those whose faith is the most great

In Souls immortal, shun them tête-à-tête.

CXV.

Were his eyes open?—Yes! and his mouth too.

Surprise has this effect—to make one dumb,

Yet leave the gate which Eloquence slips through

As wide as if a long speech were to come.

Nigh and more nigh the awful echoes drew,

Tremendous to a mortal tympanum:

His eyes were open, and (as was before

Stated) his mouth. What opened next?—the door.

CXVI.

It opened with a most infernal creak,

Like that of Hell. "Lasciate ogni speranza,

Voi, ch' entrate!"[811] The hinge seemed to speak,

Dreadful as Dante's rima, or this stanza;

Or—but all words upon such themes are weak:

A single shade's sufficient to entrance a

Hero—for what is Substance to a Spirit?

Or how is 't Matter trembles to come near it?[OG]

CXVII.

The door flew wide, not swiftly,—but, as fly

The sea-gulls, with a steady, sober flight—

And then swung back; nor close—but stood awry,

Half letting in long shadows on the light,

Which still in Juan's candlesticks burned high,

For he had two, both tolerably bright,

And in the doorway, darkening darkness, stood

The sable Friar in his solemn hood.

CXVIII.

Don Juan shook, as erst he had been shaken

The night before; but being sick of shaking,

He first inclined to think he had been mistaken;

And then to be ashamed of such mistaking;

His own internal ghost began to awaken

Within him, and to quell his corporal quaking—

Hinting that Soul and Body on the whole

Were odds against a disembodied Soul.

CXIX.

And then his dread grew wrath, and his wrath fierce,

And he arose, advanced—the Shade retreated;

But Juan, eager now the truth to pierce,

Followed, his veins no longer cold, but heated,

Resolved to thrust the mystery carte and tierce,

At whatsoever risk of being defeated:

The Ghost stopped, menaced, then retired, until

He reached the ancient wall, then stood stone still.

CXX.

Juan put forth one arm—Eternal powers!

It touched no soul, nor body, but the wall,

On which the moonbeams fell in silvery showers,

Chequered with all the tracery of the Hall;

He shuddered, as no doubt the bravest cowers

When he can't tell what 'tis that doth appal.

How odd, a single hobgoblin's nonentity

Should cause more fear than a whole host's identity!

CXXI.

But still the Shade remained: the blue eyes glared,

And rather variably for stony death;

Yet one thing rather good the grave had spared,

The Ghost had a remarkably sweet breath:

A straggling curl showed he had been fair-haired;

A red lip, with two rows of pearls beneath,

Gleamed forth, as through the casement's ivy shroud

The Moon peeped, just escaped from a grey cloud.

CXXII.

And Juan, puzzled, but still curious, thrust

His other arm forth—Wonder upon wonder!

It pressed upon a hard but glowing bust,

Which beat as if there was a warm heart under.

He found, as people on most trials must,

That he had made at first a silly blunder,

And that in his confusion he had caught

Only the wall, instead of what he sought.

CXXIII.

The Ghost, if Ghost it were, seemed a sweet soul

As ever lurked beneath a holy hood:

A dimpled chin,[OH] a neck of ivory, stole

Forth into something much like flesh and blood;

Back fell the sable frock and dreary cowl,

And they revealed—alas! that e'er they should!

In full, voluptuous, but not o'ergrown bulk,

The phantom of her frolic Grace—Fitz-Fulke![812]

FOOTNOTES:

[768] {572}March 29, 1823.

[769] [Herodotus, Hist., i. 136.]

[770] [Hamlet, act ii. sc. 2, line 103.]

[771] {573}[The story is told of St. Thomas Aquinas, that he wrote a work De Omnibus Rebus, which was followed by a second treatise, De Quibusdam Aliis.]

[772] [Not St. Augustine, but Tertullian. See his treatise, De Carne Christi, cap. V. c. (Opera, 1744, p. 310): "Crucifixus est Dei filius: non pudet, quia pudendum est: et mortuus est Dei filius: prorsus credibile est, quia ineptum est: et sepultus resurrexit: certum est quia impossibile est."]

[773] {574}["That the dead are seen no more," said Imlac, "I will not undertake to maintain, against the concurrent and unvaried testimony of all ages, and of all nations. There is no people, rude or unlearned, among whom apparitions of the dead are not related and believed. This opinion, which perhaps prevails as far as human nature is diffused, could become universal only by its truth; those that never heard of one another would not have agreed in a tale which nothing but experience can make credible. That it is doubted by single cavillers, can very little weaken the general evidence; and some, who deny it with their tongues, confess it with their fears."—Rasselas, chap. xxx., Works, ed. 1806, iii. 372, 373.]

[774] {575}The composition of the old Tyrian purple, whether from a shell-fish, or from cochineal, or from kermes, is still an article of dispute; and even its colour—some say purple, others scarlet: I say nothing.

[Kermes is cochineal, the Greek κόκκινον. The shell-fish (murex) is the Purpura patula. Both substances were used as dyes.]

[775] [See Ovid, Heroid, Epist. ix. line 161.]

[776] [Titus used to promise to "bear in mind," "to keep on his list," the petitions of all his supplicants, and once, at dinner-time, his conscience smote him, that he had let a day go by without a single grant, or pardon, or promotion. Hence his confession. "Amici, diem perdidi!" Vide Suetonius, De XII. Cæs., "Titus," lib. viii. cap. 8.]

[777] [Tuism is not in Johnson's Dictionary. Coleridge has a note dated 1800 (Literary Remains, i. 292), on "egotizing in tuism" but it was not included in Southey's Omniana of 1812, and must have been unknown to Byron.]

[778] {576}[Sc. toilette, a Gallicism.]

[779] [Byron loved to make fact and fancy walk together, but, here, his memory played him false, or his art kept him true. The Black Friar walked and walks in the Guests' Refectory (or Banqueting Hall, or "Gallery" of this stanza), which adjoins the Prior's Parlour, but the room where Byron slept (in a four-post bed—a coronet, at each corner, atop) is on the floor above the Prior's Parlour, and can only be approached by a spiral staircase. Both rooms look west, and command a view of the "lake's billow" and the "cascade." Moreover, the Guests' Refectory was never hung with "old pictures." It would seem that Don Juan (perhaps Byron on an emergency) slept in the Prior's Parlour, and that in the visionary Newstead the pictures forsook the Grand Drawing-Room for the Hall. Hence the scene! El Libertado steps out of the Gothic Chamber "forth" into the "gallery," and lo! "a monk in cowl and beads." But, Quien sabe? The Psalmist's caution with regard to princes is not inapplicable to poets.]

[780] {577}[Compare Mariner's description of the cave in Hoonga Island (Poetical Works, 1901, v. 629, note 1).]

[781] {578}["The place," wrote Byron to Moore, August 13, 1814, "is worth seeing as a ruin, and I can assure you there was some fun there, even in my time; but that is past. The ghosts, however, and the Gothics, and the waters, and the desolation, make it very lively still." "It was," comments Moore (Life, p. 262, note 1), "if I mistake not, during his recent visit to Newstead, that he himself actually fancied he saw the ghost of the Black Friar, which was supposed to have haunted the Abbey from the time of the dissolution of the monasteries, and which he thus describes from the recollection, perhaps, of his own fantasy, in Don Juan.... It is said that the Newstead ghost appeared, also, to Lord Byron's cousin, Miss Fanny Parkins, and that she made a sketch of him from memory." The legend of the Black Friar may, it is believed at Newstead (et vide post, "Song," stanza ii. line 5, p. 583), be traced to the alarm and suspicion of the country-folk, who, on visiting the Abbey, would now and then catch sight of an aged lay-brother, or monkish domestic, who had been retained in the service of the Byrons long after the Canons had been "turned adrift." He would naturally keep out of sight of a generation who knew not monks, and, when surprised in the cloisters or ruins of the church, would glide back to his own quarters in the dormitories.]

[782]

["Shew his eyes, and grieve his heart;

Come like shadows, so depart."

Macbeth, act iv. sc. 1, lines 110, 111.]

[NZ] {582}

With that she rose as graceful as a Roe

Slips from the mountain in the month of June,

And opening her Piano 'gan to play

Forthwith—"It was a Friar of Orders Gray."—[MS. erased.]

[OA] {584}By their bed of death he receives their [breath].—[MS. erased.]

[783] {585}I think that it was a carpet on which Diogenes trod, with—"Thus I trample on the pride of Plato!"—"With greater pride," as the other replied. But as carpets are meant to be trodden upon, my memory probably misgives me, and it might be a robe, or tapestry, or a table-cloth, or some other expensive and uncynical piece of furniture.

[It was Plato's couch or lounge which Diogenes stamped upon. "So much for Plato's pride!" "And how much for yours, Diogenes?" "Calco Platonis fastum!" "Ast fastu alio?" (Vide Diogenis Laertii De Vita et Sententiis, lib. vi. ed. 1595, p. 321.)

For "Attic Bee," vide Cic. I. De Div., xxxvi. § 78, "At Platoni cum in cunis parvulo dormienti apes in labellis consedissent, responsum est, singulari illum suavitate orationis fore."]

[784] {586}[For two translations of this Portuguese song, see Poetical Works, 1900, iii. 71.]

[785] I remember that the mayoress of a provincial town, somewhat surfeited with a similar display from foreign parts, did rather indecorously break through the applauses of an intelligent audience—intelligent, I mean, as to music—for the words, besides being in recondite languages (it was some years before the peace, ere all the world had travelled, and while I was a collegian), were sorely disguised by the performers:—this mayoress, I say, broke out with, "Rot your Italianos! for my part, I loves a simple ballat!" Rossini will go a good way to bring most people to the same opinion some day. Who would imagine that he was to be the successor of Mozart? However, I state this with diffidence, as a liege and loyal admirer of Italian music in general, and of much of Rossini's; but we may say, as the connoisseur did of painting in The Vicar of Wakefield, that "the picture would be better painted if the painter had taken more pains."

[A little while, and Rossini is being lauded at the expense of a degenerate modern rival. Compare Browning's Bishop Blougram's Apology. "Where sits Rossini patient in his stall."—Poetical Works, ed. 1868, v. 276.]

[786] [Compare The Two Foscari, act iii. sc. 1, line 172, Poetical Works, 1901, v. 159, note 1.]

[787] {587}[Of Lady Beaumont, who was "weak enough" to admire Wordsworth, see The Blues, Ecl. II. line 47, sq., Poetical Works, 1901, iv. 582.]

[788] [Christopher Anstey (1724-1802) published his New Bath Guide in 1766.]

[789] [Compare English Bards, etc., lines 309-318, Poetical Works, 1898, i. 321, note 1.]

[790] {588}[For "Gynocracy," vide ante, p. 473, note 1.]

[OB] {589}Thrower down of buildings——.—[MS. erased.]

[791] [Byron had, no doubt, inspected the plan of Colonel Wildman's elaborate restoration of the Abbey, which was carried out at a cost of one hundred thousand pounds (see stanza lix. lines 1, 2). The kitchen and domestic offices, which extended at right angles to the west front of the Abbey (see "Newstead from a Picture by Peter Tilleman, circ. 1720" Letters, 1898, i. (to face p.) 216), were pulled down and rebuilt, the massive Sussex Tower (so named in honour of H.R.H. the Duke of Sussex) was erected at the south-west corner of the Abbey, and the south front was, in part, rebuilt and redecorated. Byron had been ready to "leave everything" with regard to his beloved Newstead to Wildman's "own feelings, present or future" (see his letter, November 18, 1818, Letters, 1900, iv. 270); but when the time came, the necessary and, on the whole, judicious alterations of his successor, must have cost the "banished Lord" many a pang.]

[792] {590}"Ausu Romano, sere Veneto" is the inscription (and well inscribed in this instance) on the sea walls between the Adriatic and Venice. The walls were a republican work of the Venetians; the inscription, I believe, Imperial; and inscribed by Napoleon the First. It is time to continue to him that title—there will be a second by and by, "Spes altera mundi," if he live; let him not defeat it like his father. But in any case, he will be preferable to "Imbéciles." There is a glorious field for him, if he know how to cultivate it.

[Francis Charles Joseph Napoleon, Duke of Reichstadt, died at Vienna, July 22, 1832. But, none the less, Byron's prophecy was fulfilled.]

[793] [Burgage, or tenure in burgage, is where the king or some other person is lord of an ancient borough, in which the tenements are held by a yearly rent certain.]

[794]

["I conjure you, by that which you profess,

(Howe'er you come to know it) answer me:

Though you untie the winds, and let them fight

Against the churches."

Macbeth, act iv. sc. 1, lines 50-53.]

[795] {591}[See the lines "To my Son," Poetical Works, 1898, i. 260, note 1.]

[796] {592}[See Spenser's Faëry Queen, Book I. Canto IX. stanza 6, line 1.]

[OC]

To name what passes for a puzzle rather,

Although there must be such a thing—a father.—[MS. erased.]

[797] {594}

["Rather than so, come, Fate, into the list,

And champion me to the utterance."

Macbeth, act iii. sc. 1, lines 70, 71.]

[798] {595}[For "Septemberers (Septembriseurs)," see Carlyle's French Revolution, 1839, iii. 50.]

[799] {596}["Query, Sydney Smith, author of Peter Plymley's Letters?—Printer's Devil."—Ed. 1833. Byron must have met Sydney Smith (1771-1845) at Holland House. The "fat fen vicarage" (vide infra, stanza lxxxii. line 8) was Foston-le-Clay (Foston, All Saints), near Barton Hill, Yorkshire, which Lord Chancellor Erskine presented to Sydney Smith in 1806. The "living" consisted of "three hundred acres of glebe-land of the stiffest clay," and there was no parsonage house.—See A Memoir of the Rev. Sydney Smith, by Lady Holland, 1855, i. 100-107.]

[800] ["Observe, also, three grotesque figures in the blank arches of the gable which forms the eastern end of St. Hugh's Chapel," and of these, "one is popularly said to represent the 'Devil looking over Lincoln.'"—Handbook to the Cathedrals of England, by R.J. King, Eastern Division, p. 394, note x.

The devil looked over Lincoln because the unexampled height of the central tower of the cathedral excited his envy and alarm; or, as Fuller (Worthies: Lincolnshire) has it, "overlooked this church, when first finished, with a torve and tetrick countenance, as maligning men's costly devotions." So, at least, the vanity of later ages interpreted the saying; but a time was when the devil "looked over" Lincoln to some purpose, for in A.D. 1185 an earthquake clave the Church of Remigius in twain, and in 1235 a great part of the central tower, which had been erected by Bishop Hugh de Wells, fell and injured the rest of the building.]

[OD] {597}For laughter rarely shakes these aguish folks.—[MS, erased.]

[OE] Took down the gay bon-mot——.—[MS. erased.]

[OF] To hammer half a laugh——.—[MS. erased.]

[801]

["There's a difference to be seen between a beggar and a Queen;

And I 'll tell you the reason why;

A Queen does not swagger, nor get drunk like a beggar,

Nor be half so merry as I," etc.

"There's a difference to be seen,'twixt a Bishop and a Dean,

And I'll tell you the reason why;

A Dean can not dish up a dinner like a Bishop,

And that's the reason why!"]

[802] {598}["Sine Cerere et Libero friget Venus." Terentius, Eun., act iv. sc. 5, line 6.]

[803] {601}In French "mobilité." I am not sure that mobility is English; but it is expressive of a quality which rather belongs to other climates, though it is sometimes seen to a great extent in our own. It may be defined as an excessive susceptibility of immediate impressions—at the same time without losing the past: and is, though sometimes apparently useful to the possessor, a most painful and unhappy attribute.

["That he was fully aware not only of the abundance of this quality in his own nature, but of the danger in which it placed consistency and singleness of character, did not require the note on this passage to assure us. The consciousness, indeed, of his own natural tendency to yield thus to every chance impression, and change with every passing impulse, was not only for ever present in his mind, but ... had the effect of keeping him in that general line of consistency, on certain great subjects, which ... he continued to preserve throughout life."—Life, p. 646. "Mobility" is not the tendency to yield to every impression, to change with every impulse, but the capability of being moved by many and various impressions, of responding to an ever-renewed succession of impulses. Byron is defending the enthusiastic temperament from the charge of inconstancy and insincerity.]

[804] [The first edition of Cocker's Arithmetic was published in 1677. There are many allusions to Cocker in Arthur Murphy's Apprentice (1756), whence, perhaps, the saying, "according to Cocker."]

[805] {602} "[Et Horatii] Curiosa felicitas."—Petronius Arbiter, Salyricôn, cap. cxviii.

[806]

["Damn with faint praise, assent with civil leer,

And without sneering, teach the rest to sneer."

Pope on Addison, Prologue to the Satires, lines 201, 202.]

[807] {604}[Bion, Epitaphium Adonidis, line 28.]

[808] [" ... genetrix hominum, divômque voluptas, Alma Venus!" Lucret., De Rerum Nat., lib. i. lines 1, 2.]

[809] {605}[Job iv. 13.]

[810] See the account of the ghost of the uncle of Prince Charles of Saxony, raised by Schroepfer—"Karl—Karl—was willst du mit mir?"

[For Johann Georg Schrepfer (1730(?)-1774), see J.S.B. Schlegel's Tagebuch, etc., 1806, and Schwärmer und Schwindler, von Dr. Eugen Sierke, 1874, pp. 298-332.]

[811] {606}[Inferno, Canto III. line 9.]

[OG] When once discovered it don't like to come near it.—[MS.]

[OH] {607}A beardless chin——.—[MS.]

[812] [End of Canto 16. B. My. 6, 1823.—MS.]

Endnotes

[The Marquis Gabriel de Castelnau, author of an Essai sur LвҖҷHistoire ancienne et moderne de la Nouvelle Russie (Sec. Ed. 3В tom. 1827), was, at one time, resident at Odessa, where he met and made the acquaintance of Armand Emanuel, Duc de Richelieu, who took part in the siege of Ismail. M. LГ©on de Crousaz-CrГ©tet describes him as вҖңancien surintendant des thГ©Гўtres sous lвҖҷEmpereur Paul.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Le Duc de Richelieu, 1897, p. 83.] вҶ©

[For Robert Stewart, Viscount Castlereagh, second Marquis of Londonderry (1769вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1822), see Letters, 1900, iv. 108, 109, note 1.] вҶ©

[Samuel Ferrand Waddington, born 1759, hop-grower and radical politician, first came into notice as the chairman of public meetings in favour of making peace with the French in 1793. He was the author, inter alia, of A Key to a Delicate Investigation, 1812, and An Address to the People of the United Kingdom, 1812. He was alive in 1822. James Watson (1766вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1838), a radical agitator of the following of Thomas Spence, was engaged, in the autumn of 1816, in an abortive conspiracy to blow up cavalry barracks, barricade the streets, and seize the Bank and the Tower. He was tried for high treason before Lord Ellenborough, and acquitted.] вҶ©

[Macbeth, act iv. sc. 3, lines 7, 8.] вҶ©

I say by the law of the landвҒ вҖ”the laws of humanity judge more gently; but as the legitimates have always the law in their mouths, let them here make the most of it. вҶ©

[Mr.В Joseph Carttar, of Deptford, coroner for the County of Kent, addressed the jury at some length. The following sentences are taken from the report of the inquest, contained in The Annual Biography and Obituary for the year 1823, vol. vii. p. 57: вҖңAs a public man, it is impossible for me to weigh his character in any scales that I can hold. In private life I believe the world will admit that a more amiable man could not be found.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ If it should unfortunately appear that there is not sufficient evidence to prove what is generally considered the indication of a disordered mind, I trust that the jury will pay some attention to my humble opinion, which is, that no man can be in his proper senses at the moment he commits so rash an act as self-murder.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ The Bible declares that a man clings to nothing so strongly as his own life, I therefore view it as an axiom, and an abstract principle, that a man must necessarily be out of his mind at the moment of destroying himself.вҖқ Byron, probably, read the report of the inquest in CobbettвҖҷs Weekly Register (August 17, 1822, vol. 43, pp. 389вҒ вҖ“вҒ 425). The вҖңeulogyвҖқ was in perfectly good taste, but there can be little doubt that if вҖңWaddington or WatsonвҖқ had cut their вҖңcarotid arteries,вҖқ the verdict would have been different.] вҶ©

From this number must be excepted Canning. Canning is a genius, almost a universal one, an orator, a wit, a poet, a statesman; and no man of talent can long pursue the path of his late predecessor, Lord C. If ever man saved his country, Canning can, but will he? I for one, hope so.

[The phrase, вҖңgreat moral lesson,вҖқ was employed by the Duke of Wellington, Г  propos of the restoration of pictures and statues to their вҖңrightful owners,вҖқ in a despatch addressed to Castlereagh, under date, Paris, September 19, 1815 (The Dispatches, etc. (ed. by Colonel Gurwood), 1847, viii. 270). The words, вҖңmoral lesson,вҖқ as applied to the French generally, are to be found in ScottвҖҷs Field of Waterloo (conclusion, stanza vi. line 3), which was written about the same time as the despatch. Byron quotes them in his вҖңOde from the French,вҖқ stanza iv. line 8 (see Poetical Works, 1900, iii. 434, note 1). There is a satirical allusion to the DukeвҖҷs вҖңassumption of the didacticвҖқ about teaching a вҖңgreat moral lessonвҖқ in the Preface to the first number of the Liberal (1822, p. xi.).] вҶ©

When Lord Sandwich said вҖңhe did not know the difference between orthodoxy and heterodoxy,вҖқ Warburton, the bishop, replied, вҖңOrthodoxy, my lord, is my doxy, and heterodoxy is another manвҖҷs doxy.вҖқ A prelate of the present day has discovered, it seems, a third kind of doxy, which has not greatly exalted in the eyes of the elect that which Bentham calls вҖңChurch-of-Englandism.вҖқ

[For the вҖңprelate,вҖқ see Letters, 1902, vi. 101, note 2.] вҶ©

[For the Duke of Wellington and the Holy Alliance, see the Introduction to The Age of Bronze, Poetical Works, 1901, v. 538, 561.] вҶ©

[вҖңAs the Poem is to be published anonymously, omit the Dedication. I wonвҖҷt attack the dog in the dark. Such things are for scoundrels and renegadoes like himselfвҖқ [Revise]. See, too, letter to Murray, May 6, 1819 (Letters, 1900, iv. 294); and SoutheyвҖҷs letter to Bedford, July 31, 1819 (Selections from the Letters, etc., 1856, in. 137, 138). According to the editor of the Works of Lord Byron, 1833 (xv. 101), the existence of the Dedication вҖңbecame notoriousвҖқ in consequence of HobhouseвҖҷs article in the Westminster Review, 1824. He adds, for SoutheyвҖҷs consolation and encouragement, that вҖңfor several years the verses have been selling in the streets as a broadside,вҖқ and that вҖңit would serve no purpose to exclude them on the present occasion.вҖқ But Southey was not appeased. He tells Allan Cunningham (June 3, 1833) that вҖңthe new edition of ByronвҖҷs works isвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ one of the very worst symptoms of these bad timesвҖқ (Life and Correspondence, 1850, vi. 217).] вҶ©

[In the вҖңCritique on Bertram,вҖқ which Coleridge contributed to the Courier, in 1816, and republished in the Biographia Literaria, in 1817 (chap, xxiii.), he gives a detailed analysis of вҖңthe old Spanish play, entitled Atheista Fulminato [vide ante, the вҖҳIntroduction to Don JuanвҖҳ]вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ which under various names (Don Juan, the Libertine, etc.) has had its day of favour in every country throughout EuropeвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ Rank, fortune, wit, talent, acquired knowledge, and liberal accomplishments, with beauty of person, vigorous health, and constitutional hardihoodвҒ вҖ”all these advantages, elevated by the habits and sympathies of noble birth and national character, are supposed to have combined in Don Juan, so as to give him the means of carrying into all its practical consequences the doctrine of a godless nature, as the sole ground and efficient cause not only of all things, events, and appearances, but likewise of all our thoughts, sensations, impulses, and actions. Obedience to nature is the only virtue.вҖқ It is possible that Byron traced his own lineaments in this too life-like portraiture, and at the same time conceived the possibility of a new Don Juan, вҖңmade upвҖқ after his own likeness. His extreme resentment at ColeridgeвҖҷs just, though unwise and uncalled-for, attack on Maturin stands in need of some explanation. See letter to Murray, September 17, 1817 (Letters, 1900, iv. 172).] вҶ©

[вҖңHave you heard that Don Juan came over with a dedication to me, in which Lord Castlereagh and I (being hand in glove intimates) were coupled together for abuse as вҖҳthe two RobertsвҖҷ? A fear of persecution (sic) from the one Robert is supposed to be the reason why it has been suppressedвҖқ (Southey to Rev. H. Hill, August 13, 1819, Selections from the Letters, etc., 1856, iii. 142). For вҖңQuarrel between Byron and Southey,вҖқ see Introduction to The Vision of Judgment, Poetical Works, 1901, iv. 475вҒ вҖ“вҒ 480; and Letters, 1901, vi. 377вҒ вҖ“вҒ 399 (Appendix I.).] вҶ©

[The reference must be to the detailed enumeration of вҖңthe powers requisite for the production of poetry,вҖқ and the subsequent antithesis of Imagination and Fancy contained in the Preface to the collected Poems of William Wordsworth, published in 1815. In the Preface to the Excursion (1814) it is expressly stated that вҖңit is not the authorвҖҷs intention formally to announce a system.вҖқ] вҶ©

WordsworthвҖҷs place may be in the CustomsвҒ вҖ”it is, I think, in that or the ExciseвҒ вҖ”besides another at Lord LonsdaleвҖҷs table, where this poetical charlatan and political parasite licks up the crumbs with a hardened alacrity; the converted Jacobin having long subsided into the clownish sycophant [despised retainerвҒ вҖ”MS. erased] of the worst prejudices of the aristocracy.

[Wordsworth obtained his appointment as Distributor of Stamps for the county of Westmoreland in March, 1813, through Lord LonsdaleвҖҷs вҖңpatronageвҖқ (see his letter, March 6, 1813). The Excursion was dedicated to Lord Lonsdale in a sonnet dated July 29, 1814вҒ вҖ”

вҖңOft through thy fair domains, illustrious Peer,
In youth I roamedвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ
Now, by thy care befriended, I appear
Before thee, Lonsdale, and this Work present.вҖқ]

вҶ©

[Paradise Lost, vii. 25, 26.] вҶ©

вҖңPale, but not cadaverous:вҖқвҒ вҖ”MiltonвҖҷs two elder daughters are said to have robbed him of his books, besides cheating and plaguing him in the economy of his house, etc., etc. His feelings on such an outrage, both as a parent and a scholar, must have been singularly painful. Hayley compares him to Lear. See part third, Life of Milton, by W. Hayley (or Hailey, as spelt in the edition before me).

[The Life of Milton, by William Hailey (sic), Esq., Basil, 1799, p. 186.] вҶ©

OrвҒ вҖ”

вҖңWould he subside into a hackney LaureateвҒ вҖ”
A scribbling, self-sold, soul-hired, scorned Iscariot?вҖқ

I doubt if вҖңLaureateвҖқ and вҖңIscariotвҖқ be good rhymes, but must say, as Ben Jonson did to Sylvester, who challenged him to rhyme withвҒ вҖ”

вҖңI, John Sylvester,
Lay with your sister.вҖқ

Jonson answeredвҒ вҖ”вҖңI, Ben Jonson, lay with your wife.вҖқ Sylvester answeredвҒ вҖ”вҖңThat is not rhyme.вҖқвҒ вҖ”вҖңNo,вҖқ said Ben Jonson; вҖңbut it is true.вҖқ

[For Robert Stewart, Viscount Castlereagh, see The Age of Bronze, line 538, Poetical Works, 1901, v. 568, note 2; and Letters, 1900, iv. 108, note 1.] вҶ©

For the character of Eutropius, the eunuch and minister at the court of Arcadius, see Gibbon, [Decline and Fall, 1825, ii. 307, 308]. вҶ©

[вҖңMr.В John MurrayвҒ вҖ”As publisher to the Admiralty and of various Government works, if the five stanzas concerning Castlereagh should risk your ears or the Navy List, you may omit them in the publicationвҒ вҖ”in that case the two last lines of stanza 10 [i.e. 11] must end with the couplet (lines 7, 8) inscribed in the margin. The stanzas on Castlerighi (as the Italians call him) are 11, 12, 13, 14, 15.вҖқвҒ вҖ”MS. M.] вҶ©

[Commenting on a вҖңpathetic sentimentвҖқ of Leoni, the author of the Italian translation of Childe Harold (вҖңSciagurata condizione di questa mia patria!вҖқ), Byron affirms that the Italians execrated Castlereagh вҖңas the cause, by the conduct of the English at Genoa.вҖқ вҖңSurely,вҖқ he exclaims, вҖңthat man will not die in his bed: there is no spot of the earth where his name is not a hissing and a curse. Imagine what must be the manвҖҷs talent for Odium, who has contrived to spread his infamy like a pestilence from Ireland to Italy, and to make his name an execration in all languages.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Letter to Murray, May 8, 1820, Letters, 1901, v. 22, note 1.] вҶ©

[Charles James Fox and the Whig Club of his time adopted a uniform of blue and buff. Hence the livery of the Edinburgh Review.] вҶ©

I allude not to our friend LandorвҖҷs hero, the traitor Count Julian, but to GibbonвҖҷs hero, vulgarly yclept вҖңThe Apostate.вҖқ вҶ©

[Begun at Venice, September 6; finished November 1, 1818.] вҶ©

[The pantomime which Byron and his readers вҖңall had seen,вҖқ was an abbreviated and bowdlerized version of ShadwellвҖҷs Libertine. вҖңFirst produced by Mr.В Garrick on the boards of Drury Lane Theatre,вҖқ it was recomposed by Charles Anthony Delpini, and performed at the Royalty Theatre, in GoodmanвҖҷs Fields, in 1787. It was entitled Don Juan; or, The Libertine Destroyed: A Tragic Pantomimical Entertainment, In Two Acts. Music Composed by Mr.В Gluck. вҖңScaramouch,вҖқ the вҖңSganarelleвҖқ of MoliГЁreвҖҷs Festin de Pierre, was a favourite character of Joseph Grimaldi. He was cast for the part, in 1801, at SadlerвҖҷs Wells, and, again, on a memorable occasion, November 28, 1809, at Covent Garden Theatre, when the O.P. riots were in full swing, and (see the Morning Chronicle, November 29, 1809) вҖңthere was considerable tumult in the pit.вҖқ According to вҖңBozвҖқ (Memoirs of Joseph Grimaldi, 1846, ii. 81, 106, 107), Byron patronized GrimaldiвҖҷs вҖңbenefits at Covent Garden,вҖқ was repeatedly in his company, and when he left England, in 1816, вҖңpresented him with a valuable silver snuff-box.вҖқ At the end of the pantomime вҖңthe Furies gather round him [Don Juan], and the Tyrant being bound in chains is hurried away and thrown into flames.вҖқ The Devil is conspicuous by his absence.] вҶ©

[Edward Vernon, Admiral (1684вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1757), took Porto Bello in 1739.

William Augustus, second son of George II. (1721вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1765), fought at the battles of Dettingen, 1743; Fontenoy, 1745; and at Culloden, 1746. For the вҖңseverity of the Duke of Cumberland,вҖқ see ScottвҖҷs Tales of a Grandfather, Prose Works, 1830, vii. 852, sq.

James Wolfe, General, born January 2, 1726, was killed at the siege of Quebec, September 13, 1759.

Edward, Lord Hawke, Admiral (1715вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1781), totally defeated the French fleet in Quiberon Bay, November 20, 1759.

Ferdinand, Duke of Brunswick (1721вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1792), gained the victory at Minden, August 1, 1759.

John Manners, Marquess of Granby (1721вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1790), commanded the British forces in Germany (1766вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1769).

John Burgoyne, General, defeated the Americans at Germantown, October 3, 1777, but surrendered to General Gates at Saratoga, October 17, 1778. He died in 1792.

Augustus, Viscount Keppel, Admiral (1725вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1786), was tried by court-martial, January-February, 1779, for allowing the French fleet off Ushant to escape, July, 1778. He was honourably acquitted.

Richard, Earl Howe, Admiral (1725вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1799), known by the sailors as вҖңBlack Dick,вҖқ defeated the French off Ushant, June 1, 1794.] вҶ©

[Compare Macbeth, act iv. sc. i, line 65.] вҶ©

[вҖңIn the eighth and concluding lecture of Mr.В HazlittвҖҷs canons of criticism, delivered at the Surrey Institution (The English Poets, 1870, pp. 203, 204), I am accused of having вҖҳlauded Buonaparte to the skies in the hour of his success, and then peevishly wreaking my disappointment on the god of my idolatry.вҖҷ The first lines I ever wrote upon Buonaparte were the вҖҳOde to Napoleon,вҖҷ after his abdication in 1814. All that I have ever written on that subject has been done since his decline;вҒ вҖ”I never вҖҳmet him in the hour of his success.вҖҷ I have considered his character at different periods, in its strength and in its weakness: by his zealots I am accused of injusticeвҒ вҖ”by his enemies as his warmest partisan, in many publications, both English and foreign.

вҖңFor the accuracy of my delineation I have high authority. A year and some months ago, I had the pleasure of seeing at Venice my friend the honourable Douglas Kinnaird. In his way through Germany, he told me that he had been honoured with a presentation to, and some interviews with, one of the nearest family connections of Napoleon (EugГЁne Beauharnais). During one of these, he read and translated the lines alluding to Buonaparte, in the Third Canto of Childe Harold. He informed me, that he was authorized by the illustrious personageвҒ вҖ”(still recognized as such by the Legitimacy in Europe)вҒ вҖ”to whom they were read, to say, that вҖҳthe delineation was complete,вҖҷ or words to this effect. It is no puerile vanity which induces me to publish this fact;вҒ вҖ”but Mr.В Hazlitt accuses my inconsistency, and infers my inaccuracy. Perhaps he will admit that, with regard to the latter, one of the most intimate family connections of the Emperor may be equally capable of deciding on the subject. I tell Mr.В Hazlitt that I never flattered Napoleon on the throne, nor maligned him since his fall. I wrote what I think are the incredible antitheses of his character.

вҖңMr.В Hazlitt accuses me further of delineating myself in Childe Harold, etc., etc. I have denied this long agoвҒ вҖ”but, even were it true, Locke tells us, that all his knowledge of human understanding was derived from studying his own mind. From Mr.В HazlittвҖҷs opinion of my poetry I do not appeal; but I request that gentleman not to insult me by imputing the basest of crimesвҒ вҖ”viz. вҖҳpraising publicly the same man whom I wished to depreciate in his adversity:вҖҷвҒ вҖ”the first lines I ever wrote on Buonaparte were in his dispraise, in 1814вҒ вҖ”the last, though not at all in his favour, were more impartial and discriminative, in 1818. Has he become more fortunate since 1814?вҖқ For ByronвҖҷs various estimates of NapoleonвҖҷs character and career, see Childe Harold, Canto III, stanza xxxvi. line 7, Poetical Works, 1899, ii. 238, note 1.] вҶ©

[Charles FranГ§ois Duperier Dumouriez (1739вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1823) defeated the Austrians at Jemappes, November 6, 1792, etc. He published his MГ©moires (Hamburg et Leipsic), 1794. For the spelling, see Memoirs of General Dumourier, written by himself, translated by John Fenwick. London, 1794. See, too, Lettre de Joseph Servan, Ex-ministre de la Guerre, Sur le mГ©moire lu par M. Dumourier le 13 Juin Г  lвҖҷAssemblГ©e Nationale; BibiothГЁque Historique de la RГ©volution, вҖңJustifications,вҖқ 7, 8, 9.] вҶ©

[Antoine Pierre Joseph Barnave, born 1761, was appointed President of the Constituent Assembly in 1790. He was guillotined November 30, 1793.

Jean Pierre Brissot de Warville, philosopher and politician, born January 14, 1754, was one of the principal instigators of the revolt of the Champ de Mars, July, 1789. He was guillotined October 31, 1793.

Marie Jean Antoine, Marquis de Condorcet, born September 17, 1743, was appointed President of the Legislative Assembly in 1792. Proscribed by the Girondins, he poisoned himself to escape the guillotine, March 28, 1794.

HonorГ© Gabriel Riquetti, Comte de Mirabeau, born March 9, 1749, died April 2, 1791.

JГ©rГҙme Petion de Villeneuve, born 1753, Mayor of Paris in 1791, took an active part in the imprisonment of the king. In 1793 he fell under RobespierreвҖҷs displeasure, and to escape proscription took refuge in the department of Calvados. In 1794 his body was found in a field, half eaten by wolves.

Jean Baptiste, Baron de Clootz (better known as Anacharsis Clootz), was born in 1755. In 1790, at the bar of the National Convention, he described himself as the вҖңSpeaker of Mankind.вҖқ Being suspected by Robespierre, he was condemned to death, March 24, 1794. On the scaffold he begged to be executed last, вҖңin order to establish certain principles.вҖқ (See CarlyleвҖҷs French Revolution, 1839, iii. 315.)

Georges Jacques Danton, born October 28, 1759, helped to establish the Revolutionary Tribunal, March 10, and the Committee of Public Safety, April 6, 1793; agreed to proscription of the Girondists, June, 1793; was executed with Camille Desmoulins and others, April 5, 1794.

Jean Paul Marat, born May 24, 1744, physician and man of science, proposed and carried out the wholesale massacre of September 2вҒ вҖ“вҒ 5, 1792; was denounced to, but acquitted by, the Revolutionary Tribunal, May, 1793; assassinated by Charlotte Corday, July 13, 1793.

Marie Jean Paul, Marquis de La Fayette, born September 6, 1757, died May 19, 1834.

With the exception of La Fayette, who outlived Byron by ten years, and Lord St.В Vincent, all вҖңthe famous personsвҖқ mentioned in stanzas ii.-iv. had passed away long before the First Canto of Don Juan was written.] вҶ©

[BarthГ©lemi Catherine Joubert, born April 14, 1769, distinguished himself at the engagements of Cava, Montebello, Rivoli, and in the Tyrol. He was afterwards sent to oppose SuvГіroff, and was killed at Novi, August 15, 1799.

For Hoche and Marceau, vide ante, Poetical Works, 1899, ii. 296.

Jean Lannes, Duke of Montebello, born April 11, 1769, distinguished himself at Lodi, Aboukir, Acre, Austerlitz, Jena and, lastly, at Essling, where he was mortally wounded. He died May 31, 1809.

Louis Charles Antoine Desaix de Voygoux, born August 27, 1768, won the victory at the Pyramids, July 21, 1798. He was mortally wounded at Marengo, June 14, 1800.

Jean Victor Moreau, born August 11, 1763, was victorious at Engen, May 3, and at Hohenlinden, December 3, 1800. He was struck by a cannon-ball at the battle of Dresden, August 27, and died September 2, 1813.] вҶ©

[Hor., Od., iv. c. ix. 1. 25вҒ вҖ”

вҖңVixere fortes ante Agamemnona,вҖқ etc.]

вҶ©

[Hor., Epist. Ad Pisones, lines 148, 149вҒ вҖ”

вҖңSemper ad eventum festinat, et in medias res,
Non secus ac notas, auditorem rapitвҒ вҖ”вҖқ]

вҶ©

[вҖңQuien no ha visto Sevilla, no ha visto maravilla.вҖқ] вҶ©

[In his reply to Blackwood (No. xxix. August, 1819), Byron somewhat disingenuously rebuts the charge that Don Juan contained вҖңan elaborate satire on the character and manners of his wife.вҖқ вҖңIf,вҖқ he writes, вҖңin a poem by no means ascertained to be my production there appears a disagreeable, casuistical, and by no means respectable female pedant, it is set down for my wife. Is there any resemblance? If there be, it is in those who make itвҒ вҖ”I can see none.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Letters, 1900, iv. 477. The allusions in stanzas xii.-xiv., and, again, in stanzas xxvii.-xxix., are, and must have been meant to be, unmistakable.] вҶ©

[Gregor von Feinagle, born? 1765, was the inventor of a system of mnemonics, вҖңfounded on the topical memory of the ancients,вҖқ as described by Cicero and Quinctilian. He lectured, in 1811, at the Royal Institution and elsewhere. When Rogers was asked if he attended the lectures, he replied, вҖңNo; I wished to learn the Art of ForgettingвҖқ (Table-Talk of Samuel Rogers, 1856, p. 42).] вҶ©

Little she spokeвҒ вҖ”but what she spoke was Attic all,
With words and deeds in perfect unanimity.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[Sir Samuel Romilly, born 1757, lost his wife on the 29th of October, and committed suicide on the 2nd of November, 1818.вҒ вҖ”вҖңBut there will come a day of reckoning, even if I should not live to see it. I have at least seen Romilly shivered, who was one of the assassins. When that felon or lunaticвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ was doing his worst to uproot my whole family, tree, branch, and blossomsвҒ вҖ”when, after taking my retainer, he went over to them [see Letters, 1899, iii. 324]вҒ вҖ”when he was bringing desolationвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ on my household godsвҒ вҖ”did he think that, in less than three years, a natural eventвҒ вҖ”a severe, domestic, but an unexpected and common calamityвҒ вҖ”would lay his carcase in a cross-road, or stamp his name in a verdict of Lunacy! Did he (who in his drivelling sexagenary dotage had not the courage to survive his NurseвҒ вҖ”for what else was a wife to him at his time of life?)вҒ вҖ”reflect or consider what my feelings must have been, when wife, and child, and sister, and name, and fame, and country, were to be my sacrifice on his legal altarвҒ вҖ”and this at a moment when my health was declining, my fortune embarrassed, and my mind had been shaken by many kinds of disappointmentвҒ вҖ”while I was yet young, and might have reformed what might be wrong in my conduct, and retrieved what was perplexing in my affairs! But the wretch is in his grave,вҖқ etc.-Letter to Murray, June 7, 1819, Letters, 1900, iv. 316.] вҶ©

[Maria Edgeworth (1767вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1849) published Castle Rackrent, etc., etc., etc., in 1800. вҖңIn 1813,вҖқ says Byron, вҖңI recollect to have met them [the Edgeworths] in the fashionable world of London.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ She was a nice little unassuming вҖҳJeannie Deans-looking body,вҖҷ as we Scotch say; and if not handsome, certainly not ill-lookingвҖқ (Diary, January 19, 1821, Letters, 1901, v. 177вҒ вҖ“вҒ 179).] вҶ©

[Sarah Trimmer (1741вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1810) published, in 1782, Easy Introduction to the Study of Nature; History of the Robins (dedicated to the Princess Sophia) in 1786, etc.] вҶ©

[Hannah More (1745вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1833) published Coelebs in Search of a Wife in 1809.] вҶ©

[Pope, Rape of the Lock, Canto II, line 17.] вҶ©

[John Harrison (1693вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1776), known as вҖңLongitudeвҖқ Harrison, was the inventor of watch compensation. He received, in slowly and reluctantly paid instalments, a sum of ВЈ20,000 from the Government, for producing a chronometer which should determine the longitude within half a degree. A watch which contained his latest improvements was worn by Captain Cook during his three yearsвҖҷ circumnavigation of the globe.] вҶ©

вҖңDescription des vertus incomparables de lвҖҷHuile de Macassar.вҖқ See the Advertisement. [An Historical, Philosophical and Practical Essay on the Human Hair, was published by Alexander Rowland, jun., in 1816. It was inscribed, вҖңTo her Royal Highness the Princess Charlotte of Wales and Cobourg.вҖқ] вҶ©

Where all was innocence and quiet bliss.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

And so she seemed, in all outside formalities.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[вҖңвҖҠвҖҳZounds, an I were now by this rascal, I could brain him with his ladyвҖҷs fan.вҖқвҒ вҖ”I Henry IV., act ii, sc 3, lines 19, 20.] вҶ©

Wishing each other damned, divorced, or dead.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[According to Medwin (Conversations, 1824, p. 55), Byron вҖңwas surprised one day by a Doctor and a Lawyer almost forcing themselves at the same time into my room. I did not know,вҖқ he adds, вҖңtill afterwards the real object of their visit. I thought their questions singular, frivolous, and somewhat importunate, if not impertinent: but what should I have thought, if I had known that they were sent to provide proofs of my insanity?вҖқ Lady Byron, in her Remarks on Mr.В MooreвҖҷs Life, etc. (Life, pp. 661вҒ вҖ“вҒ 663), says that Dr.В Baillie (vide post, p. 412, note 2), whom she consulted with regard to her husbandвҖҷs supposed insanity, вҖңnot having had access to Lord Byron, could not pronounce a positive opinion on this point.вҖқ It appears, however, that another doctor, a Mr.В Le Mann (see Letters, 1899, iii. 293, note 1, 295, 299, etc.), visited Byron professionally, and reported on his condition to Lady Byron. Hence, perhaps, the mention of вҖңdruggists.вҖқ] вҶ©

[вҖңI deem it my duty to God to act as I am acting.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Letter of Lady Byron to Mrs.В Leigh, February 14, 1816, Letters, 1899, iii. 311.] вҶ©

[вҖңThis is so very pointed.вҖқвҒ вҖ”[?Hobhouse.] вҖңIf people make application, it is their own fault.вҖқвҒ вҖ”[B.].вҒ вҖ”[Revise.] вҶ©

[вҖңThere is some doubt about this.вҖқвҒ вҖ”[H.] вҖңWhat has the вҖҳdoubtвҖҷ to do with the poem? it is, at least, poetically true. Why apply everything to that absurd woman? I have no reference to living characters.вҖқвҒ вҖ”[B.].вҒ вҖ”[Revise.] Medwin (Conversations, 1824, p. 54) attributes the вҖңbreaking open my writing-deskвҖқ to Mrs.В Charlment (i.e. Mrs.В Clermont) the original of вҖңA Sketch,вҖқ Poetical Works, 1900, iii. 540вҒ вҖ“вҒ 544. It is evident from ByronвҖҷs reply to HobhouseвҖҷs remonstrance that Medwin did not invent this incident, but that some one, perhaps FletcherвҖҷs wife, had told him that his papers had been overhauled.] вҶ©

First their friends tried at reconciliation.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

The lawyers recommended a divorce.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

He had been ill brought up, besides was
besides being bilious.

or,

The reason was, perhaps, that he was bilious.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

And we may ownвҒ вҖ”since he is now but
laid in earth.вҒ вҖ”[MS.]

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[вҖңI could have forgiven the dagger or the bowlвҒ вҖ”any thing but the deliberate desolation piled upon me, when I stood alone upon my hearth, with my household gods shivered around me.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ Do you suppose I have forgotten it? It has, comparatively swallowed up in me every other feeling, and I am only a spectator upon earth till a tenfold opportunity offers.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Letter to Moore, September 19, 1818, Letters, 1900, iv, 262, 263. Compare, tooвҒ вҖ”

вҖңI had one only fount of quiet left,
And that they poisoned! My pure household gods
Were shivered on my hearth, and oвҖҷer their shrine
Sate grinning Ribaldry and sneering Scorn.вҖқ

Marino Faliero, act iii. sc. II, lines 361вҒ вҖ“вҒ 364.]

вҶ©

Save death or litigationвҒ вҖ”
banishmentвҒ вҖ” so he died.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[Compare Leigh Hunt on the illustrations to Andrew TookeвҖҷs Pantheon: вҖңI see before me, as vividly now as ever, his Mars and ApolloвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ and Venus very handsome, we thought, and not looking too modest in a вҖҳlight cymar.вҖҷвҖҠвҖқвҒ вҖ”Autobiography, 1860, p. 75.] вҶ©

Defending still their Iliads and Odysseys.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

See Longinus, Section 10, вҖңбјҪОҪОұ ОјбҪҙ бј•ОҪ П„О№ ПҖОөПҒбҪ¶ ОұбҪҗП„бҪҙОҪ ПҖО¬ОёОҝПӮ ПҶОұОҜОҪО·П„ОұО№, ПҖОұОёбҝ¶ОҪ ОҙбҪІ ПғПҚОҪОҝОҙОҝПӮ.

[вҖңThe effect desired is that not one passion only should be seen in her, but a concourse of passionsвҖқ (Longinis on the Sublime, by W. Rhys Roberts, 1899, pp. 70, 71).

The Ode alluded to is the famous ОҰОұОҜОҪОөП„ОұОҜ ОјОҝО№ ОәбҝҶОҪОҝПӮ бјҙПғОҝПӮ ОёОөОҝбҝ–ПғО№ОҪ, Оә.П„.О».

вҖңHim rival to the gods I place;
Him loftier yet, if loftier be,
Who, Lesbia, sits before thy face,
Who listens and who looks on thee.вҖқ

W.E. Gladstone.

вҖңI do not think you are quite held out by the quotation. Longinus says the circumstantial assemblage of the passions makes the sublime; he does not talk of the sublime being soaring and ample.вҖқвҒ вҖ”[H.] вҖңI do not care for thisвҒ вҖ”it must stand.вҖқвҒ вҖ”[B.]вҒ вҖ”[Marginal notes in Revise.]] вҶ©

[Bucol., Ecl. ii. вҖңAlexis.вҖқ] вҶ©

Too much their antique
modest
downright bard by the elision
omission.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

Fact! There is, or was, such an edition, with all the obnoxious epigrams of Martial placed by themselves at the end.

[In the Delphin Martial (Amsterdam, 1701) the Epigrammata Obscaena are printed as an Appendix (pp. 2вҒ вҖ“вҒ 56), вҖң[Ne] quiequam desideraretur a morosis quibusdam hominibus.вҖқ] вҶ©

See his Confessions, lib. i. cap. ix.; [lib. ii. cap. ii., et passim]. By the representation which Saint Augustine gives of himself in his youth, it is easy to see that he was what we should call a rake. He avoided the school as the plague; he loved nothing but gaming and public shows; he robbed his father of everything he could find; he invented a thousand lies to escape the rod, which they were obliged to make use of to punish his irregularities. вҶ©

[ByronвҖҷs early letters are full of complaints of his motherвҖҷs violent temper. See, for instance, letter to the Hon.В Augusta Byron, April 23, 1805. In another letter to John M.B. Pigot, August 9, 1806, he speaks of her as вҖңMrs.В Byron вҖҳfuriosaвҖҳвҖқ (Letters, 1898, i. 60, 101).] вҶ©

[вҖңHaving surrendered the last symbol of power, the unfortunate Boabdil continued on towards the Alpuxarras, that he might not behold the entrance of the Christians into his capital.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ Having ascended an eminence commanding the last view of Granada, the Moors paused involuntarily to take a farewell gaze at their beloved city, which a few steps more would shut from their sight for ever.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ The heart of Boabdil, softened by misfortunes, and overcharged with grief, could no longer contain itself. вҖҳAllah achbar! God is great!вҖҷ said he; but the words of resignation died upon his lips, and he burst into a flood of tears.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Chronicle of the Conquest of Granada, by Washington Irving, 1829, ii. 379вҒ вҖ“вҒ 381.] вҶ©

IвҖҷll tell you a secretвҒ вҖ”silence! hush!
which youвҖҷll hush

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

Spouses from twenty years of age to thirty
Are most admired by women of strict
staid virtue.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

For the particulars of St.В AnthonyвҖҷs recipe for hot blood in cold weather, see Mr.В Alban ButlerвҖҷs Lives of the Saints.

[вҖңI am not sure it was not St.В Francis who had the wife of snowвҒ вҖ”in that case the line must run, вҖҳSt.В Francis back to reason.вҖҷвҖҠвҖқвҒ вҖ”[MS. M.]

For the seven snow-balls, of which вҖңthe greatestвҖқ was his wife, see Life of вҖңSt.В Francis of AssisiвҖқ (The Golden Legend (edited by F.S. Ellis), 1900, v. 221). See, too, the Lives of the Saints, etc., by the Rev. Alban Butler, 1838, ii. 574.] вҶ©

[The sorceress in TassoвҖҷs Gerusalemme Liberata. The story of Armida and Rinaldo forms the plot of operas by GlГјck and Rossini.] вҶ©

Thinking God might not understand the case.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. M., Revise.]

вҶ©

[вҖңQuel giorno piГ№ non vi leggemmo avante.вҖқ

Dante, Inferno, canto v. line 138.]

вҶ©

[вҖңConscienzia mвҖҷassicura,
La buona compagnia che lвҖҷuom francheggia
Sotto lвҖҷosbergo del sentirsi pura.вҖқ

Inferno, canto xxviii, lines 115вҒ вҖ“вҒ 117.]

вҶ©

Deemed that her thoughts no more required control.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[See Ovid, Metamorph., vii. 9, sq.] вҶ©

CampbellвҖҷs Gertrude of WyomingвҒ вҖ”(I think)вҒ вҖ”the opening of Canto Second [Part III. stanza i. lines 1вҒ вҖ“вҒ 4]вҒ вҖ”but quote from memory. вҶ©

[See ColeridgeвҖҷs Biographia Literaria, chap. i. (ed. 1847, i. 14, 15); and Dejection: An Ode, lines 86вҒ вҖ“вҒ 93.] вҶ©

I say this by the wayвҒ вҖ”so donвҖҷt look stern.
But if youвҖҷre angry, reader, pass it by.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[Juan Boscan, of Barcelona (1500вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1544), in concert with his friend Garcilasso, Italianized Castilian poetry. He was the author of the Leandro, a poem in blank verse, of canzoni, and sonnets after the model of Petrarch, and of The Allegory.вҒ вҖ”History of Spanish Literature, by George Ticknor, 1888, i. 513.] вҶ©

[Garcias Lasso or Garcilasso de la Vega (1503вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1536), of a noble family at Toledo, was a warrior as well as a poet, вҖңnow seizing on the sword and now the pen.вҖқ After serving with distinction in Germany, Africa, and Provence, he was killed at Muy, near Frejus, in 1536, by a stone, thrown from a tower, which fell on his head as he was leading on his battalion. He was the author of thirty-seven sonnets, five canzoni, and three pastorals.вҒ вҖ”Vide ibidem, pp. 522вҒ вҖ“вҒ 535.] вҶ©

A real wittol always is suspicious,
But always also hunts in the wrong place.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

Change horses every hour from night till noon.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

Except the promises of true theology.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[вҖңOh, Susan! IвҖҷve said, in the moments of mirth,
WhatвҖҷs devotion to thee or to me?
I devoutly believe thereвҖҷs a heaven on earth,
And believe that that heavenвҖҷs in thee.вҖқ

вҖңThe Catalogue,вҖқ Poetical Works of the late Thomas Little, 1803, p. 128.]

вҶ©

She stood on GuiltвҖҷs steep brink, in all the sense
And full security of Innocence.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

To leave these two young people then and there.вҒ вҖ”[MS.] вҶ©

[вҖңAge Xerxes.. eo usque luxuria gaudens, ut edicto prГҰmium ei proponeret, qui novum voluptatis genus reperisset.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Val. Max, De Dictis, etc., lib. ix. cap. 1, ext. 3.] вҶ©

[вҖңYou certainly will be damned for all this scene.вҖқвҒ вҖ”[H.]] вҶ©

[Compare Childe Harold, Canto IV. stanza iii. line 2, Poetical Works, ii. 329, note 3.] вҶ©

Our coming, nor look brightly till we come.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

Sweet is a lawsuit to the attorneyвҒ вҖ”sweet, etc.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[So, too, Falstaff, Henry IV., act ii. sc. 2, lines 79, 80.] вҶ©

WhoвҖҷve made us waitвҒ вҖ”God knows how long already,
For an entailed estate, or country-seat,
Wishing them not exactly damned, but deadвҒ вҖ”he
Knows nought of grief, who has not so been worriedвҒ вҖ”
вҖҳT is strange old people donвҖҷt like to be buried.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[Byron has not been forgotten at Harrow, though it is a bend of the Cam (ByronвҖҷs Pool), not his favourite Duck Pool (now вҖңDuckerвҖқ) which bears his name.] вҶ©

[The reference is to the metallic tractors of Benjamin Charles Perkins, which were advertised as a вҖңcure for all disorders, Red Noses,вҖқ etc. Compare English Bards, etc., lines 131, 132вҒ вҖ”

вҖңWhat varied wonders tempt us as they pass!
The Cow-pox, Tractors, Galvanism, and Gas.вҖқ

See Poetical Works, 1898, i. 307, note 3.]

вҶ©

[Edward Jenner (1749вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1823) made his first experiments in vaccination, May 14, 1796. Napoleon caused his soldiers to be vaccinated, and imagined that the English would be gratified by his recognition of JennerвҖҷs discovery.

Sir William Congreve (1772вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1828) invented вҖңCongreve rocketsвҖқ or shells in 1804. They were used with great effect at the battle of Leipzig, in 1813.] вҶ©

[вҖңMon cher ne touchez pas Г  la petite VГ©role.вҖқвҒ вҖ”[H.]вҒ вҖ”[Revise.]] вҶ©

[Experiments in galvanism were made on the body of Forster the murderer, by GalvaniвҖҷs nephew, Professor Aldini, January and February, 1803.] вҶ©

[вҖңPut out these lines, and keep the others.вҖқвҒ вҖ”[H.]вҒ вҖ”[Revise.]] вҶ©

[Sir Humphry Davy, P.R.S. (1778вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1829), invented the safety-lamp in 1815.] вҶ©

[In a critique of An Account of the Empire of Marocco.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ To which is added anвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ account of Tombuctoo, the great Emporium of Central Africa, by James Grey Jackson, London, 1809, the reviewer comments on the authorвҖҷs pedantry in correcting вҖңthe common orthography of African names.вҖқ вҖңWe do not,вҖқ he writes, вҖңgreatly object toвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ Fas for Fez, or even Timbuctoo for Tombuctoo, but Marocco for Morocco is a little too much.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Edinburgh Review, July, 1809В vol. xiv. p. 307.] вҶ©

[Sir John Ross (1777вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1856) published A Voyage of DiscoveryвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ for the purpose of Exploring BaffinвҖҷs Bay, etc., in 1819; Sir W.E. Parry (1790вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1855) published his Journal of a Voyage of Discovery to the Arctic Regions between 4th April and 18th November, 1818, in 1820.] вҶ©

Not only pleasureвҖҷs sin, but sinвҖҷs a pleasure.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

And lose in shining snow their summits blue.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

вҖҷTwas midnightвҒ вҖ”dark and sombre was the night, etc.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

And supper, punch, ghost-stories, and such chat.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[вҖңвҖҠвҖҳAll that, Egad,вҖҷ as Bayes saysвҖқ [in the Duke of BuckinghamвҖҷs play The Rehearsal].вҒ вҖ”Letter to Murray, September 28, 1820, Letters, 1901, v. 80.] вҶ©

[вҖңLobster-sallad, not a lobster-salad. Have you been at a London ball, and not known a Lobster-sallad?вҖңвҒ вҖ”[H.]вҒ вҖ”[Revise.] ] вҶ©

[вҖңTo-night, as Countess Guiccioli observed me poring over Don Juan, she stumbled by mere chance on the 137th stanza of the First Canto, and asked me what it meant. I told her, вҖҳNothingвҒ вҖ”but your husband is coming.вҖҷ As I said this in Italian with some emphasis, she started up in a fright, and said, вҖҳOh, my God, is he coming?вҖҷ thinking it was her own.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ You may suppose we laughed when she found out the mistake. You will be amused, as I was;вҒ вҖ”it happened not three hours ago.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Letter to Murray, November 8, 1819, Letters, 1900, iv. 374.

It should be borne in mind that the loves of Juan and Julia, the irruption of Don Alfonso, etc., were rather of the nature of prophecy than of reminiscence. The First Canto had been completed before the Countess Guiccioli appeared on the scene.] вҶ©

And thus as вҖҷtwere herself from out them crept.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. M.]

вҶ©

Ere I the wife of such a man had been!

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

But while this search was making, JuliaвҖҷs tongue.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

The Spanish вҖңCortejoвҖқ is much the same as the Italian вҖңCavalier Servente.вҖқ вҶ©

Donna Julia here made a mistake. Count OвҖҷReilly did not take AlgiersвҒ вҖ”but Algiers very nearly took him: he and his army and fleet retreated with great loss, and not much credit, from before that city, in the year 1775.

[Alexander OвҖҷReilly, born 1722, a Spanish general of Irish extraction, failed in an expedition against Algiers in 1775, in which the Spaniards lost four thousand men. In 1794 he was appointed commander-in-chief of the forces equipped against the army of the French National Convention. He died March 23, 1794.] вҶ©

[The Italian names have an obvious signification.] вҶ©

The chimneyвҒ вҖ”fit retreat for any lover!

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

вёәвҒ may deplore.

вҖ”вҒ [Alternative reading. MS. M.]

вҶ©

[вҖңThou speakest as one of the foolish women speakethвҖқ (Job ii. 10).] вҶ©

[вҖңDonвҖҷt be read aloud.вҖқвҒ вҖ”[H.]вҒ вҖ”[Revise.]] вҶ©

вёәвҒ than be put
To drown with Clarence in his Malmsey butt.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

And reckon up our balance with the devil.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[вҖңCarissimo, do review the whole scene, and think what you would say of it, if written by another.вҖқвҒ вҖ”[H.] вҖңI would say, read вҖҳThe MiracleвҖҷ [вҖҳA Tale from BoccaceвҖҷ] in HobhouseвҖҷs poems, and вҖҳJanuary and May,вҖҷ and вҖҳPaulo Purganti,вҖҷ and вҖҳHans Carvel,вҖҷ and вҖҳJoconde.вҖҷ These are laughable: it is the seriousвҒ вҖ”LittleвҖҷs poems and Lalla RookhвҒ вҖ”that affect seriously. Now Lust is a serious passion, and cannot be excited by the ludicrous.вҖқвҒ вҖ”[B.]вҒ вҖ”Marginal Notes in Revise.]

For the вҖңMiracle,вҖқ see Imitations and Translations, 1809, pp. 111вҒ вҖ“вҒ 128. вҖңJanuary and MayвҖқ is PopeвҖҷs version of ChaucerвҖҷs MerchantвҖҷs Tale. вҖңPaulo PurgantiвҖқ and вҖңHans CarvelвҖқ are by Matthew Prior; and for вҖңJocondeвҖқ (Nouvelle TirГ©e de LвҖҷAriosto, canto xxviii.) see Contes et Nouvelles en Vers, de Mr.В de la Fontaine, 1691, i. 1вҒ вҖ“вҒ 19.] вҶ©

[Compare вҖңThe use made in the French tongue of the word tact, to denote that delicate sense of propriety, which enables a man to feel his way in the difficult intercourse of polished society, seems to have been suggested by similar considerations (i.e. similar to those which suggested the use of the word taste).вҖқвҒ вҖ”Outlines of Moral Philosophy, by Dugald Stewart, Part I. sect. x. ed. 1855, p. 48. For DвҖҷAlembertвҖҷs use of tact, to denote вҖңthat peculiar delicacy of perception (which, like the nice touch of a blind man) arises from habits of close attention to those slighter feelings which escape general notice,вҖқ see Philosophical Essays, by Dugald Stewart, 1818, p. 603.] вҶ©

With base suspicion now no longer haunted.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[For the incident of the shoes, Lord Byron was probably indebted to the Scottish balladвҒ вҖ”

вҖңOur goodman came hame at eвҖҷen, and hame came he;
He spyвҖҷd a pair of jack-boots, where nae boots should be,
WhatвҖҷs this now, goodwife? WhatвҖҷs this I see?
How came these boots there, without the leave oвҖҷ me!
Boots! quoвҖҷ she:
Ay, boots, quoвҖҷ he.
Shame faвҖҷ your cuckold face, and ill mat ye see,
ItвҖҷs but a pair of water stoups the cooper sent to me,вҖқ etc.

See James JohnsonвҖҷs Musical Museum, 1787, etc., v. 466.] вҶ©

FoundвҒ вҖ”heaven knows howвҒ вҖ”his solitary way.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[William Brodie Gurney (1777вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1855), the son and grandson of eminent shorthand writers, вҖңreported the proceedings against the Duke of York in 1809, the trials of Lord Cochrane in 1814, and of Thistlewood in 1820, and the proceedings against Queen Caroline.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Dict. of Nat. Biog., art. вҖңGurney.вҖқ] вҶ©

[вҖңVenice, December 7, 1818.

вҖңAfter that stanza in the first canto of Don Juan (sent by Lord Lauderdale) towards the conclusion of the cantoвҒ вҖ”I speak of the stanza whose two last lines areвҒ вҖ”

вҖңвҖҠвҖҳThe best is that in short-hand taвҖҷen by Gurney,
Who to Madrid on purpose made a journey,вҖҷ

insert the following stanzas, вҖҳBut Donna Inez,вҖҷ etc.вҖқвҒ вҖ”[B.]

The text is based on a second or revised copy of stanzas cxc.-cxcviii. Many of the corrections and emendations which were inserted in the first draft are omitted in the later and presumably improved version. ByronвҖҷs first intention was to insert seven stanzas after stanza clxxxix., descriptive and highly depreciatory of Brougham, but for reasons of вҖңfairnessвҖқ (vide infra) he changed his mind. The casual mention of вҖңblundering BroughamвҖқ in English Bards, etc. (line 524, Poetical Works, 1898, i. 338, note 2), is a proof that his suspicions were not aroused as to the authorship of the review of Hours of Idleness (Edin. Rev., January, 1808), and it is certain that ByronвҖҷs animosity was due to the part played by Brougham at the time of the Separation. (In a letter to Byron, dated February 18, 1817, Murray speaks of a certain B. вҖңas your incessant persecutorвҒ вҖ”the source of all affected public opinion respecting you.вҖқ) The stanzas, with the accompanying notes, are not included in the editions of 1833 or 1837, and are now printed for the first time.

I

вҖңвҖҠвҖҷTwas a fine cause for those in law delightingвҒ вҖ”
вҖҷTis pity that they had no Brougham in Spain,
Famous for always talking, and neвҖҷer fighting,
For calling names, and taking them again;
For blustering, bungling, trimming, wrangling, writing,
Groping all paths to power, and all in vainвҒ вҖ”
Losing elections, character, and temper,
A foolish, clever, fellowвҒ вҖ”Idem semper!

II

вҖңBully in Senates, skulker in the Field,[A]
The AdultererвҖҷs advocate when duly feed,
The libellerвҖҷs gratis Counsel, dirty shield
Which Law affords to many a dirty deed;
A wondrous Warrior against those who yieldвҒ вҖ”
A rod to Weakness, to the brave a reedвҒ вҖ”
The PeopleвҖҷs sycophant, the PrinceвҖҷs foe,
And serving him the more by being so.

III

вҖңTory by nurture, Whig by Circumstance,
A Democrat some once or twice a year,
WheneвҖҷer it suits his purpose to advance
His vain ambition in its vague career:
A sort of Orator by sufferance,
Less for the comprehension than the ear;
With all the arrogance of endless power,
Without the sense to keep it for an hour.

IV

вҖңThe House-of-Commons Damocles of wordsвҒ вҖ”
Above him, hanging by a single hair,
On each harangue depend some hostile Swords;
And deems he that we always will forbear?
Although Defiance oft declined affords
A blotted shield no ShireвҖҷs true knight would wear:
Thersites of the House. Parolles[B] of Law,
The double Bobadill[C] takes Scorn for Awe.

V

вҖңHow noble is his languageвҒ вҖ”never pertвҒ вҖ”
How grand his sentiments which neвҖҷer run riot!
As when he swore вҖҳby God heвҖҷd sell his shirt
To head the poll!вҖҷ I wonder who would buy it
The skin has passed through such a deal of dirt
In grovelling on to powerвҒ вҖ”such stains now dye itвҒ вҖ”
So black the long-worn LionвҖҷs hide in hue,
YouвҖҷd swear his very heart had sweated through.

VI

вҖңPanting for powerвҒ вҖ”as harts for cooling streamsвҒ вҖ”
Yet half afraid to venture for the draught;
A go-between, yet blundering in extremes,
And tossed along the vessel fore and aft;
Now shrinking back, now midst the first he seems,
Patriot by force, and courtisan[D] by craft;
Quick without wit, and violent without strengthвҒ вҖ”
A disappointed Lawyer, at full length.

VII

вҖңA strange example of the force of Law,
And hasty temper on a kindling mindвҒ вҖ”
Are these the dreams his young Ambition saw?
Poor fellow! he had better far been blind!
IвҖҷm sorry thus to probe a wound so rawвҒ вҖ”
But, then, as Bard my duty to Mankind,
For warning to the rest, compels these rapsвҒ вҖ”
As Geographers lay down a Shoal in Maps.вҖқ

[[A] For BroughamвҖҷs Fabian tactics with regard to duelling, vide post, Canto XIII. stanza lxxxiv. line 1, p. 506, note 1.]

[[B] Vide post, Canto XIII. stanza lxxxiv. line 1, p. 506, note 1.]

[[C] For вҖңCaptain Bobadill, a PaulвҖҷs man,вҖқ see Ben JonsonвҖҷs Every Man in his Humour, act iv. sc. 5, et passim.]

[[D] The N. Eng. Dict., quotes a passage in Phil. Trans., iv. 286 (1669), as the latest instance of вҖңcourtisanвҖқ for вҖңcourtier.вҖқ]

Note to the Annexed Stanzas on Brougham.

вҖңDistrusted by the Democracy, disliked by the Whigs, and detested by the Tories, too much of a lawyer for the people, and too much of a demagogue for Parliament, a contestor of counties, and a Candidate for cities, the refuse of half the Electors of England, and representative at last upon sufferance of the proprietor of some rotten borough, which it would have been more independent to have purchased, a speaker upon all questions, and the outcast of all parties, his support has become alike formidable to all his enemies (for he has no friends), and his vote can be only valuable when accompanied by his Silence. A disappointed man with a bad temper, he is endowed with considerable but not first-rate abilities, and has blundered on through life, remarkable only for a fluency, in which he has many rivals at the bar and in the Senate, and an eloquence in which he has several Superiors. вҖҳWilling to wound and not afraid to strike, until he receives a blow in return, he has not yet betrayed any illegal ardour, or Irish alacrity, in accepting the defiances, and resenting the disgraceful terms which his proneness to evil-speaking have (sic) brought upon him. In the cases of Mackinnon and Manners,[E] he sheltered himself behind those parliamentary privileges, which Fox, Pitt, Canning, Castlereagh, Tierney, Adam, Shelburne, Grattan, Corry, Curran, and Clare disdained to adopt as their buckler. The House of Commons became the Asylum of his Slander, as the Churches of Rome were once the Sanctuary of Assassins.

вҖңHis literary reputation (with the exception of one work of his early career) rests upon some anonymous articles imputed to him in a celebrated periodical work; but even these are surpassed by the Essays of others in the same Journal. He has tried every thing and succeeded in nothing; and he may perhaps finish as a Lawyer without practice, as he has already been occasionally an orator without an audience, if not soon cut short in his career.

вҖңThe above character is not written impartially, but by one who has had occasion to know some of the baser parts of it, and regards him accordingly with shuddering abhorrence, and just so much fear as he deserves. In him is to be dreaded the crawling of the centipede, not the spring of the tigerвҒ вҖ”the venom of the reptile, not the strength of the animalвҒ вҖ”the rancour of the miscreant, not the courage of the Man.

вҖңIn case the prose or verse of the above should be actionable, I put my name, that the man may rather proceed against me than the publisherвҒ вҖ”not without some faint hope that the brand with which I blast him may induce him, however reluctantly, to a manlier revenge.вҖқ

Extract from Letter to Murray.

вҖңI enclose you the stanzas which were intended for 1st Canto, after the line

вҖҳWho to Madrid on purpose made a journey:вҖҷ

but I do not mean them for present publication, because I will not, at this distance, publish that of a Man, for which he has a claim upon another too remote to give him redress.

вҖңWith regard to the Miscreant Brougham, however, it was only long after the fact, and I was made acquainted with the language he had held of me on my leaving England (with regard to the Dss of D.вҖҷs house),[F] and his letter to Me. de StaГ«l, and various matters for all of which the first time he and I foregatherвҒ вҖ”be it in England, be it on earthвҒ вҖ”he shall account, and one of the two be carried home.

вҖңAs I have no wish to have mysteries, I merely prohibit the publication of these stanzas in print, for the reasons of fairness mentioned; but I by no means wish him not to know their existence or their tenor, nor my intentions as to himself: he has shown no forbearance, and he shall find none. You may show them to him and to all whom it may concern, with the explanation that the only reason that I have not had satisfaction of this man has been, that I have never had an opportunity since I was aware of the facts, which my friends had carefully concealed from me; and it was only by slow degrees, and by piecemeal, that I got at them. I have not sought him, nor gone out of my way for him; but I will find him, and then we can have it out: he has shown so little courage, that he must fight at last in his absolute necessity to escape utter degradation.

вҖңI send you the stanzas, which (except the last) have been written nearly two years, merely because I have been lately copying out most of the MSS. which were in my drawers.вҖқ

[E] [Possibly George Manners (1778вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1853), editor of The Satirist, whose appointment to a foreign consulate Brougham sharply criticized in the House of Commons, July 9, 1817 (Parl. Deb., vol. xxxvi. pp. 1320, 1321); and Daniel Mackinnon (1791вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1836), the nephew of Henry Mackinnon, who fell at Ciudad Rodrigo. Byron met вҖңDanвҖқ Mackinnon at Lisbon in 1809, and (Gronow, Reminiscences, 1889, ii. 259, 260) was amused by his вҖңvarious funny stories.вҖқ]

[F] [ByronвҖҷs town-house, in 1815вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1816, No.В 13, Piccadilly, belonged to the Duchess of Devonshire. When he went abroad in April, 1816, the rent was still unpaid. The duchess, through her agent, distrained, but was unable to recover the debt. See ByronвҖҷs вҖңLetter to Elizabeth, Duchess of Devonshire,вҖқ November 3, 1817, Letters, 1900, iv. 178.] вҶ©

Julia was sent into a nunnery,
And there, perhaps, her feelings may be better.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. M.]

вҶ©

ManвҖҷs love is of his lifeвҒ вҖ”.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. M.]

вҶ©

[вҖңQue les hommes sont heureux dвҖҷaller Г  la guerre, dвҖҷexposer leur vie, de se livrer Г  lвҖҷenthousiasme de lвҖҷhonneur et du danger! Mais il nвҖҷy a rien au-dehors qui soulage les femmes.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Corinne, ou LвҖҷItalie, Madame de StaГ«l, liv., xviii. chap. v. ed. 1835, iii. 209.] вҶ©

To mourn alone the love which has undone.

or,

To lift our fatal love to God from man.

Take that which, of these three, seems the best prescription.вҒ вҖ”B. вҶ©

You will proceed in beauty and in pride,
You will returnвҒ вҖ”.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. M.]

вҶ©

Or,

That word is fatal now
lost for me
deadly nowвҒ вҖ”but let it go.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. M.]

вҶ©

I struggle, but can not collect my mind.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

As turns the needle trembling to the pole
It neвҖҷer can reachвҒ вҖ”so turns to you my soul.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

With a neat crow-quill, rather hard, but new.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[Byron had a seal bearing this motto.] вҶ©

And there are other incidents remaining
Which shall be specified in fitting time,
With good discretion, and in current rhyme.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

To newspapers, to sermons, which the zeal
Of pious men have published on his acts.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

IвҖҷll call the work вҖңReflections oвҖҷer a Bottle.вҖқ

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[Here, and elsewhere in Don Juan, Byron attacked Coleridge fiercely and venomously, because he believed that his protГ©gГ© had accepted patronage and money, and, notwithstanding, had retailed scandalous statements to the detriment and dishonour of his advocate and benefactor (see letter to Murray, November 24, 1818, Letters, 1900, iv. 272; and вҖңIntroduction to the Vision of Judgment,вҖқ Poetical Works, 1901, iv. 475). Byron does not substantiate his charge of ingratitude, and there is nothing to show whether Coleridge ever knew why a once friendly countenance was changed towards him. He might have asked, with the Courtenays, Ubi lapsus, quid feci? If Byron had been on his mind or his conscience he would have drawn up an elaborate explanation or apology; but nothing of the kind is extant. He took the abuse as he had taken the favoursвҒ вҖ”for the unmerited gifts of the blind goddess Fortune. (See, too, LetterвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰвҖҠ, by John Bull, 1821, p. 14.)] вҶ©

[Compare ByronвҖҷs вҖңLetter to the Editor of My GrandmotherвҖҷs Review,вҖқ Letters, 1900, iv. Appendix VII. 465вҒ вҖ“вҒ 470; and letter to Murray, August 24, 1819, ibid., p. 348: вҖңI wrote to you by last post, enclosing a buffooning letter for publication, addressed to the buffoon Roberts, who has thought proper to tie a canister to his own tail. It was written off-hand, and in the midst of circumstances not very favourable to facetiousness, so that there may, perhaps, be more bitterness than enough for that sort of small acid punch.вҖқ The letter was in reply to a criticism of Don Juan (Cantos I., II.) in the British Review (No. xxvii., 1819, vol. 14, pp. 266вҒ вҖ“вҒ 268), in which the Editor assumed, or feigned to assume, that the accusation of bribery was to be taken au grand sГ©rieux.] вҶ©

[Hor., Od. III. C. xiv. lines 27, 28.] вҶ©

I thought of dyeing it the other day.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[Compare Childe Harold, Canto III. stanza cvii. line 2.] вҶ©

вҖңMe nec femina, nec puer
Jam, nec spes animi credula mutui,
Nec certare juvat mero;
Nec vincire novis tempora floribus.вҖқ

Hor., Od. IV. i. 30.

[In the revise the words nec puer Jam were omitted. On this Hobhouse comments, вҖңBetter add the whole or scratch out all after femina.вҖқвҒ вҖ”вҖңQuote the whole thenвҒ вҖ”it was only in compliance with your settentrionale notions that I left out the remnant of the line.вҖқвҒ вҖ”[B.]] вҶ©

[For вҖңHow Fryer Bacon made a Brazen head to speak,вҖқ see The Famous Historie of Fryer Bacon (Reprint, London, 1815, pp. 13вҒ вҖ“вҒ 18); see, too, Friar Bacon and Friar Bungay, by Robert Greene, ed. Rev. Alexander Dyce, 1861, pp. 153вҒ вҖ“вҒ 181.] вҶ©

[вҖңAh! who can tell how hard it is to climb
The steep where FameвҖҷs proud temple shines afar?вҖқ etc.

BeattieвҖҷs Minstrel, Bk. I. stanza i. lines 1, 2.]

вҶ©

A bookвҒ вҖ”a damned bad pictureвҒ вҖ”and worse bust.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

[вҖңDonвҖҷt swear againвҒ вҖ”the third вҖҳdamn.вҖҷвҖҠвҖқвҒ вҖ”[H.]вҒ вҖ”[Revise.]] вҶ©

[Byron sat for his bust to Thorwaldsen, in May, 1817.] вҶ©

[This stanza appears to have been suggested by the following passage in the Quarterly Review, April, 1818, vol. xix. p. 203: вҖң[It was] the opinion of the Egyptians, that the soul never deserted the body while the latter continued in a perfect state. To secure this union, King Cheops is said, by Herodotus, to have employed three hundred and sixty thousand of his subjects for twenty years in raising over the вҖҳangusta domusвҖҷ destined to hold his remains, a pile of stone equal in weight to six millions of tons, which is just three times that of the vast Breakwater thrown across Plymouth Sound; and, to render this precious dust still more secure, the narrow chamber was made accessible only by small, intricate passages, obstructed by stones of an enormous weight, and so carefully closed externally as not to be perceptible.вҒ вҖ”Yet, how vain are all the precautions of man! Not a bone was left of Cheops, either in the stone coffin, or in the vault, when Shaw entered the gloomy chamber.] вҶ©

Must bid you both farewell in accents bland.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[Lines 1вҒ вҖ“вҒ 4 are taken from the last stanza of the Epilogue to the Lay of the Laureate, entitled вҖңLвҖҷEnvoy.вҖқ (See Poetical Works of Robert Southey, 1838, x. 174.)] вҶ©

Begun at Venice, December 13, 1818,-finished January 20, 1819. вҶ©

Lost that most precious stone of stonesвҒ вҖ”his modesty.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[Compare вҖңThe Girl of Cadiz,вҖқ Poetical Works, 1900, iii. 1, and note 1. вҶ©

But dвҒ вёәвҒ n me if I ever saw the like.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

FazzioliвҒ вҖ”literally, little handkerchiefsвҒ вҖ”the veils most availing of St.В Mark.

[вҖңI fazzioli, or kerchiefs (a white kind of veil which the lower orders wear upon their heads).вҖқвҒ вҖ”Letter to Rogers, March 3, 1818, Letters, 1900, iv. 208.] вҶ©

Their manners mending, and their morals curing.
She taught them to suppress their viceвҒ вҖ”and urine.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[CompareвҒ вҖ”

вҖңAnd fast the white rocks faded from his view
вӢ®
And then, it may be, of his wish to roam
Repented he.вҖқ

Childe Harold, Canto I. stanza xii. lines 3вҒ вҖ“вҒ 6, Poetical Works, 1898, i. 24.]

вҶ©

[вҖңTo breathe a veinвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ to lance it so as to let blood.вҖқ CompareвҒ вҖ”

Rosalind | Is the fool sick?
Biron | Sick at heart.
Ros | Alack, let it blood.вҖқ

LoveвҖҷs LabourвҖҷs Lost, act ii. sc. I, line 185.]

вҶ©

Sea-sickness death; then pardon JuanвҒ вҖ”how else
Keep down his stomach neвҖҷer at sea before?

вҖ”вҒ [MS. M.]

вҶ©

[вҖңWith regard to the charges about the Shipwreck, I think that I told you and Mr.В Hobhouse, years ago, that there was not a single circumstance of it not taken from fact: not, indeed, from any single shipwreck, but all from actual facts of different wrecks.вҖқвҒ вҖ” Letter to Murray, August 23, 1821. In the Monthly Magazine, vol. liii. (August, 1821, pp. 19вҒ вҖ“вҒ 22, and September, 1821, pp. 105вҒ вҖ“вҒ 109), ByronвҖҷs indebtedness to Sir G. DalzellвҖҷs Shipwrecks and Disasters at Sea (1812, 8vo) is pointed out, and the parallel passages are printed in full.] вҶ©

[вҖңNight came on worse than the day had been; and a sudden shift of wind, about midnight, threw the ship into the trough of the sea, which struck her aft, tore away the rudder, started the stern-post, and shattered the whole of her stern-frame. The pumps were immediately sounded, and in the course of a few minutes the water had increased to four feet.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ

вҖңOne gang was instantly put on them, and the remainder of the people employed in getting up rice from the run of the ship, and heaving it over, to come at the leak, if possible. After three or four hundred bags were thrown into the sea, we did get at it, and found the water rushing into the ship with astonishing rapidity; therefore we thrust sheets, shirts, jackets, tales of muslin, and everything of the like description that could be got, into the opening.

вҖңNotwithstanding the pumps discharged fifty tons of water an hour, the ship certainly must have gone down, had not our expedients been attended with some success. The pumps, to the excellent construction of which I owe the preservation of my life, were made by Mr.В Mann of London. As the next day advanced, the weather appeared to moderate, the men continued incessantly at the pumps, and every exertion was made to keep the ship afloat.вҖңвҒ вҖ”See вҖңLoss of the American ship Hercules, Captain Benjamin Stout, June 16, 1796,вҖқ Shipwrecks and Disasters at Sea, 1812, iii. 316, 317.] вҶ©

[вҖңScarce was this done, when a gust, exceeding in violence everything of the kind I had ever seen, or could conceive, laid the ship on her beam ends.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ

вҖңThe ship lay motionless, and, to all appearance, irrevocably overset.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ The water forsook the hold, and appeared between decks.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ

вҖңImmediate directions were given to cut away the main and mizen masts, trusting when the ship righted, to be able to wear her. On cutting one or two lanyards, the mizen-mast went first over, but without producing the smallest effect on the ship, and, on cutting the lanyard of one shroud, the main-mast followed. I had next the mortification to see the foremast and bowsprit also go over. On this, the ship immediately righted with great violence.вҖқвҒ вҖ”вҖңLoss of the Centaur Man-of-War, 1782, by Captain Inglefield,вҖқ Shipwrecks and Disasters at Sea, 1812, iii. 41.] вҶ©

Perhaps the whole would have got drunk, but for.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[вҖңA midshipman was appointed to guard the spirit-room, to repress that unhappy desire of a devoted crew to die in a state of intoxication. The sailors, though in other respects orderly in conduct, here pressed eagerly upon him.

вҖңвҖҳGive us some grog,вҖҷ they exclaimed, вҖҳit will be all one an hour hence.вҖҷвҒ вҖ”вҖҳI know we must die,вҖҷ replied the gallant officer, coolly, вҖҳbut let us die like men!вҖҳвҒ вҖ”Armed with a brace of pistols, he kept his post, even while the ship was sinking.вҖқвҒ вҖ”вҖңLoss of the Earl of Abergavenny, February 5, 1805,вҖқ Shipwrecks and Disasters at Sea, 1812, iii. 418. John Wordsworth, the poetвҖҷs brother, was captain of the Abergavenny. See Life of William Wordsworth, by Professor Knight, 1889, i. 370вҒ вҖ“вҒ 380; see, too, ColeridgeвҖҷs Anima PoetГҰ, 1895, p. 132. For a contemporary report, see a Maltese paper, Il Cartaginense, April 17, 1805.] вҶ©

[вҖңHowever, by great exertions of the chain-pumps, we held our own.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ All who were not seamen by profession, had been employed in thrumming a sail which was passed under the shipвҖҷs bottom, and I thought had some effect.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ

вҖңThe Centaur laboured so much, that I could scarce hope she would swim till morning:вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ our sufferings for want of water were very great.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ

вҖңThe weather again threatened, and by noon it blew a storm. The ship laboured greatly; the water appeared in the fore and after-hold. I was informed by the carpenter also that the leathers were nearly consumed, and the chains of the pumps, by constant exertion, and friction of the coils, were rendered almost useless.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ

вҖңAt this period the carpenter acquainted me that the well was stove inвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ and the chain-pumps displaced and totally useless.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ Seeing their efforts useless, many of them [the people] burst into tears, and wept like children.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ

вҖңI perceived the ship settling by the head.вҖңвҒ вҖ”вҖңLoss of the Centaur,вҖқ Shipwrecks and Disasters at Sea, 1812, iii. pp. 45вҒ вҖ“вҒ 49.] вҶ©

вҖҳT is ugly dying in the Gulf of Lyons.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[Byron may have had in mind the story of the half-inaudible vow of a monster wax candle, to be offered to St.В Christopher of Paris, which Erasmus tells in his Naufragium. The passage is scored with a pencil-mark in his copy of the Colloquies.] вҶ©

[Stanza xliv. recalls Cardinal de RetzвҖҷs description of the storm at sea in the Gulf of Lyons: вҖңEverybody were at their prayers, or were confessing themselves.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ The private captain of the galley caused, in the greatest height of the danger, his embroidered coat and his red scarf to be brought to him, saying, that a true Spaniard ought to die bearing his KingвҖҷs Marks of distinction. He sat himself down in a great elbow chair, and with his foot struck a poor Neapolitan in the chops, who, not being able to stand upon the Coursey of the Galley, was crawling along, crying out aloud, вҖҳSennor Don Fernando, por lвҖҷamor de Dios, Confession.вҖҷ The captain, when he struck him, said to him, вҖҳInimigo de Dios piedes Confession!вҖҷ And as I was representing to him, that his inference was not right, he said that that old man gave offence to the whole galley. You canвҖҷt imagine the horror of a great storm; you can as little imagine the Ridicule mixed with it. A Sicilian Observantine monk was preaching at the foot of the great mast, that St.В Francis had appeared to him, and had assured him that we should not perish. I should never have done, should I undertake to describe all the ridiculous frights that are seen on these occasions.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Memoirs of Cardinal de Retz, 1723, iii. 353.] вҶ©

[вҖңSome appeared perfectly resigned, went to their hammocks, and desired their messmates to lash them in; others were securing themselves to gratings and small rafts; but the most predominant idea was that of putting on their best and cleanest clothes. The boatsвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ were got over the side.вҖқвҒ вҖ”вҖңLoss of the Centaur,вҖқ Shipwrecks and Disasters at Sea, 1812, iii. 49, 50.] вҶ©

Men will prove hungry, even when next perdition.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[вҖңEight bags of rice, six casks of water, and a small quantity of salted beef and pork, were put into the long-boat, as provisions for the whole.вҖқвҒ вҖ”вҖңWreck of the Sidney, 1806,вҖқ Shipwrecks and Disasters at Sea, 1812, iii. 434.] вҶ©

[вҖңThe yawl was stove alongside and sunk.вҖқвҒ вҖ”вҖңLoss of the Centaur,вҖқ ibid., iii. 50.] вҶ©

[вҖңOne oar was erected for a main-mast, and the other broke to the breadth of the blankets for a yard.вҖқвҒ вҖ”вҖңLoss of the Duke William Transport, 1758,вҖқ ibid., ii. 387.] вҶ©

Which being withdrawn, discloses but the frown.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

Of one who hates us, so the night was shown
And grimly darkled oвҖҷer their faces pale,
And hopeless eyes, which oвҖҷer the deep alone
Gazed dim and desolateвҒ вҖ”.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[вҖңAs rafts had been mentioned by the carpenter, I thought it right to make the attempt.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ It was impossible for any man to deceive himself with the hopes of being saved on a raft in such a sea.вҖқвҒ вҖ”вҖңLoss of the Centaur,вҖқ Shipwrecks and Disasters at Sea, 1812, iii. 50. 51.] вҶ©

[вҖңSpars, booms, hencoops, and every thing buoyant, was therefore cast loose, that the men might have some chance to save themselves.вҖқвҒ вҖ”вҖңLoss of the Pandora,вҖқ ibid., iii. 197.] вҶ©

[вҖңWe had scarce quitted the ship, when she gave a heavy lurch to port, and then went down, head foremost.вҖңвҒ вҖ”вҖңLoss of the Lady Hobart,вҖқ ibid., iii. 378.] вҶ©

[вҖңAt this moment, one of the officers told the captain that she was going downвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ and bidding him farewell, leapt overboard:вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ the crew had just time to leap overboard, which they did, uttering a most dreadful yell.вҖқвҒ вҖ”вҖңLoss of the Pandora,вҖқ ibid., iii. 198.] вҶ©

[вҖңThe boat, being fastened to the rigging, was no sooner cleared of the greatest part of the water, than a dog of mine came to me running along the gunwale. I took him in.вҖқвҒ вҖ”вҖңShipwreck of the Sloop Betsy, on the Coast of Dutch Guiana, August 5, 1756 (Philip Aubin, Commander),вҖқ Remarkable Shipwrecks, Hartford, 1813, p. 175.] вҶ©

[Qy. вҖңMy good Sir! when the sea runs very high this is the case, as I know, but if my authority is not enough, see BlighвҖҷs account of his run to Timor, after being cut adrift by the mutineers headed by Christian.вҖқвҒ вҖ”[B.]

вҖңPray tell me who was the Lubber who put the query? surely not you, Hobhouse! We have both of us seen too much of the sea for that. You may rely on my using no nautical word not founded on authority, and no circumstances not grounded in reality.вҖқ] вҶ©

[вҖңIt blew a violent storm, and the sea ran very high, so that between the seas the sail was becalmed; and when on the top of the sea, it was too much to have set, but I was obliged to carry it, for we were now in very imminent danger and distress; the sea curling over the stern of the boat, which obliged us to bale with all our might.вҖқвҒ вҖ”A Narrative of the Mutiny of the Bounty, by William Bligh, 1790, p. 23.] вҶ©

[вҖңBefore it was dark, a blanket was discovered in the boat. This was immediately bent to one of the stretchers, and under it, as a sail, we scudded all night, in expectation of being swallowed up by every wave.вҖңвҒ вҖ”вҖңLoss of the Centaur,вҖқ Shipwrecks and Disasters at Sea, 1812, iii. 52.] вҶ©

[вҖңThe sun rose very fiery and red, a sure indication of a severe gale of wind.вҒ вҖ”We could do nothing more than keep before the sea.вҒ вҖ”I now served a tea-spoonful of rum to each person,вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ with a quarter of a bread-fruit, which was scarce eatable, for dinner.вҖқвҒ вҖ”A Narrative, etc., by W. Bligh, 1790, pp. 23, 24.] вҶ©

[вҖң[As] our lodgings were very miserable and confined, I had only in my power to remedy the latter defect, by putting ourselves at watch and watch; so that one half always sat up, while the other half lay down on the boatвҖҷs bottom, with nothing to cover us but the heavens.вҖқвҒ вҖ”A Narrative of the Mutiny of the Bounty, by William Bligh, 1790, p. 28.] вҶ©

[For ByronвҖҷs debts to Mrs.В Massingberd, вҖңJewвҖқ King, etc., and for money raised on annuities, see Letters, 1898, ii. 174, note 2, and letter to Hanson, December 11, 1817, Letters, 1900, iv. 187, вҖңThe list of annuities sent by Mr.В Kinnaird, including Jews and Sawbridge, amounts to twelve thousand eight hundred and some odd pounds.вҖқ] вҶ©

[вҖңThe third day we began to suffer exceedinglyвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ from hunger and thirst. I then seized my dog, and plunged the knife in his throat. We caught his blood in the hat, receiving in our hands and drinking what ran over; we afterwards drank in turn out of the hat, and felt ourselves refreshed.вҖқвҒ вҖ”вҖңShipwreck of the Betsy,вҖқ Remarkable Shipwrecks, Hartford, 1813, p. 177.] вҶ©

[вҖңOne day, when I was at home in my hut with my Indian dog, a party came to my door, and told me their necessities were such that they must eat the creature or starve. Though their plea was urgent, I could not help using some arguments to endeavour to dissuade them from killing him, as his faithful services and fondness deserved it at my hands; but, without weighing my arguments, they took him away by force and killed him.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ Three weeks after that I was glad to make a meal of his paws and skin which, upon recollecting the spot where they had killed him, I found thrown aside and rotten.вҖқвҒ вҖ”The Narrative of the Honourable John Byron, etc., 1768, pp. 47, 48.] вҶ©

[Being driven to distress for want of food, вҖңthey soaked their shoes, and two hairy caps in water; and when sufficiently softened ate portions of the leather.вҖқ But day after day having passed, and the cravings of hunger pressing hard upon them, they fell upon the horrible and dreadful expedient of eating each other; and in order to prevent any contention about who should become the food of the others, вҖңthey cast lots to determine the sufferer.вҖқвҒ вҖ”вҖңSufferings of the Crew of the Thomas [Twelve Men in an Open Boat, 1797],вҖқ Shipwrecks and Disasters at Sea, 1812, iii 356.] вҶ©

[вҖңThe lots were drawn: вҖҳthe captain, summoning all his strength, wrote upon slips of paper the name of each man, folded them up, put them into a hat, and shook them together. The crew, meanwhile, preserved an awful silence; each eye was fixed and each mouth open, while terror was strongly impressed upon every countenance.вҖҷ The unhappy person, with manly fortitude, resigned himself to his miserable associates.вҖқвҒ вҖ”вҖңFamine in the American Ship Peggy, 1765,вҖқ Remarkable Shipwrecks, Hartford, 1813, pp. 358, 359.] вҶ©

[вҖңHe requested to be bled to death, the surgeon being with them, and having his case of instruments in his pocket when he quitted the vessel.вҖқвҒ вҖ”вҖңSufferings of the Crew of the Thomas,вҖқ Shipwrecks, etc., 1812, iii. 357.] вҶ©

[вҖңYet scarce was the vein divided when the operator, applying his own parched lips, drank the stream as it flowed, and his comrades anxiously watched the last breath of the victim, that they might prey upon his flesh.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Shipwrecks and Disasters at Sea, 1812, iii. 357.] вҶ©

[вҖңThose who indulged their cannibal appetite to excess speedily perished in raging madness,вҖқ etc.вҒ вҖ”Ibid.] вҶ©

[вҖңAnother expedient we had frequent recourse to, on finding it supplied our mouths with temporary moisture, was chewing any substance we could find, generally a bit of canvas, or even lead.вҖқвҒ вҖ”вҖңThe Shipwreck of the Juno on the Coast of Aracan,вҖқ 1795, Shipwrecks and Disasters at Sea, 1812, iii. 270.] вҶ©

[вҖңAt noon, some noddies came so near to us that one of them was caught by hand.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ I divided it into eighteen portions. In the evening we saw several boobies.вҖқвҒ вҖ”A Narrative of the Mutiny of the Bounty, by William Bligh, 1790, p. 41.] вҶ©

[вҖңQuandвҖҷ ebbe detto ciГІ, con gli occhi torti
Riprese il teschio misero coi denti,
Che furo allвҖҷ osso, come dвҖҷun can forti.вҖқ

Dante, Inferno, canto xxxiii. lines 76вҒ вҖ“вҒ 78.]

вҶ©

[вҖңWhenever a heavy shower afforded us a few mouthfuls of fresh water, either by catching the drops as they fell or by squeezing them out of our clothes, it infused new life and vigour into us, and for a while we had almost forgot our misery.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Shipwrecks and Disasters at Sea, 1812, iii. 270. Compare The Island, Canto I. stanza ix. lines 193, 194, Poetical Works, 1901, v. 595.] вҶ©

[CompareвҒ вҖ”

вҖңWith throats unslaked, with black lips baked.вҖқ

Ancient Mariner, Part III. line 157.]

вҶ©

[вҖңMr.В WadeвҖҷs boy, a stout healthy lad, died early, and almost without a groan; while another, of the same age, but of a less promising appearance, held out much longer. Their fathers were both in the fore-top, when the boys were taken ill. [Wade], hearing of his sonвҖҷs illness, answered, with indifference, that he could do nothing for him, and left him to his fate.вҖқвҒ вҖ”вҖңNarrative of the Shipwreck of the Juno, 1795,вҖқ Shipwrecks and Disasters at Sea, 1812, iii. 273.] вҶ©

[вҖңThe other [Father] hurried down.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ By that time only three or four planks of the quarter-deck remained, just over the quarter gallery. To this spot the unhappy man led his son, making him fast to the rail, to prevent his being washed away.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Ibid.] вҶ©

[вҖңWhenever the boy was seized with a fit of retching, the father lifted him up and wiped away the foam from his lips; and if a shower came, he made him open his mouth to receive the drops, or gently squeezed them into it from a rag.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Ibid.] вҶ©

[вҖңIn this affecting situation both remained four or five days, till the boy expired. The unfortunate parent, as if unwilling to believe the fact, raised the body, looked wistfully at it, and when he could no longer entertain any doubt, watched it in silence until it was carried off by sea; then wrapping himself in a piece of canvas, sunk down, and rose no more; though he must have lived two days longer, as we judged from the quivering of his limbs when a wave broke over him.вҖқвҒ вҖ”вҖңNarrative of the Shipwreck of the Juno, 1795,вҖқ Shipwrecks and Disasters at Sea, p. 274.] вҶ©

[вҖңAbout this time a beautiful white bird, web-footed, and not unlike a dove in size and plumage, hovered over the mast-head of the cutter, and, notwithstanding the pitching of the boat, frequently attempted to perch on it, and continued fluttering there till dark. Trifling as such an incident may appear, we all considered it a propitious omen.вҖқвҒ вҖ”вҖңLoss of the Lady Hobart, 1803,вҖқ Shipwrecks and Disasters at Sea, 1812, iii. 389.] вҶ©

[вҖңI found it necessary to caution the people against being deceived by the appearance of land, or calling out till we were quite convinced of its reality, more especially as fog-banks are often mistaken for land: several of the poor fellows nevertheless repeatedly exclaimed they heard breakers, and some the firing of guns.вҖқвҒ вҖ”вҖңLoss of the Lady Hobart,вҖқ Shipwrecks and Disasters at Sea, 1812, iii. 391.] вҶ©

[вҖңAt length one of them broke out into a most immoderate swearing fit of joy, which I could not restrain, and declared, that he had never seen land in his life, if what he now saw was not so.вҖқвҒ вҖ”вҖңLoss of the Centaur,вҖқ ibid., p. 55.] вҶ©

[вҖңThe joy at a speedy relief affected us all in a most remarkable way. Many burst into tears; some looked at each other with a stupid stare, as if doubtful of the reality of what they saw; while several were in such a lethargic condition, that no animating words could rouse them to exertion. At this affecting period, I proposed offering up our solemn thanks to Heaven for the miraculous deliverance.вҖқвҒ вҖ”вҖңLoss of the Lady Hobart,вҖқ ibid., p. 391.] вҶ©

[After having suffered the horrors of hunger and thirst for many days, вҖңthey accidentally descried a small turtle floating on the surface of the water asleep.вҖқвҒ вҖ”вҖңSufferings of the Crew of the Thomas,вҖқ ibid., p. 356.] вҶ©

[вҖңAn indifferent spectator would have been at a loss which most to admire; the eyes of famine sparkling at immediate relief, or the horror of their preservers at the sight of so many spectres, whose ghastly countenances, if the cause had been unknown, would rather have excited terror than pity. Our bodies were nothing but skin and bones, our limbs were full of sores, and we were clothed in rags.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Narrative of the Mutiny of the Bounty, by William Bligh, 1790, p. 80. Compare The Siege of Corinth, lines 1048, 1049, Poetical Works, 1900, iii. 494, note 3.] вҶ©

[вҖңThey discovered land right ahead, and steered for it. There being a very heavy surf, they endeavoured to turn the boatвҖҷs head to it, which, from weakness, they were unable to accomplish, and soon afterwards the boat upset.вҖқвҒ вҖ”вҖңSufferings of Six Deserters from St.В Helena, 1799,вҖқ Shipwrecks and Disasters at Sea, 1812, iii, 371.] вҶ©

[Compare lines вҖңWritten after swimming from Sestos to Abydos,вҖқ Poetical Works, 1900, iii. 13, note 1; see, too, Letters, 1898, i. 262, 263, note 1.] вҶ©

[CompareвҒ вҖ”

вҖңHow long in that same fit I lay
I have not to declare.вҖқ

The Ancient Mariner, Part V. lines 393, 394.]

вҶ©

вёәвҒ in short sheвҖҷs one.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

A set of humbug rascals, when allвҖҷs doneвҒ вҖ”
IвҖҷve seen much finer women, ripe and real,
Than all the nonsense of their dвҒ вёәвҒ d ideal.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[Compare Childe Harold, Canto IV. stanza 1. lines 6вҒ вҖ“вҒ 9, Poetical Works, 1899, ii. 366, note 1.] вҶ©

[Probably that вҖңAlpha and Omega of Beauty,вҖқ Lady Adelaide Forbes (daughter of George, sixth Earl of Granard), whom Byron compared to the Apollo Belvidere. See Letters, 1898, ii. 230, note 3.] вҶ©

[вҖңThe saya or basquiГұaвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ the outer petticoatвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ is always black, and is put over the indoor dress on going out.вҖқ Compare ОңОөО»ОұОҪОөОҜОјОҝОҪОөПӮ бј…ПҖОұОҪП„ОөПӮ П„бҪё ПҖО»ОӯОҝОҪ бјҗОҪ ПғО¬ОіОҝО№ПӮ, Strabo, lib. iii. ed. 1807, i. 210. FordвҖҷs Handbook for Spain, 1855, i. 111.] вҶ©

[вҖңWhen Ajax, Ulysses, and Phoenix stand before Achilles, he rushes forth to greet them, brings them into the tent, directs Patroclus to mix the wine, cuts up the meat, dresses it, and sets it before the ambassadors.вҖқ (Iliad, ix. 193, sq.)вҒ вҖ”Study of the Classics, by H.N. Coleridge, 1830, p, 71] вҶ©

And such a bed of furs, and a pelisse.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

вёәвҒ which often spread,
And come like opening Hell upon the mind,
No вҖңbaseless fabricвҖқ but вҖңa wrack behind.вҖқ

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

Had eвҖҷer escaped more dangers on the deep;вҒ вҖ”
And those who are not drowned, at least may sleep.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[Entitled вҖңA Narrative of the Honourable John Byron (Commodore in a late expedition round the world), containing an account of the great distresses suffered by himself and his companions on the coast of Patagonia, from the year 1740, till their arrival in England, 1746. Written by Himself,вҖқ London, 1768, 40. For the Hon.В John Byron, 1723вҒ вҖ“вҒ 86, younger brother of William, fifth Lord Byron, see Letters, 1898, i. 3.] вҶ©

Wore for a husbandвҒ вҖ”or some such like brute.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

вёәвҒ although of late
IвҖҷve changed, for some few years, the day to night.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[The second canto of Don Juan was finished in January, 1819, when the Venetian Carnival was at its height.] вҶ©

[Strabo (lib. xvi. ed. 1807, p. 1106) gives various explanations of the name, assigning the supposed redness to the refraction of the rays of the vertical sun; or to the shadow of the scorched mountain-sides which form its shores; or, as Ctesias would have it, to a certain fountain which discharged red oxide of lead into its waters. вҖңAbyssinianвҖқ Bruce had no doubt that вҖңlarge trees or plants of coral spread everywhere over the bottom,вҖқ made the sea вҖңred,вҖқ and accounted for the name. But, according to Niebuhr, the Red Sea is the Sea of Edom, which, being interpreted, is вҖңRed.вҖқ] вҶ©

вёәвҒ just the same
As at this moment I should like to do;вҒ вҖ”
But I have done with kissesвҒ вҖ”having kissed
All those that wouldвҒ вҖ”regretting those I missed.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

Fair as the rose just plucked to crown the wreath,
Soft as the unfledged birdling when at rest.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[Compare Mazeppa, lines 829, sq., Poetical Works, 1901, iv. 232.] вҶ©

That finer melody was never heard,
The kind of sound whose echo is a tear,
Whose accents are the steps of MusicвҖҷs throne.[*]

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

[*] [вҖңTo the Publisher. Take of these varieties which is thought best. I have no choice.вҖқ] вҶ©

[Moore, quoting from memory from one of ByronвҖҷs MS. journals, says that he speaks of вҖңmaking earnest love to the younger of his fair hostesses at Seville, with the help of a dictionary.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Life, p. 93. See, too, letter to his mother, August 11, 1809, Letters, 1898, i. 240.] вҶ©

Pressure of hands, et ceteraвҒ вҖ”or a kiss.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. Alternative reading.]

вҶ©

Italian rather more, having more teachers.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[вҖңIn 1813вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ in the fashionable world of London, of which I then formed an item, a fraction, the segment of a circle, the unit of a million, the nothing of something.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ I had been the lion of 1812.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Extracts from a Diary, January 19, 1821, Letters, 1901, v. 177, 178.] вҶ©

foes, friends, sex, kind, are nothing more to me
Than a mere dream of something oвҖҷer the sea.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[For the same archaism or blunder, compare Manfred, act i. sc. 4, line 19, Poetical Works, 1901, iv. 132.] вҶ©

[Compare The Prisoner of Chillon, line 78, ibid., p. 16.] вҶ©

Holding her sweet breath oвҖҷer his cheek and mouth,
As oвҖҷer a bed of roses, etc.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[Vide post, Canto XVI. stanza lxxxvi. line 6, p. 598, note 1.] вҶ©

For without heart Love is not quite so good;
Ceres is commissary to our bellies,
And Love, which also much depends on food:
While Bacchus will provide with wine and jelliesвҒ вҖ”
Oysters and eggs are also living food.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

He was her own, her Ocean lover, cast
To be her soulвҖҷs first idol, and its last.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

And saw the sunset and the rising moon.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[The MS. and the editions of 1819, 1823, 1828, read вҖңwoman.вҖқ The edition of 1833 reads вҖңwomen.вҖқ The text follows the MS. and the earlier editions.] вҶ©

[Compare stanza prefixed to Dedication, vide ante, p. 2.] вҶ©

[CompareвҒ вҖ”

вҖңYes! thy Sherbet to-night will sweetly flow,
See how it sparkles in its vase of snow!вҖқ

Corsair, Canto I. lines 427, 428, Poetical Works, 1900, iii. 242.]

вҶ©

A pleasure naught but drunkenness can bring:
For not the blest sherbet all chilled with snow.
Nor the full sparkle of the desert-spring,
Nor wine in all the purple of its glow.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

Spread like an Ocean, varied, vast, and bright.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

вёә IвҖҷm sure they never reckoned;
And being joinedвҒ вҖ”like swarming bees they clung,
And mixed until the very pleasure stung.

or,

And one was innocent, but both too young,
Their hearts the flowers, etc.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

In all the burning tongues the Passions teach
They had no further feeling, hope, nor care
Save one, and that was Love.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

Pillowed upon her beating heartвҒ вҖ”which panted
With the sweet memory of all it granted.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

Some drown themselves, some in the vices grovel.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[Lady Caroline LambвҖҷs Glenarvon was published in 1816. For ByronвҖҷs farewell letter of dismissal, which Lady Caroline embodied in her novel (vol. iii. chap. ix.), see Letters, 1898, ii. 135, note 1. According to Medwin (Conversations, 1824, p. 274), Madame de StaГ«l catechized Byron with regard to the relation of the story to fact.] вҶ©

In their sweet feelings holily united,
By Solitude (soft parson) they were wed.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[Titus forebore to marry вҖңIncestaвҖқ Berenice (see Juv., Sat. vi. 158), the daughter of Agrippa I., and wife of Herod, King of Chalcis, out of regard to the national prejudice against intermarriage with an alien.] вҶ©

[CГҰsarвҖҷs third wife, Pompeia, was suspected of infidelity with Clodius (see LanghorneвҖҷs Plutarch, 1838, p. 498); PompeyвҖҷs third wife, Mucia, intrigued with CГҰsar (vide ibid., p. 447); MahometвҖҷs favourite wife, Ayesha, on one occasion incurred suspicion; Antonina, the wife of Belisarius, was notoriously profligate (see GibbonвҖҷs Decline and Fall, 1825, iii. 432, 102).] вҶ©

[Compare Sardanapalus, act i. sc. 2, line 252, Poetical Works, 1901, v. 23, note 1.] вҶ©

вҖ”of ticklish dust.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. Alternative reading.]

вҶ©

[вҖңMr.В Hobhouse is at it again about indelicacy. There is no indelicacy. If he wants that, let him read Swift, his great idol; but his imagination must be a dunghill, with a viperвҖҷs nest in the middle, to engender such a supposition about this poem.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Letter to Murray, May 15, 1819, Letters, 1900, iv. 295.] вҶ©

Two hundred stanzas reckoned as before.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[November 30, 1819. Copied in 1820 (MS.D.). Moore (Life, 421) says that Byron was at work on the third canto when he stayed with him at Venice, in October, 1819. вҖңOne day, before dinner, [he] read me two or three hundred lines of it; beginning with the stanzas вҖңOh Wellington,вҖқ etc., which, at the time, formed the opening of the third canto, but were afterwards reserved for the commencement of the ninth.вҖқ The third canto, as it now stands, was completed by November 8, 1819; see Letters, 1900, iv. 375. The date on the MS. may refer to the first fair copy.] вҶ©

And fits her like a stocking or a glove.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. D.]

вҶ©

[вҖңOn peut trouver des femmes qui nвҖҷont jamais eu de galanterie, mais il est rare dвҖҷen trouver qui nвҖҷen aient jamais eu quвҖҷune.вҖқвҒ вҖ”RГ©flexionsвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ du Duc de la Rochefoucauld, No. lxxiii.

Byron prefixed the maxim as a motto to his вҖңOde to a Lady whose Lover was killed by a Ball, which at the same time shivered a Portrait next his Heart.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Poetical Works, 1901, iv. 552.] вҶ©

[Merchant of Venice, act iv. sc. 1, line 254.] вҶ©

Had PetrarchвҖҷs passion led to PetrarchвҖҷs wedding,
How many sonnets had ensued the bedding?

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[The Ballad of вҖңDeath and the LadyвҖқ was printed in a small volume, entitled A Guide to Heaven, 1736, 12mo. It is mentioned in The Vicar of Wakefield (chap. xvii.), Works of Oliver Goldsmith, 1854, i. 369. See Old English Popular Music, by William Chappell, F.S.A., 1893, ii. 170, 171.] вҶ©

[See The Prophecy of Dante, Canto I. lines 172вҒ вҖ“вҒ 174, Poetical Works, 1901, iv. 253, note 1.] вҶ©

MiltonвҖҷs first wife ran away from him within the first month. If she had not, what would John Milton have done?

[Mary Powell did not вҖңrun away,вҖқ but at the end of the honeymoon obtained her husbandвҖҷs consent to visit her family at Shotover, вҖңupon a promise of returning at Michaelmas.вҖқ вҖңAnd in the mean while his studies went on very vigorously; and his chief diversion, after the business of the day, was now and then in an evening to visit the Lady Margaret Lee.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ This lady, being a woman of excellent wit and understanding, had a particular honour for our author, and took great delight in his conversation; as likewise did her husband, Captain Hobson.вҖқ See, too, his sonnet вҖңTo the Lady Margaret Ley.вҖқвҒ вҖ”The Life of Milton (by Thomas Newton, D.D.), Paradise Regained, ed. (Baskerville), 1758, pp. xvii., xviii.] вҶ©

[вҖңYesterday a very pretty letter from Annabella.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ She is a poetessвҒ вҖ”a mathematicianвҒ вҖ”a metaphysician.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Journal November 30, 1813, Letters, 1898, ii. 357.] вҶ©

Displayed much more of nerve, perhaps, of wit,
Than any of the parodies of Pitt.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

вёәвҒ toothpicks, a bidet.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. Alternative reading.]

вҖңDr.В MurrayвҒ вҖ”As you are squeamish you may put вҖҳteapot, tray,вҖҷ in case the other piece of feminine furniture frightens you.вҒ вҖ”B.вҖқ вҶ©

[For ByronвҖҷs menagerie, see Werner, act i. sc. 1, line 216, Poetical Works, 1902, v. 348, note 1.] вҶ©

[вҖңBut as for canine recollectionsвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ I had one (half a wolf by the she-side) that doted on me at ten years old, and very nearly ate me at twenty. When I thought he was going to enact Argus, he bit away the backside of my breeches, and never would consent to any kind of recognition, in despite of all kinds of bones which I offered him.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Letter to Moore, January 19, 1815, Letters, 1899, iii. 171, 172. Compare, too, Childe Harold, Canto I. Song, stanza ix., Poetical Works, 1899, ii. 30.] вҶ©

Yet for all that donвҖҷt stay away too long,
A sofa, like a bed, may come by wrong.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

IвҖҷve known the friend betrayedвҒ вҖ”.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. D.]

вҶ©

[The Pyrrhic war-dance represented вҖңby rapid movements of the body, the way in which missiles and blows from weapons were avoided, and also the mode in which the enemy was attackedвҖқ (Dict. of Ant.). Dodwell (Tour through Greece, 1819, ii. 21, 22) observes that in Thessaly and Macedon dances are performed at the present day by men armed with their musket and sword. See, too, HobhouseвҖҷs description (Travels in Albania, 1858, i. 166, 167) of the Albanian war-dance at LoutrГЎki.] вҶ©

[вҖңTheir manner of dancing is certainly the same that Diana is sung to have danced on the banks of Eurotas. The great lady still leads the dance, and is followed by a troop of young girls, who imitate her steps, and, if she sings, make up the chorus. The tunes are extremely gay and lively, yet with something in them wonderfully soft. The steps are varied according to the pleasure of her that leads the dance, but always in exact time, and infinitely more agreeable than any of our dances.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Lady M.W. Montagu to Pope, April 1, O.S., 1817, Letters, etc., 1816, p. 138. The вҖңkerchief-wavingвҖқ dance is the Romaika. See The Waltz, line 125, Poetical Works, 1898, i. 492, note 1. See, too, Voyage PittoresqueвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ by the Comte de Choiseul-Gouffier, 1782, vol. i. Planche 33.] вҶ©

That would have set Tom Moore, though married, raving.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[вҖңUpon the whole, I think the part of Don Juan in which LambroвҖҷs return to his home, and Lambro himself are described, is the best, that is, the most individual, thing in all I know of Lord B.вҖҷs works. The festal abandonment puts one in mind of Nicholas PoussinвҖҷs pictures.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Table Talk of S.T. Coleridge, June 7, 1824.] вҶ©

[Compare Hudibras, Part I. canto iii. lines 1, 2вҒ вҖ”

вҖңAy me! what perils do environ
The man that meddles with cold iron!вҖқ

ByronвҖҷs friend, C.S. Matthews, shouted these lines, con intenzione, under the windows of a Cambridge tradesman named Hiron, who had been instrumental in the expulsion from the University of Sir Henry Smyth, a riotous undergraduate. (See letter to Murray, October 19, 1820.)] вҶ©

All had been open, heart, and open house,
Ever since Juan served her for a spouse.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[вҖңRispose allor Margutte: a dirtel tosto,
Io non credo piГ№ al nero chвҖҷ allвҖҷ azzurro;
Ma nel cappone, o lesso, o vuogli arrosto,
E credo alcuna volta anche nel burro;
Nella cervogia, e quando io nвҖҷ ho nel mosto,
E molto piГ№ nellвҖҷ aspro che il mangurro;
Ma sopra tutto nel buon vino ho fede,
E credo che sia salvo chi gli crede.вҖқ

Pulci, Morgante Maggiore, Canto XVIII. stanza cxv.]

вҶ©

For instance, if a first or second wife.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

And send him forth like Samson strong in blindness.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. D.]

And make him Samson-likeвҒ вҖ”more fierce with blindness.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. M.]

вҶ©

Not so the single, deep, and wordless ire,
Of a strong human heartвҒ вҖ”.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[вҖңAlmost all Don Juan is real life, either my own, or from people I knew. By the way, much of the description of the furniture, in Canto Third, is taken from TullyвҖҷs Tripoli (pray note this), and the rest from my own observation. Remember, I never meant to conceal this at all, and have only not stated it, because Don Juan had no preface, nor name to it.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Letter to Murray, August 23, 1821, Letters, 1901, v. 346.

The first edition of вҖңTullyвҖҷs TripoliвҖқ is entitled Narrative of a Ten YearsвҖҷ Residence in Tripoli In Africa: From the original correspondence in the possession of the Family of the late Richard Tully, Esq., the British Consul, 1816, 410. The book is in the form of letters (so says the Preface) written by the ConsulвҖҷs sister. The description of HaidГ©eвҖҷs dress is taken from the account of a visit to Lilla Kebbiera, the wife of the Bashaw (p. 30); the description of the furniture and refreshments from the account of a visit to вҖңLilla Amnani,вҖқ Hadgi AbderrahmamвҖҷs Greek wife (pp. 132вҒ вҖ“вҒ 137). It is evident that the вҖңChielвҖқ who took these вҖңnotesвҖқ was the ConsulвҖҷs sister, not the Consul: вҖңLilla Aisha, the BeyвҖҷs wife, is thought to be very sensible, though rather haughty. Her apartments were grand, and herself superbly habited. Her chemise was covered with gold embroidery at the neck; over it she wore a gold and silver tissue jileck, or jacket without sleeves, and over that another of purple velvet richly laced with gold, with coral and pearl buttons set quite close together down the front; it had short sleeves finished with a gold band not far below the shoulder, and discovered a wide loose chemise of transparent gauze, with gold, silver, and ribband strips. She wore round her anclesвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ a sort of fetter made of a thick bar of gold so fine that they bound it round the leg with one hand; it is an inch and a half wide, and as much in thickness: each of these weighs four pounds. Just above this a band three inches wide of gold thread finished the ends of a pair of trousers made of pale yellow and white silk.вҖқ

Page 132. вҖң[Lilla] rose to take coffee, which was served in very small china cups, placed in silver filigree cups; and gold filigree cups were put under those presented to the married ladies. They had introduced cloves, cinnamon, and saffron into the coffee, which was abundantly sweetened; but this mixture was very soon changed, and replaced by excellent simple coffee for the European ladies.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰвҖқ

Page 133. вҖңThe Greek then shewed us the gala furniture of her own room.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ The hangings of the room were of tapestry, made in pannels of different coloured velvets, thickly inlaid with flowers of silk damask; a yellow border, of about a foot in depth, finished the tapestry at top and bottom, the upper border being embroidered with Moorish sentences from the Koran in lilac letters. The carpet was of crimson satin, with a deep border of pale blue quilted; this is laid over Indian mats and other carpets. In the best part of the room the sofa is placed, which occupies three sides in an alcove, the floor of which is raised. The sofa and the cushions that lay around were of crimson velvet, the centre cushions were embroidered with a sun in gold of highly embossed work, the rest were of gold and silver tissue. The curtains of the alcove were made to match those before the bed. A number of looking-glasses, and a profusion of fine china and chrystal completed the ornaments and furniture of the room, in which were neither tables nor chairs. A small table, about six inches high, is brought in when refreshments are served; it is of ebony, inlaid with mother-of-pearl, tortoiseshell, ivory, gold and silver, of choice woods, or of plain mahogany, according to the circumstances of the proprietor.вҖқ

Page 136. вҖңOn the tables were placed all sorts of refreshments, and thirty or forty dishes of meat and poultry, dressed different ways; there were no knives nor forks, and only a few spoons of gold, silver, ivory, or coral.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰвҖқ

Page 137. вҖңThe beverage was various sherbets, some composed of the juice of boiled raisins, very sweet; some of the juice of pomegranates squeezed through the rind; and others of the pure juice of oranges. These sherbets were copiously supplied in high glass ewers, placed in great numbers on the ground.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ After the dishes of meat were removed, a dessert of Arabian fruits, confectionaries, and sweetmeats was served; among the latter was the date-bread. This sweetmeat is made in perfection only by the blacks at Fezzan, of the ripe date of the country.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ They make it in the shape of loaves, weighing from twenty to thirty pounds; the stones of the fruit are taken out, and the dates simply pressed together with great weights; thus preserved, it keeps perfectly good for a year.вҖқ] вҶ©

[вҖңHe writes like a man who has that clear perception of the truth of things which is the result of the guilty knowledge of good and evil; and who, by the light of that knowledge, has deliberately preferred the evil with a proud malignity of purpose, which would seem to leave little for the last consummating change to accomplish. When he calculates that the reader is on the verge of pitying him, he takes care to throw him back the defiance of laughter, as if to let him know that all the PoetвҖҷs pathos is but the sentimentalism of the drunkard between his cups, or the relenting softness of the courtesan, who the next moment resumes the bad boldness of her degraded character. With such a man, who would wish either to laugh or to weep?вҖқвҒ вҖ”Eclectic Review (Lord ByronвҖҷs Mazeppa), August, 1819, vol. xii. p. 150.] вҶ©

For thatвҖҷs the name they like to cant beneath.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

The upholstererвҖҷs вҖңfiat luxвҖқ had bade to issue.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

This dress is Moorish, and the bracelets and bar are worn in the manner described. The reader will perceive hereafter, that as the mother of HaidГ©e was of Fez, her daughter wore the garb of the country. [Vide ante, p. 160, note 1.] вҶ©

The bar of gold above the instep is a mark of sovereign rank in the women of the families of the Deys, and is worn as such by their female relatives. [Vide ibid.] вҶ©

This is no exaggeration: there were four women whom I remember to have seen, who possessed their hair in this profusion; of these, three were English, the other was a Levantine. Their hair was of that length and quantity, that, when let down, it almost entirely shaded the person, so as nearly to render dress a superfluity. Of these, only one had dark hair; the OrientalвҖҷs had, perhaps, the lightest colour of the four. вҶ©

[CompareвҒ вҖ”

вҖңYet there was round thee such a dawn
Of Light neвҖҷer seen before,
As Fancy never could have drawn,
And never can restore.вҖқ

Song by Rev. C. Wolfe (1791вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1823).

Compare, tooвҒ вҖ”

вҖңShe was a form of Life and Light
That, seen, became a part of sight.вҖқ

The Giaour, lines 1127, 1128.]

вҶ©

[вҖқвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ but Psyche owns no lordвҒ вҖ”
She walks a goddess from above;
All saw, all praised her, all adored,
But no one ever dared to love.вҖқ

The Golden Ass of Apuleius; in English verse, entitled Cupid and Psyche, by Hudson Gurney, 1799.]

вҶ©

[King John, act iv. sc. 2, line 11.] вҶ©

[вҖңRichard Crashaw (died 1650), the friend of Cowley, was honoured,вҖқ says Warton, вҖңwith the praise of Pope; who both read his poems and borrowed from them. After he was ejected from his Fellowship at Peterhouse for denying the covenant, he turned Roman Catholic, and died canon of the church at Loretto.вҖқ Cowley sang his In MemoriamвҒ вҖ”

вҖңAngels (they say) brought the famed Chappel there;
And bore the sacred Load in Triumph through the air:вҒ вҖ”
вҖҳT is surer much they brought thee there, and They,
And Thou, their charge, went singing all the way.вҖқ

The Works, etc., 1668, pp. 29, 30.]

вҶ©

Believed like SoutheyвҒ вҖ”and perused like Crashaw.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[The second chapter of ColeridgeвҖҷs Biographia Literaria is on the вҖңsupposed irritability of men of genius.вҖқ Ed. 1847, i. 29.] вҶ©

Their poet a sad Southey.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. D.]

вҶ©

Of roguesвҒ вҖ”.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. D.]

вҶ©

Of which the causers never know the cause.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. D.]

вҶ©

[Vide St.В August. Epist., xxxvi., cap. xiv., вҖңIlle [Ambrosius, Mediolanensis Episcopus] adjecit; Quando hic sum, non jejuno sabbato; quando Romae sum, jejuno sabbato.вҖқвҒ вҖ”MigneвҖҷs PatrologiГҰ Cursus, 1845, xxxiii. 151.] вҶ©

From the high lyrical to the low rational.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. D.]

вҶ©

[The allusion is to ColeridgeвҖҷs eulogy of Southey in the Biographia Literaria (ed. 1847, i. 61): вҖңIn poetry he has attempted almost every species of composition known before, and he has added new ones; and if we except the very highest lyricвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ he has attempted every species successfully.вҖқ But the satire, primarily and ostensibly aimed at Southey, now and again glances at SoutheyвҖҷs eulogist.] вҶ©

[вҖңGoethe pourroit reprГ©senter la littГ©rature allemande toute entiГЁre.вҖқвҒ вҖ”De LвҖҷAllemagne, par Mme.В la Baronne de StaГ«l-Holstein, 1818, i. 227.] вҶ©

[The poet is not вҖңa sad Southey,вҖқ but is sketched from memory. вҖңLord Byron,вҖқ writes Finlay (History of Greece, vi. 335, note), вҖңused to describe an evening passed in the company of Londos [a Morean landowner, who took part in the first and second Greek Civil Wars], at Vostitza (in 1809), when both were young men, with a spirit that rendered the scene worthy of a place in Don Juan. After supper Londos, who had the face and figure of a chimpanzee, sprang upon a table,вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ and commenced singing through his nose RhigaвҖҷs Hymn to Liberty. A new cadi, passing near the house, inquired the cause of the discordant hubbub. A native Mussulman replied, вҖҳIt is only the young primate Londos, who is drunk, and is singing hymns to the new panaghia of the Greeks, whom they call Eleutheria.вҖҷвҖҠвҖқ (See letter to Andreas Londos (undated), Letters, 1901, vi. 320, note 1.)] вҶ©

The ОңОұОәО¬ПҒПүОҪ ОҪбҝҶПғОҝО№ [Hesiod, Works and Days, line 169] of the Greek poets were supposed to have been the Cape de Verd Islands, or the Canaries. вҶ©

Euboea looks on Marathon,
And Marathon looks on the sea, etc.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[See ГҶschylus, PersГҰ, 463, sq.; and Herodotus, viii. 90. Harpocration records the preservation, in the Acropolis, of the silver-footed throne on which Xerxes sat when he watched the battle of Salamis from the slope of Mount ГҶgaleos.] вҶ©

The Heroic heart awakes no more.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. D.]

вҶ©

[For вҖңthat most ancient military dance, the Pyrrhica,вҖқ see Travels, by E.D. Clarke, 1814, part ii. sect. 11, p. 641; and for specimens of вҖңCadmean characters,вҖқ vide ibid., p. 593.] вҶ©

[After his birthplace Teos was taken by the Persians, B.C. 510, Anacreon migrated to Abdera, but afterwards lived at Samos, under the protection of Polycrates.] вҶ©

Which Hercules might deem his own.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[See the translation of a speech delivered to the Pargiots, in 1815, by an aged citizen: вҖңI exhort you well to consider, before you yield yourselves up to the English, that the King of England now has in his pay all the kings of EuropeвҒ вҖ”obtaining money for this purpose from his merchants; whence, should it become advantageous to the merchants to sell you, in order to conciliate Ali, and obtain certain commercial advantages in his harbours, the English will sell you to Ali.вҖқвҒ вҖ”вҖңParga,вҖқ Edinburgh Review, October, 1819. vol. 32, pp. 263вҒ вҖ“вҒ 293. Here, perhaps, the вҖңFranksвҖқ are the Russians. CompareвҒ вҖ”

вҖңGreeks only should free Greece,
Not the barbarian with his masque of peace.вҖқ

The Age of Bronze, lines 298, 299, Poetical Works, 1901, v. 557, note 1.]

вҶ©

[О“ОөОҪОҝОҜОјОұОҪ, бјөОҪвҖҷ бҪ‘О»бҫ¶ОөОҪ бј”ПҖОөПғП„О№ ПҖПҢОҪ-
П„ОҝП… ПҖПҒПҢОІО»О·ОјвҖҷ бјҒО»ОҜОәО»П…ПғП„ОҝОҪ, бј„-
ОәПҒОұОҪ бҪ‘ПҖбҪё ПҖО»О¬ОәОұ ОЈОҝП…ОҪОҜОҝП…, Оә.П„.О».

Sophocles, Ajax, lines 1190вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1192.]

вҶ©

[CompareвҒ вҖ”

вҖңWhat poets feel not, when they make,
A pleasure in creating,
The world, in its turn, will not take
Pleasure in contemplating.вҖқ

Matthew Arnold (Motto to Poems, 1869, vol. i. Fly-leaf).]

вҶ©

[For this вҖңsentence,вҖқ see Journal, November 16, 1813, Letters, 1898, ii. 320, note 1; see, too, letter to Rogers, 1814, Letters, 1899, iii. 89, note 1.] вҶ©

In digging drains for a new water-closet.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[For Edmund Hoyle (1672вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1769), see English Bards, etc., lines 966вҒ вҖ“вҒ 968, Poetical Works, 1898, i. 372, note 4.] вҶ©

[William Coxe (1747вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1828), Archdeacon of Wilts, a voluminous historian and biographer, published Memoirs of John, Duke of Marlborough, in 1817вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1819.] вҶ©

[See Life of Milton, Works of Samuel Johnson, 1825, vii. pp. 67, 68, 80, et vide ante, p. 146, note 2.] вҶ©

[According to Suetonius, the youthful Titus amused himself by copying handwriting, and boasted that he could have made a first-rate falsarius. One of CГҰsarвҖҷs вҖңearliest actsвҖқ was to crucify some jovial pirates, who had kidnapped him, and with whom he pretended to be on pleasant if not friendly terms.] вҶ©

[James Currie, M.D. (1756вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1805), published, anonymously, the Works of Robert Burns, with an account of his Life, etc., in 1800.] вҶ©

[вҖңHe [Cromwell] was very notorious for robbing orchards, a puerile crimeвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ but grown so scandalous and injurious by the frequent spoyls and damages of Trees, breaking of Hedges, and Inclosures, committed by this Apple-Dragon, that many solemn complaints were made both to his Father and Mother for redresse thereof; which missed not their satisfaction and expiation out of his hide,вҖқ etc.вҒ вҖ”Flagellum, by James Heath, 1663, p. 5. See, too, for his вҖңname of a RoysterвҖқ at Cambridge, A Short View of the Late Troubles in England, by Sir William Dugdale, 1681, p. 459.] вҶ©

[In The Friend, 1818, ii. 38, Coleridge refers to вҖңa planвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ of trying the experiment of human perfectibility on the banks of the Susquehanna;вҖқ and Southey, in his Letter to William Smith, Esq. (1817), (Essays Moral and Political, by Robert Southey, 1832, ii. 17), speaks of his вҖңpurpose to retire with a few friends into the wilds of America, and there lay the foundations of a community,вҖқ etc.; but the word вҖңPantisocracyвҖқ is not mentioned. It occurs, perhaps, for the first time in print, in George DyerвҖҷs biographical sketch of Southey, which he contributed to Public Characters of 1799вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1800, p. 225, вҖңColeridge, no less than Southey, possessed a strong passion for poetry. They commenced, like two young poets, an enthusiastic friendship, and in connection with others, struck out a plan for settling in America, and for having all things in common. This scheme they called Pantisocracy.вҖқ Hence, the phrase must have вҖңcaught on,вҖқ for, in a footnote to his review of ColeridgeвҖҷs Literary Life (Edin. Rev., August, 1817, vol. xxviii. p. 501), Jeffrey speaks of вҖңthe Pantisocratic or Lake School.вҖқ] вҶ©

[Wordsworth was вҖңhired,вҖқ but not, like Burns, вҖңexcised.вҖқ Hazlitt (Lectures on the English Poets, 1870, p. 174) is responsible for the epithet: вҖңMr.В Wordsworth might have shown the incompatibility between the Muse and the Excise,вҖқ etc.] вҶ©

Confined his pedlar poems to democracy.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[Coleridge began his poetical contributions to the Morning Post in January, 1798; his poetical articles in 1800.] вҶ©

Flourished its sophistry for aristocracy.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[Coleridge was married to Sarah Fricker, October 5; Southey to her younger sister Edith, November 15, 1795. Their father, Stephen Fricker, who had been an innkeeper, and afterwards a potter at Bristol, migrated to Bath about the year 1780. For the last six years of his life he was owner and manager of a coal wharf. He had inherited a small fortune, and his wife brought him money, but he died bankrupt, and left his family destitute. His widow returned to Bristol, and kept a school. In a letter to Murray, dated September 11, 1822 (Letters, 1901, vi. 113), Byron quotes the authority of вҖңLuttrell,вҖқ and вҖңhis friend Mr.В Nugent,вҖқ for the statement that Mrs.В Southey and вҖңColeridgeвҖҷs SaraвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ before they were marriedвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ were millinerвҖҷs or dressmakerвҖҷs apprentices.вҖқ The story rests upon their evidence. It is certain that in 1794, when Coleridge appeared upon the scene, the sisters earned their living by going out to work in the houses of friends, and were not, at that time, вҖңmilliners of Bath.вҖқ] вҶ©

[For Joanna Southcott (1750вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1814), see Letters, 1899, iii. 128вҒ вҖ“вҒ 130, note 2.] вҶ©

[Here follows, in the original MS.вҒ вҖ”

вҖңTime has approved Ennui to be the best
Of friends, and opiate draughts; your love and wine,
Which shake so much the human brain and breast,
Must end in languor;вҒ вҖ”men must sleep like swine:
The happy lover and the welcome guest
Both sink at last into a swoon divine;
Full of deep raptures and of bumpers, they
Are somewhat sick and sorry the next day.вҖқ]

вҶ©

[вҖңQuandoque bonus dormitat Homerus.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Hor., Epist. Ad Pisones, line 359.] вҶ©

[WordsworthвҖҷs Benjamin the Waggoner, was written in 1805, but was not published till 1819. вҖңBenjaminвҖқ was servant to William Jackson, a Keswick carrier, who built Greta Hall, and let off part of the house to Coleridge.] вҶ©

[вҖңThereвҖҷs something in a flying horse,
ThereвҖҷs something in a huge balloon;
But through the clouds IвҖҷll never float
Until I have a little Boat,
Shaped like the crescent-moon.вҖқ

WordsworthвҖҷs Peter Bell, stanza i.]

вҶ©

[For MedeaвҖҷs escape from the wrath of Jason, вҖңTitaniacis ablata draconibus,вҖқ see Ovid., Met., vii. 398.] вҶ©

[In his вҖңEssay, Supplementary to the Preface,вҖқ to his вҖңPoemsвҖқ of 1815, Wordsworth, commenting on a passage on Night in DrydenвҖҷs Indian Emperor, says, вҖңDrydenвҖҷs lines are vague, bombastic, and senseless.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ The verses of Dryden once celebrated are forgotten.вҖқ He is not passing any general criticism on вҖңhim who drew Achitophel.вҖқ In a letter to Sir Walter Scott (November 7, 1805), then engaged on his great edition of DrydenвҖҷs Works, he admits that Dryden is not вҖңas a poet any great favourite of mine. I admire his talents and genius highly, but he is not a poetical genius. The only qualities I can find in Dryden that are essentially poetical, are a certain ardour and impetuosity of mind, with an excellent earвҖқ (Life of Wordsworth, by W. Knight, 1889, ii. 26вҒ вҖ“вҒ 29). Scott may have remarked on WordsworthвҖҷs estimate of Dryden in conversation with Byron.] вҶ©

While swung the signal from the sacred tower.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

Are not these pretty stanzas?вҒ вҖ”some folks sayвҒ вҖ”
Downright in printвҒ вҖ”.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[Compare ColeridgeвҖҷs Lines to Nature, which were published in the Morning Herald, in 1815, but must have been unknown to ByronвҒ вҖ”

вҖңSo will I build my altar in the fields,
And the blue sky my fretted dome shall be.вҖқ]

вҶ©

[вҖңAs early as the fifth or sixth century of the Christian era, the port of Augustus was converted into pleasant orchards, and a lovely grove of pines covered the ground where the Roman fleet once rode at anchor.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ This advantageous situation was fortified by art and labour, and in the twentieth year of his age, the Emperor of the WestвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ retired toвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ the walls and morasses of Ravenna.вҖқвҒ вҖ”GibbonвҖҷs Decline and Fall, 1825, ii. 244, 245.] вҶ©

[вҖңThe first time I had a conversation with Lord Byron on the subject of religion was at Ravenna, my native country, in 1820, while we were riding on horseback in an extensive solitary wood of pines. The scene invited to religious meditation. It was a fine day in spring. вҖҳHow,вҖҷ he said, вҖҳraising our eyes to heaven, or directing them to the earth, can we doubt of the existence of God?вҒ вҖ”or how, turning them to what is within us, can we doubt that there is something more noble and durable than the clay of which we are formed?вҖҷвҖҠвҖқвҒ вҖ”Count Gamba.] вҶ©

[If the Pineta of Ravenna, bois funГЁbre, invited Byron вҖңto religious meditation,вҖқ the mental picture of the вҖңspectre huntsmanвҖқ pursuing his eternal vengeance on вҖңthe inexorable dameвҖқвҒ вҖ”вҖңthat fatal she,вҖқ who had mocked his woesвҒ вҖ”must have set in motion another train of thought. Such lines as these would вҖңspeak comfortablyвҖқ to himвҒ вҖ”

вҖңBecause she deemвҖҷd I well deserved to die,
And made a merit of her cruelty,вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ
Mine is the ungrateful maid by heaven designвҖҷd:
Mercy she would not give, nor mercy shall she find.вҖқ
вҖңBy her example warnвҖҷd, the rest beware;
More easy, less imperious, were the fair;
And that one hunting, which the Devil designвҖҷd
For one fair female, lost him half the kind.вҖқ

DrydenвҖҷs Theodore and Honoria (sub fine).]

вҶ©

О•ПғПҖОөПҒОө ПҖОұОҪП„Оұ ПҶОөПҒОөО№ПӮ
ОҰОөПҒОөО№ПӮ ОҝО№ОҪОҝОҪвҒ вҖ”ПҶОөПҒОөО№ПӮ ОұО№ОіОұ
ОҰОөПҒОөО№ПӮ ОјОұП„ОөПҒО№ ПҖОұО№ОҙОұ.

Fragment of Sappho.

[ПңОӯПғПҖОөПҒОө, ПҖО¬ОҪП„Оұ ПҶОӯПҒПүОҪ, бҪ…ПғОұ ПҶОұОҜОҪОҝО»О№ПӮ бјҗПғОәОӯОҙОұПғвҖҷ ОұбҪ”ПүПӮВ·
ОҰОӯПҒОөО№ПӮ ОҝбјҙОҪ ПҶОӯПҒОөО№ПӮ Оұбј¶ОіОұ, ОҰОӯПҒОөО№ПӮ бј„ПҖП… ОјОұП„ОӯПҒО№ ПҖОұбҝ–ОҙОұ.

Sappho, Memoir, Text, by Henry Thornton Wharton, 1895, p. 136.

вҖңEvening, all things thou bringest
Which dawn spread apart from each other;
The lamb and the kid thou bringest,
Thou bringest the boy to his mother.вҖқ

J.A. Symonds.

Compare TennysonвҖҷs Locksley Hall, Sixty Years AfterвҒ вҖ”вҖңHesper, whom the poet callвҖҷd the Bringer home of all good things.вҖқ] вҶ©

вҖңEra giГ  lвҖҷora che volge il disio
Ai naviganti, e intenerisce il cuore;
Lo di chвҖҷ han detto ai dolci amici addio;
E che lo nuovo peregrinвҖҷ damore
Punge, se ode squilla di lontano,
Che paia il giorno pianger che si more.вҖқ

DanteвҖҷs Purgatory, canto viii., lines 1вҒ вҖ“вҒ 6.

This last line is the first of GrayвҖҷs Elegy, taken by him without acknowledgment. вҶ©

See Suetonius for this fact.

[вҖңThe public joy was so great upon the occasion of his death, that the common people ran up and down with caps upon their heads. And yet there were some, who for a long time trimmed up his tomb with spring and summer flowers, and, one while, placed his image upon his rostra dressed up in state robes, another while published proclamations in his name, as if he was yet alive, and would shortly come to Rome again, with a vengeance to all his enemies.вҖқвҒ вҖ”De XII. CГҰs., lib. vi. cap. lvii.] вҶ©

But IвҖҷm digressingвҒ вҖ”what on earth have Nero
And WordsworthвҒ вҖ”both poetical buffoons, etc.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[See De PoeticГў, cap. xxiv. See, too, the Preface to DrydenвҖҷs вҖңDedicationвҖқ of the ГҶneis (Works of John Dryden, 1821, xiv. 130вҒ вҖ“вҒ 134). Dryden is said to have derived his knowledge of Aristotle from DacierвҖҷs translation, and it is probable that Byron derived his from Dryden. See letter to Hodgson (Letters, 1891, v. 284), in which he quotes Aristotle as quoted in JohnsonвҖҷs Life of Dryden.] вҶ©

[вҖңTill Pride and worse Ambition threw me down,
Warring in Heaven against HeavenвҖҷs matchless King.вҖқ

Paradise Lost, iv. 40, 41.]

вҶ©

[вҖңTime hovers oвҖҷer, impatient to destroy,
And shuts up all the passages of joy:
In vain their gifts the bounteous seasons pour,
The fruit autumnal, and the vernal flowвҖҷr;
With listless eyes the dotard views the store,
He views, and wonders that they please no more.вҖқ

JohnsonвҖҷs Vanity of Human Wishes.]

вҶ©

[вҖқвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ my May of Life
Is fallвҖҷn into the sere, the yellow leaf.вҖқ

Macbeth, act v. sc. 3, lines 22, 23.]

вҶ©

Itself to that fit apathy whose deed.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

First in the icy depths of LetheвҖҷs spring.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[See вҖңIntroduction to the Morgante Maggiore,вҖқ Poetical Works, 1901, iv. 280.] вҶ©

Pulci being FatherвҒ вҖ”.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. Alternative reading.]

вҶ©

[вҖңCum canerem reges et prГҰlia, Cynthius aurem Vellit, et admonuit.вҖқ Virgil, Ecl. vi. lines 3, 4.] вҶ©

вёәвҒ from its motherвҖҷs knee
When its last weaning draught is drained for ever,
The child dividedвҒ вҖ”it were less to see,
Than these two from each other torn apart.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[See Herodotus (Cleobis and Biton), i. 31. The sentiment is in a fragment of Menander.

бҪҚОҪ Оҝбјұ ОёОөОҝбҪ¶ ПҶО№О»ОҝбҝҰПғО№ОҪ бјҖПҖОҝОёОҪО®ПғОәОөО№ ОҪОӯОҝПӮ

or

бҪҚОҪ ОібҪ°ПҒ ПҶО№О»Оөбҝ– ОёОөбҪёПӮ бјҖПҖОҝОёОҪО®ПғОәОөО№ ОҪОӯОҝПӮ.

Menandri at Philomenis reliquiГҰ, edidit Augustus Meineke, p. 48.

See Letters, 1898, ii. 22, note 1. Byron applied the saying to Allegra in a letter to Sir Walter Scott, dated May 4, 1822, Letters, 1901, vi. 57.] вҶ©

[Compare Childe Harold, Canto II. stanza xcvi. line 7. Compare, too, YoungвҖҷs Night Thoughts (вҖңThe Complaint,вҖқ Night I. ed. 1825, p. 5)] вҶ©

[Compare SwiftвҖҷs вҖңlittle languageвҖқ in his letter to Stella: Podefar, for instance, which is supposed to stand for вҖңPoor dear foolish rogue,вҖқ and Ppt., which meant вҖңPoor pretty thing.вҖқвҒ вҖ”See The Journal of Stella, edited by G.A. Aitken, 1901, xxxv. note 1, and вҖңJournal: March, 1710вҒ вҖ“вҒ 11,вҖқ 165, note 2.] вҶ©

For theirs were buoyant spirits, which would bound
вҖҷGainst common failings, etc.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[The reference may be to ColeridgeвҖҷs Kubla Khan, which, to MedwinвҖҷs wonderment, вҖңdelightedвҖқ Byron (Conversations, 1824, p. 264). De QuincyвҖҷs Confessions of an English Opium Eater appeared in the London Magazine, October, November, 1821, after Cantos III., IV., V., of Don Juan were published. But, perhaps, he was contrasting the вҖңsimpler blissesвҖқ of Juan and HaidГ©e with ShelleyвҖҷs mystical affinities and divagations.] вҶ©

вёәвҒ had set their hearts a bleeding.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[вҖңThe shadowy desert, unfrequented woods,
I better brook than flourishing peopled towns:
There can I sit alone, unseen of any,
And to the nightingaleвҖҷs complaining notes
Tune my distresses, and record, my woes.вҖқ

Two Gentlemen of Verona, act v. sc. 4, lines 2вҒ вҖ“вҒ 6.]

вҶ©

Called social, where all Vice and Hatred are.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

Moved with her dreamвҒ вҖ”.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

Strange state of being!вҒ вҖ”for вҖҳt is still to beвҒ вҖ”
And who can know all false what then we see?

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[Compare the description of the вҖңspacious cave,вҖқ in The Island, Canto IV. lines 121, sq., Poetical Works, 1901, v. 629, note 1.] вҶ©

вёәвҒ methought.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. Alternative reading.]

вҶ©

[The reader will observe a curious mark of propinquity which the poet notices, with respect to the hands of the father and daughter. Lord Byron, we suspect, is indebted for the first hint of this to Ali Pacha, who, by the bye, is the original of Lambro; for, when his lordship was introduced, with his friend Hobhouse, to that agreeable mannered tyrant, the Vizier said that he knew he was the Megalos Anthropos (i.e. the great Man), by the smallness of his ears and hands.вҒ вҖ”Galt. See ByronвҖҷs letter to his mother, November 12, 1809, Letters, 1898, i. 251.] вҶ©

And if I did my duty as thou hast,
This hour were thine, and thy young minions last.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

Till further orders should his doom assign.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

Loving and lovedвҒ вҖ”.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

But thou, sweet fury of the fiery rill,
Makest on the liver a still worse attack;
Besides, thy price is something dearer still.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[вҖңAs squire Sullen says, вҖҳ\My head aches consumedly,вҖҷ вҖҳScrub, bring me a dram!вҖҷ Drank some Imola wine, and some punch!вҖқвҒ вҖ”Extracts from a Diary, February 25, 1821, Letters, 1901, v. 209. For rack or вҖңarrackвҖқ punch, see ThackerayвҖҷs Vanity Fair, A Novel without a Hero, chap. vi. ed. 1892, p. 44.] вҶ©

[вҖңAt Fas [Fez] the houses of the great and wealthy have, within-side, spacious courts, adorned with sumptuous galleries, fountains, basons of fine marble, and fish-ponds, shaded with orange, lemon, pomegranate, and fig trees, abounding with fruit, and ornamented with roses, hyacinths, jasmine, violets, and orange flowers, emitting a delectable fragrance.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Account of the Empire of Marocco and Suez, by James Grey Jackson, 1811, pp. 69, 70.] вҶ©

Beauty and Passion were the natural dower
Of HaidГ©eвҖҷs mother, but her climateвҖҷs force
Lay at her heart, though sleeping at the source.

or,

But in her large eye lay deep PassionвҖҷs force,
Like to a lion sleeping by a source.

or,

But in her large eye lay deep PassionвҖҷs force,
As sleeps a lion by a riverвҖҷs source.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[Compare Manfred, act iii. sc. 1, line 128, Poetical Works, 1901, iv. 125.] вҶ©

The blood gushed from her lips, and ears, and eyes:
Those eyes, so beautifulвҒ вҖ”beheld no more.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

This is no very uncommon effect of the violence of conflicting and different passions. The Doge Francis Foscari, on his deposition in 1457, hearing the bells of St.В Mark announce the election of his successor, вҖңmourut subitement dвҖҷune hГ©morragie causГ©e par une veine qui sвҖҷГ©clata dans sa poitrineвҖқ [see Sismondi, 1815, x. 46, and Daru, 1821, ii. 536; see, too, The Two Foscari, act v. sc. i, line 306, and Introduction to the Two Foscari, Poetical Works, 1901, v. 118, 193], at the age of eighty years, when вҖңWho would have thought the old man had so much blood in him?вҖқ (Macbeth, act v. sc. 1, lines 34вҒ вҖ“вҒ 36.) Before I was sixteen years of age I was witness to a melancholy instance of the same effect of mixed passions upon a young person, who, however, did not die in consequence, at that time, but fell a victim some years afterwards to a seizure of the same kind, arising from causes intimately connected with agitation of mind. вҶ©

[The view of the Venus of Medici instantly suggests the lines in the вҖңSeasonsвҖқ [the description of вҖңMusidora bathingвҖқ in Summer]вҒ вҖ”

вҖқвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ With wild surprise,
As if to marble struck, devoid of sense,
A stupid moment motionless she stood:
So stands the statue that enchants the world.вҖқ

Hobhouse.

A still closer parallel to this stanza, and to Childe Harold, Canto IV. stanzas xlix., cxl., cxli., clx., clxi., is to be found in ThomsonвҖҷs Liberty, pt. iv. lines 131вҒ вҖ“вҒ 206, where the вҖңFarnese Hercules,вҖқ the вҖңDying Gladiator,вҖқ the вҖңVenus of Medici,вҖқ and the вҖңLaocoonвҖқ group, are commemorated as typical works of art.] вҶ©

Distinct from life, as being still the same.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

вҖ”working slow.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

Have dawned a child of beauty, though of sin.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[вҖқвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ Duncan is in his grave:
After lifeвҖҷs fitful fever he sleeps well.вҖқ

Macbeth, act iii. sc. 2., lines 22, 23.]

вҶ©

No stone is there to read, nor tongue to say,
No dirgeвҒ вҖ”save when arise the stormy seas.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[вҖңBut now I am cabined, cribbed,вҖқ etc. Macbeth, act iii. sc. 4, line 24.] вҶ©

[Jacob Bryant (1715вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1804) published his Dissertation concerning the War of Troy, etc., in 1796. See The Bride of Abydos, Canto II. lines 510, sq., Poetical Works, 1900, iii. 179, note 1. See, too, Extracts from a Diary, January 11, 1821, Letters, 1901, v. 165, 166, вҖңI have stood upon that plain [of Troy] daily, for more than a month, in 1810; and if anything diminished my pleasure, it was that the blackguard Bryant had impugned its veracity.вҖқ Hobhouse, in his Travels in Albania, 1858, ii. 93, sq., discusses at length the identity of the barrows of the Troad with the tumuli of Achilles, Ajax, and Protesilaus, and refutes BryantвҖҷs arguments against the identity of Cape Janissary and the Sigean promontory. вҶ©

All heroes who alive perhaps
if still alive.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. Alternative reading]

вҶ©

вҖ”and mountain-bounded
and mountain-outlined plain.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. Alternative reading]

вҶ©

[вҖңThe whole region was, in a manner, in possession of the SalsetteвҖҷs crew, parties of whom, in their white summer dresses, might be seen scattered over the plains collecting the tortoises, which swarm on the sides of the rivulets, and are found under every furze-bush.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Travels in Albania, 1858, ii. 116. See, too, for mention of вҖңhundreds of tortoisesвҖқ falling вҖңfrom the overhanging branches, and thick underwood,вҖқ into the waters of the Mender, Travels, etc., by E.D. Clarke, 1812, Part II. sect. i. p. 96.] вҶ©

вёәвҒ and land tortoise crawls.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. Alternative reading.]

вҶ©

вҖ”their learned researches bear.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. Alternative reading.]

вҶ©

This is a fact. A few years ago a man engaged a company for some foreign theatre, embarked them at an Italian port, and carrying them to Algiers, sold them all. One of the women, returned from her captivity, I heard sing, by a strange coincidence, in RossiniвҖҷs opera of LвҖҷItaliana in Algieri, at Venice, in the beginning of 1817.

[We have reason to believe that the following, which we take from the MS. journal of a highly respectable traveller, is a more correct account: вҖңIn 1812 a Signor Guariglia induced several young persons of both sexesвҒ вҖ”none of them exceeding fifteen years of ageвҒ вҖ”to accompany him on an operatic excursion; part to form the opera, and part the ballet. He contrived to get them on board a vessel, which took them to Janina, where he sold them for the basest purposes. Some died from the effect of the climate, and some from suffering. Among the few who returned were a Signor Molinari, and a female dancer named Bonfiglia, who afterwards became the wife of Crespi, the tenor singer. The wretch who so basely sold them was, when Lord Byron resided at Venice, employed as capo deвҖҷ vestarj, or head tailor, at the Fenice.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Maria Graham (Lady Callcot). Ed. 1832.] вҶ©

[A comic singer in the opera buffa. The Italians, however, distinguish the buffo cantante, which requires good singing, from the buffo comico, in which there is more acting.вҒ вҖ”Ed. 1832.] вҶ©

[The figuranti are those dancers of a ballet who do not dance singly, but many together, and serve to fill up the background during the exhibition of individual performers. They correspond to the chorus in the opera.вҒ вҖ”Maria Graham.] вҶ©

To help the ladies in their dress and lacing.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

It is strange that it should be the Pope and the Sultan, who are the chief encouragers of this branch of tradeвҒ вҖ”women being prohibited as singers at St.В PeterвҖҷs, and not deemed trustworthy as guardians of the harem.

[вҖңScarcely a soul of them can read. Pacchierotti was one of the best informed of the castratiвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ Marchesi is so grossly ignorant that he wrote the word opera, opperra, but Nature has been so bountiful to the animal, that his ignorance and insolence were forgotten the moment he sang.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Venice, etc., by a Lady of Rank, 1824, ii. 86.] вҶ©

[The N. Engl. Dict. cites Bunyan, Walpole, Fielding, Miss Austen, and Dickens as authorities for the plural вҖңwas.вҖқ See art. вҖңbe.вҖқ Here, as elsewhere, Byron wrote as he spoke.] вҶ©

He never shows his feelings, but his teeth.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. Alternative reading.]

вҶ©

[вҖңOur firman arrived from Constantinople on the 30th of April (1810).вҖқвҒ вҖ”Travels in Albania, 1858, ii. 186.] вҶ©

That each pulled, different waysвҒ вҖ”and waxing rough,
Had cuffed each other, only for the cuff.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[вҖңO, who can hold a fire in his hand,
By thinking on the frosty Caucasus?вҖқ

Richard II., act i. sc. 3, lines 294, 295.]

вҶ©

Having had some experience in my youth.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[вҖңDon Juan will be known, by and by, for what it is intendedвҒ вҖ”a Satire on abuses in the present states of society, and not an eulogy of vice. It may be now and then voluptuous:вҒ вҖ”I canвҖҷt help that. Ariosto is worse. Smollett (see Lord Strutwell in vol. 2nd of R[oderick] R[andom][1793, pp. 119вҒ вҖ“вҒ 127]) ten times worse; and Fielding no better.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Letter to Murray, December 25, 1822, Letters, 1901, vi. 155, 156.] вҶ©

[Vide ante, p. 204, note 1. вҖңIt seems hardly to admit of doubt, that the plain of Anatolia, watered by the Mender, and backed by a mountainous ridge, of which Kazdaghy is the summit, offers the precise territory alluded to by Homer. The long controversy, excited by Mr.В BryantвҖҷs publication, and since so vehemently agitated, would probably never have existed, had it not been for the erroneous maps of the country which, even to this hour, disgrace our geographical knowledge of that part of Asia.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Travels, etc., by E.D. Clarke, 1812, Part II. sect, i. p. 78.] вҶ©

The pillar which records the battle of Ravenna is about two miles from the city, on the opposite side of the river to the road towards Forli. Gaston de Foix [(1489вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1512) Duc de Nemours, nephew of Louis XII.], who gained the battle, was killed in it: there fell on both sides twenty thousand men. The present state of the pillar and its site is described in the text.

[Beyond the Porta Sisi, about two miles from Ravenna, on the banks of the Ronco, is a square pillar (La Colonna de Francesi), erected in 1557 by Pietro Cesi, president of Romagna, as a memorial of the battle gained by the combined army of Louis XII. and the Duke of Ferrara over the troops of Julius II. and the King of Spain, April 11 1512.вҒ вҖ”Handbook of Northern Italy, p. 548.] вҶ©

[Compare Childe Harold, Canto IV. stanza lvii. line i, Poetical Works, 1899, ii. 371, note i. See, too, Preface to the Prophecy of Dante, ibid., iv. 243.] вҶ©

Protects his tomb, but greater care is paid.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

With human ordure is it now defiled,
As if the peasantвҖҷs scorn this mode invented
To show his loathing of the thing he soiled.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

Those sufferings once reserved for Hell alone.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

Its fumes are frankincense; and were there nought
Even of this vapour, still the chilling yoke
Of silence would not long be borne by Thought.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

I have drunk deep of passions as they pass,
And dearly bought the bitter power to give.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[See, for instance, WilsonвҖҷs review of Don Juan, in BlackwoodвҖҷs Edinburgh Magazine, August, 1819, vol. v. p. 512, sq.: вҖңTo confessвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ to his Maker, and to weep over in secret agonies the wildest and most fantastic transgressions of heart and mind, is the part of a conscious sinner, in whom sin has not become the sole principle of life and action.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ But to lay bare to the eye of manвҒ вҖ”and of womanвҒ вҖ”all the hidden convulsions of a wicked spirit,вҖқ etc.] вҶ©

What! must I go with Wordy to the cooks?
ReadвҒ вҖ”were it but your GrandmotherвҖҷs to vexвҒ вҖ”
And let me not the only minstrel be
Cut off from tasting your Castalian tea.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[CompareвҒ вҖ”

вҖңI leave them to their daily вҖҳtea is ready,вҖҷ
Snug coterie, and literary lady.вҖқ

Beppo, stanza lxxvi. lines 7, 8, Poetical Works, 1901, iv. 184, note.]

вҶ©

[The caged starling, by its repeated cry, вҖңI canвҖҷt get out! I canвҖҷt get out!вҖқ cured Yorick of his sentimental yearnings for imprisonment in the Bastille. See SterneвҖҷs Sentimental Journey, ed. 1804, pp. 100вҒ вҖ“вҒ 106.] вҶ©

[In his Essay, Supplement to the Preface (Poems by William Wordsworth, ed. 1820, iii. 315вҒ вҖ“вҒ 348), Wordsworth maintains that the appreciation of great poetry is a plant of slow growth, that immediate recognition is a mark of inferiority, or is to be accounted for by the presence of adventitious qualities: вҖңSo strange, indeed, are the obliquities of admiration, that they whose opinions are much influenced by authority will often be tempted to think that there are no fixed principles in human nature for this art to rest upon.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ Away, then, with the senseless iteration of the word popular!вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ The voice that issues from this spirit [of human knowledge] is that Vox Populi which the Deity inspires. Foolish must he be who can mistake for this a local acclamation, or a transitory outcryвҒ вҖ”transitory though it be for years, local though from a Nation. Still more lamentable is his error who can believe that there is anything of divine infallibility in this clamour of that small though loud portion of the community ever governed by factitious influence, which under the name of the Public, passes itself upon the unthinking for the People.вҖқ Naturally enough Byron regarded this pronouncement as a taunt if not as a challenge. WordsworthвҖҷs noble appeal from a provincial to an imperial authority, from the present to the future, is not strengthened by the obvious reference to the popularity of contemporaries.] вҶ©

[SoutheyвҖҷs Madoc in Wales, Poetical Works, Part I. Canto V. Ed. 1838, v. 39.] вҶ©

Not having looked at many of that hue,
Nor gartersвҒ вҖ”save those of the вҖңhoni soitвҖңвҒ вҖ”which lie
Round the Patrician legs which walk about,
The ornaments of levee and of rout.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[Probably Lady Charlemont. See вҖңJournal,вҖқ November 22, 1813.] вҶ©

[The cyanometer, an instrument for ascertaining the intensity of the blue colour of the sky, was invented by Horace BГ©nГ©dict de Saussure (1740вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1799); see his Essai sur lвҖҷHygromГ©trie. F.H. Alexander von Humboldt (1769вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1859) вҖңmade great use of his instrument on his voyages, and ascertained by the colour the degree of blueness, the accumulation and the nature of the non-transparent exhalations of the air.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Alexander von Humboldt, by Professor Klencke, translated by Juliette Bauer, 1852, pp. 45, 46.] вҶ©

IвҖҷll back a London вҖңBasвҖқ against Peru.

or,

IвҖҷll bet some pair of stocking beat Peru.

or,

And so, old Sotheby, weвҖҷll measure you.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[вҖңThe slave-market is a quadrangle, surrounded by a covered gallery, and ranges of small and separate apartments.вҖқ Here the poor wretches sit in a melancholy posture. вҖңBefore they cheapen вҖҷem, they turn вҖҷem about from this side to that, survey вҖҷem from top to bottom.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ Such of вҖҷem, both men and women, to whom Dame Nature has been niggardly of her charms, are set apart for the vilest services: but such girls as have youth and beauty pass their time well enough.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ The retailers of this human ware are the Jews, who take good care of their slavesвҖҷ education, that they may sell the better: their choicest they keep at home, and there you must go, if you would have better than ordinary; for вҖҷtis here, as вҖҷtis in markets for horses, the handsomest donвҖҷt always appear, but are kept within doors.вҖқвҒ вҖ”A Voyage into the Levant, by M. Tournefort, 1741, ii. 198, 199. See, too, for the description of the sale of two Circassians and one Georgian, Voyage de Vienne Г  Belgrade,вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ par N.E. Kleeman, 1780, pp. 141, 142. The вҖңlowest offer for the prize Circassian was 4000 piastres.вҖқ] вҶ©

The females stood, till chosen each as victim
To the soft oath of вҖңAna seing Siktum!вҖқ[*]

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

[* If the Turkish words are correctly given, вҖңthe oathвҖқ may be an imprecation on вҖңyour motherвҖҷsвҖқ chastity.] вҶ©

For fear the Canto should become too long.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[Canto V. was begun at Ravenna, October the 16th, and finished November the 20th, 1820. It was published August 8, 1821, together with Cantos III. and IV.] вҶ©

This expression of Homer has been much criticized. It hardly answers to our Atlantic ideas of the ocean, but is sufficiently applicable to the Hellespont, and the Bosphorus, with the Aegean intersected with islands.

[Vide Iliad, xiv. 245, etc. HomerвҖҷs вҖңocean-streamвҖқ was not the Hellespont, but the rim of waters which encircled the disk of the world.] вҶ©

[вҖңThe pleasure of going in a barge to Chelsea is not comparable to that of rowing upon the canal of the sea here, where, for twenty miles together, down the Bosphorus, the most beautiful variety of prospects present themselves. The Asian side is covered with fruit trees, villages, and the most delightful landscapes in nature; on the European stands Constantinople, situated on seven hills; showing an agreeable mixture of gardens, pine and cypress trees, palaces, mosques, and public buildings, raised one above another, with as much beauty and appearance of symmetry as your ladyship ever saw in a cabinet adorned by the most skilful hands, where jars show themselves above jars, mixed with canisters, babies, and candlesticks. This is a very odd comparison: but it gives me an exact idea of the thing.вҖқвҒ вҖ”See letter to Mr.В Pope, No. xl. June 17, 1717, and letter to the Countess of Bristol, No. xlvi. n.d., Letters of the Lady Mary Worthy Montagu, 1816, pp. 183вҒ вҖ“вҒ 219. See, too, letter to Mrs.В Byron, June 28, 1810, Letters, 1890, i. 280, note 1.] вҶ©

[For ByronвҖҷs вҖңMarys,вҖқ see Poetical Works, 1898, i. 192, note 2.] вҶ©

The вҖңGiantвҖҷs GraveвҖқ is a height on the Asiatic shore of the Bosphorus, much frequented by holiday parties; like Harrow and Highgate.

[вҖңThe GiantвҖҷs Mountain, 650 feet high, is almost exactly opposite BuyukderehвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ It is called by the Turks Yoshadagh, Mountain of Joshua, because the GiantвҖҷs Grave on the top is, according to the Moslem legend, the grave of Joshua. The grave was formerly called the Couch of Hercules; but the classical story is that it was the tomb of Amycus, king of the Bebryces [on his grave grew the laurus insana, a branch of which caused strife (Plin., Hist. Nat., lib. xvi. cap. xliv. ed. 1593, ii. 198)]. The grave is 20 feet long, and 5 feet broad; it is within a stone enclosure, and is planted with flowers and bushes.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Handbook for Constantinople, p. 103.] вҶ©

For then the Parca are most busy spinning
The fates of seamen, and the loud winds raise.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

That he a man of rank and birth had been,
And then they calculated on his ransom,
And last not leastвҒ вҖ”he was so very handsome.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

It chanced that near him, separately lotted,
From out the group of slaves put up for sale,
A man of middle age, andвҒ вҖ”.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[The object of SuwarofвҖҷs campaign of 1789 was the conquest of Belgrade and Servia, that of Wallachia by the Austrians, etc. Neither of these plans succeeded.вҖқвҒ вҖ”The Life of Field-Marshal Suwarof, by L.M.P. Tranchant de Laverne, 1814, pp. 105, 106.] вҶ©

[The Turkish zecchino is a gold coin, worth about seven shillings and sixpence. The para is not quite equal to an English halfpenny.] вҶ©

[CandideвҖҷs increased satisfaction with life is implied in the narrative. For example, in chap, xviii., where Candide visits Eldorado:вҒ вҖ”вҖңNever was there a better entertainment, and never was more wit shown at table than that which fell from His Majesty. Cacambo explained the kingвҖҷs bons mots to Candide, and notwithstanding they were translated, they still appeared bons mots.вҖқ This was after supper. See, too, Part II. chap, ii.] вҶ©

See Plutarch in Alex., Q. Curt. Hist. Alexand., and Sir Richard ClaytonвҖҷs вҖңCritical Inquiry into the Life of Alexander the Great,вҖқ 1763 [from the Examen Critique, etc., of Guilhem de Clermont-LodГЁve, Baron de Sainte Croix, 1775.]

[вҖңHe used to say that sleep and the commerce with the sex were the things that made him most sensible of his mortality,вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ He was also very temperate in eating.вҖқвҒ вҖ”PlutarchвҖҷs Alexander, Langhorne, 1838, p. 473.] вҶ©

But for mere food, I think with PhilipвҖҷs son,
Or AmmonвҖҷsвҒ вҖ”for two fathers claimed this one.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

The assassination alluded to took place on the 8th of December, 1820, in the streets of Ravenna, not a hundred paces from the residence of the writer. The circumstances were as described.

[вҖңDecember 9, 1820. I open my letter to tell you a fact, which will show the state of this country better than I can. The commandant of the troops is now lying dead in my house. He was shot at a little past eight oвҖҷclock, about two hundred paces from my door. I was putting on my great coat to visit Madame la Comtessa G., when I heard the shot. On coming into the hall, I found all my servants on the balcony, exclaiming that a man was murdered. I immediately ran down, calling on Tita (the bravest of them) to follow me. The rest wanted to hinder us from going, as it is the custom for everybody here, it seems, to run away from вҖҳthe stricken deer.вҖҷвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ we found him lying on his back, almost, if not quite, dead, with five wounds; one in the heart, two in the stomach, one in the finger, and the other in the arm. Some soldiers cocked their guns, and wanted to hinder me from passing. However, we passed, and I found Diego, the adjutant, crying over him like a childвҒ вҖ”a surgeon, who said nothing of his professionвҒ вҖ”a priest, sobbing a frightened prayerвҒ вҖ”and the commandant, all this time, on his back, on the hard, cold pavement, without light or assistance, or anything around him but confusion and dismay. As nobody could, or would, do anything but howl and pray, and as no one would stir a finger to move him, for fear of consequences, I lost my patienceвҒ вҖ”made my servant and a couple of the mob take up the bodyвҒ вҖ”sent off two soldiers to the guardвҒ вҖ”despatched Diego to the Cardinal with the news, and had him carried upstairs into my own quarters. But it was too lateвҒ вҖ”he was gone.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ I had him partly strippedвҒ вҖ”made the surgeon examine him, and examined him myself. He had been shot by cut balls or slugs. I felt one of the slugs, which had gone through him, all but the skin.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ He only said, вҖҳO Dio!вҖҷ and вҖҳGesu!вҖҷ two or three times, and appeared to have suffered little. Poor fellow! he was a brave officer; but had made himself much disliked by the people.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Letter to Moore, December 9, 1820, Letters, 1901, v. 133. The commandantвҖҷs name was Del Pinto (Life, p. 472).] вҶ©

вёәвҒ so I had
Him borne, as soonвҖҷs I could, up several pair
Of stairsвҒ вҖ”and looked to,вҒ вёәвҒ But why should I add
More circumstances?вҒ вёә.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

And now as silent as an unstrung drum.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

The light and elegant wherries plying about the quays of Constantinople are so called. вҶ©

[Ilderim, a Syrian Tale, by Henry Gally Knight, was published in 1816; Phrosyne, a Grecian Tale, and Alashtar, an Arabian Tale, in 1817. MooreвҖҷs Lalla Kookh also appeared in 1817.] вҶ©

[St.В Bartholomew was вҖңdiscoriate, and flayed quickвҖқ (Golden Legend, 1900, v. 43).] вҶ©

We from impalementвҒ вҖ”.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

вҖңMany of the seraГҜ and summer-houses [on the Bosphorus] have received these significant, or rather fantastic names: one is the Pearl Pavilion; another is the Star Palace; a third the Mansion of Looking-glasses.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Travels in Albania, 1858, ii. 243. вҶ©

Of speeches, beauty, flatteryвҒ вҖ”there is no
Method more sureвҒ вҖ”.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[Guide des Voyageurs; Directions for Travellers, etc.вҒ вҖ”Rhymes, Incidental and Humorous; Rhyming Reminiscences; Effusions in Rhyme, etc.вҒ вҖ”Lady MorganвҖҷs Tour in Italy; Tour through Istria, etc., etc.вҒ вҖ”Sketches of Italy; Sketches of Modern Greece, etc., etc.вҒ вҖ”Historical Illustrations of the Fourth Canto of Childe Harold, by J.C. Hobhouse, 1818.] вҶ©

In Turkey nothing is more common than for the Mussulmans to take several glasses of strong spirits by way of appetiser. I have seen them take as many as six of raki before dinner, and swear that they dined the better for it: I tried the experiment, but fared like the Scotchman, who having heard that the birds called kittiwakes were admirable whets, ate six of them, and complained that вҖңhe was no hungrier than when he began.вҖқ вҶ©

[вҖңEverything is so still [in the court of the Seraglio], that the motion of a fly might be heard, in a manner; and if any one should presume to raise his voice ever so little, or show the least want of respect to the Mansion-place of their Emperor, he would instantly have the bastinado by the officers that go the rounds.вҖқ-A Voyage in the Levant, by M. Tournefort, 1741, ii. 183.] вҶ©

A common furniture. I recollect being received by Ali Pacha, in a large room, paved with marble, containing a marble basin, and fountain playing in the centre, etc., etc.

[Compare Childe Harold, Canto II. stanza lxii.вҒ вҖ”

вҖңIn marble-paved pavilion, where a spring
Of living water from the centre rose,
Whose bubbling did a genial freshness fling,
And soft voluptuous couches breathed repose,
Ali reclined, a man of war and woes,вҖқ etc.]

вҶ©

[A reminiscence of Newstead. Compare MooreвҖҷs song, вҖңOft in the Stilly NightвҖқвҒ вҖ”

вҖңI feel like one
Who treads alone
Some banquet-hall deserted.вҖқ]

вҶ©

A small, snug chamber on a winterвҖҷs night,
Well furnished with a book, friend, girl, or glass, etc.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

I pass my days in long dull galleries solely.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[When this stanza was written Byron was domiciled in the Palazzo Guiccioli (in the Via di Porta Adriana) at Ravenna; but he may have had in his mind the monksвҖҷ refectory at Newstead Abbey, вҖңthe dark gallery, where his fathers frownedвҖқ (Lara, Canto I. line 137), or the corridors which form the upper story of the cloisters.] вҶ©

[вҖңNabuchodonosor,вҖқ here used metri gratiГў, is Latin (see the Vulgate) and French (see J.P. De BГ©ranger, Chansons InГ©dites, 1828, p. 48) for Nebuchadnezzar.] вҶ©

[See OvidвҖҷs Metamorphoses, lib. iv. lines 55вҒ вҖ“вҒ 58вҒ вҖ”

вҖңIn Babylon, where first her queen, for state,
Raised walls of brick magnificently great,
Lived Pyramus and Thisbe, lovely pair!
He found no Eastern youth his equal there,
And she beyond the fairest nymph was fair.вҖқ

Garth.]

вҶ©

Babylon was enlarged by Nimrod, strengthened and beautified by Nabuchadonosor, and rebuilt by Semiramis.

[Pliny (Nat. Hist., lib. viii. cap. xlii. ed. 1593, i. 392) cites Juba, King of Mauretania, died A.D. 19, as his authority for the calumny.] вҶ©

In an Erratum of her Horse for Courier.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[Queen CarolineвҒ вҖ”whose trial (AugustвҒ вҖ”November, 1820) was proceeding whilst this canto was being writtenвҒ вҖ”was charged with having committed adultery with Bartolommeo Bergami, who had been her courier, and was, afterwards, her chamberlain.] вҶ©

[вҖңMemoir on the Ruins of Babylon, by Claudius James Rich, Esq., Resident for the Honourable East India Company at the Court of the Pasha of Bagdad, 1815,вҖқ pp. 61вҒ вҖ“вҒ 64: Second Memoir on Babylon,вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ 1818, by Claudius James Rich. See the plates at the end of the volume.] вҶ©

If they shall not as soon cut off my head.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

A pair of drawersвҒ вҖ”.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[Compare вҖңExtracts from a Diary,вҖқ January 24, 1821, Letters, 1901, v. 184.] вҶ©

Kings are not more imperative than rhymes.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

He looked almost in modesty a maid.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

Features of a gateвҒ вҖ”a ministerial metaphor: вҖңthe feature upon which this question hinges.вҖқ See the вҖңFudge Family,вҖқ or hear Castlereagh.

[Phil. Fudge, in his letter to Lord Castlereagh, saysвҒ вҖ”

вҖңAs thou wouldвҖҷst say, my guide and teacher
In these gay metaphoric fringes,
I must embark into the feature
On which this letter chiefly hinges.вҖқ

MooreвҖҷs note adds, вҖңVerbatim from one of the noble ViscountвҖҷs speeches:вҒ вҖ”вҖҷAnd now, sir, I must embark into the feature on which this question chiefly hinges.вҖҷвҖҠвҖқвҒ вҖ”Fudge Family in Paris, Letter II. See, too, post, the Preface to Cantos VI., VII., and VIII., p. 264, note 3.] вҶ©

[CompareвҒ вҖ”

вҖңA snakeвҖҷs small eye blinks dull and sly,
And the ladyвҖҷs eyes they shrunk in her head,
Each shrunk up to a serpentвҖҷs eye.вҖқ

Christabel, Part II. lines 583вҒ вҖ“вҒ 585.]

вҶ©

A few years ago the wile of Muchtar Pacha complained to his father of his sonвҖҷs supposed infidelity: he asked with whom, and she had the barbarity to give in a list of the twelve handsomest women in Yanina. They were seized, fastened up in sacks, and drowned in the lake the same night. One of the guards who was present informed me, that not one of the victims uttered a cry, or showed a symptom of terror at so sudden a вҖңwrench from all we know, from all we love.вҖқ

[See The Giaour, line 1328, Poetical Works, 1900, iii. 144, note 1.] вҶ©

As Venus rose from OceanвҒ вҖ”bent on them
With a far-reaching glance, a Paphian pair.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

But there are forms which Time adorns, not wears,
And to which Beauty obstinately clings.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[Legend has credited Ninon de Lenclos (1620вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1705) with lovers when she had вҖңcome to four-score years.вҖқ According to Voltaire, John Casimir, ex-king of Poland, succumbed to her secular charms (see Mazeppa, line 138, Poetical Works, 1901, iv. 212, note 1). вҖңIn her old age, her house was the rendezvous of wits and men of letters. Scarron is said to have consulted her on his romances, Saint-Evremond on his poems, MoliГЁre on his comedies, Fontenelle on his dialogues, and La Rochefoucauld on his maxims. Coligny, SГ©vignГ©, etc., were her lovers and friends. At her death, in 1705, she bequeathed to Voltaire two thousand francs, to expend in books.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Biographic Universelle, art. вҖңLenclos.вҖқ] вҶ©

[вҖңHer fair maids were ranged below the sofa, to the number of twenty, and put me in mind of the pictures of the ancient nymphs. I did not think all nature could have furnished such a scene of beauty,вҖқ etc.вҒ вҖ”Lady M.W. Montagu to the Countess of Mar, April 18, O.S. 1717, ed. 1816, p. 163.] вҶ©

[вҖңNil admirari prope res est una, Numici,
Solaque quГҰ possit facere et servare beatum.вҖқ

Hor., Epist., lib. 1, ep. vi. lines 1, 2.]

вҶ©

[вҖңNot to admire, is all the Art I know
To make men happy, and to keep them so,
(Plain Truth, dear Murray, needs no flowвҖҷrs of speech,
So take it in the very words of Creech).вҖқ

To Mr.В Murray (Lord Mansfield), PopeвҖҷs Imitations of Horace, Book I. epist. vi. lines 1вҒ вҖ“вҒ 4.

Thomas Creech (1659вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1701) published his Translation of Horace in 1684. In the second edition, 1688, p. 487, the lines runвҒ вҖ”

вҖңNot to admire, as most are wont to do,
It is the only method that I know,
To make Men happy and to keep вҖҷem so.вҖқ]

вҶ©

[Johnson placed judgment and friendship above admiration and love. вҖңAdmiration and love are like being intoxicated with champagne; judgment and friendship like being enlivened.вҖқ See BoswellвҖҷs Life of Johnson, 1876, p. 450.] вҶ©

There is nothing, perhaps, more distinctive of birth than the hand. It is almost the only sign of blood which aristocracy can generate. вҶ©

[In old pictures of the Fall, it is a cherub who whispers into the ear of Eve. The serpentвҖҷs coils are hidden in the foliage of the tree.] вҶ©

The very women half forgave her face.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. Erased.]

вҶ©

Had his instructionsвҒ вҖ”where and how to deal.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

And husbands now and then are mystified.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[Narrow javelins, once known as archegaysвҒ вҖ”the assegais of Zulu warfare.] вҶ©

But nature teaches what power cannot spoil
And, though it was a new and strange sensation,
Young female hearts are such a genial soil
For kinder feelings, she forgot her station.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

War with your heartвҒ вҖ”.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[See FieldingвҖҷs History of the Adventures of Joseph Andrews, bk. i. chap. v.] вҶ©

[вҖңвҖҠвҖҳBut if my boy with virtue be endued,
What harm will beauty do him?вҖҷ Nay, what good?
Say, what availвҖҷd, of old, to TheseusвҖҷ son,
The stern resolve? what to Bellerophon?вҒ вҖ”
O, then did Phaedra redden, then her pride
Took fire to be so steadfastly denied!
Then, too, did Sthenobaea glow with shame,
And both burst forth with unextinguishвҖҷd flame!вҖқ

Gifford, Juvenal, Sat. x. 473вҒ вҖ“вҒ 480.

The adventures of Hippolytus, the son of Theseus, and Bellerophon are well known. They were accused of incontinence, by the women whose inordinate passions they had refused to gratify at the expense of their duty, and sacrificed to the fatal credulity of the husbands of the disappointed fair ones. It is very probable that both the stories are founded on the Scripture account of Joseph and PotipharвҖҷs wife.вҒ вҖ”Footnote, ibid., ed. 1817, ii. pp. 49, 50.] вҶ©

The poets and romancesвҒ вҖ”.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

And this strong second cause (to tire no longer
Your patience) shows the first must still be stronger.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. Alternative reading.]

вҶ©

[вҖңBy Heaven! methinks, it were an easy leap,
To pluck bright honour from the pale-faced moon.вҖқ

Henry IV., act i. sc. 3, lines 201, 202.]

вҶ©

Like natural Shakespeare on the immortal page.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[вҖңAnd when I have stolвҖҷn upon these sons-in law,
Then kill, kill, kill, kill, kill, kill.вҖқ

King Lear, act iv. sc. 6, lines 185, 186.]

вҶ©

[вҖңA woman scornвҖҷd is pitiless as fate,
For, there, the dread of shame adds stings to hate.вҖқ

GiffordвҖҷs Juvenal, Sat. x. lines 481, 482, ed. 1817, ii. p. 50.]

вҶ©

[вҖңYesвҒ вҖ”my valour is certainly going! it is sneaking off! I feel it oozing out, as it were, at the palms of my hands!вҖқвҒ вҖ”SheridanвҖҷs Rivals, act v. sc. 3.] вҶ©

Or all the stuff which uttered by the вҖңBluesвҖқ is.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

But pritheeвҒ вҖ”get my women in the way,
That all the stars may gleam with due adorning.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

Of Cantemir or KnollД“sвҒ вҖ”.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

It may not be unworthy of remark, that Bacon, in his essay on вҖңEmpireвҖқ (Essays, No. xx.), hints that Solyman was the last of his line; on what authority, I know not. These are his words: вҖңThe destruction of Mustapha was so fatal to SolymanвҖҷs line; as the succession of the Turks from Solyman until this day is suspected to be untrue, and of strange blood; for that Selymus the second was thought to be supposititious.вҖқ But Bacon, in his historical authorities, is often inaccurate. I could give half a dozen instances from his Apophthegms only.

[Selim II. (1524вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1574) succeeded his father as Sultan in 1566. Hofmann (Lexicon Univ.) describes him as вҖңmeticulosus, effeminatus, ebriosus,вҖқ but neither Demetrius Cantemir, in his History of the Growth and Decay of the Othman Empire (translated by N. Tyndal, 1734); nor The Turkish History (written by Mr.В Knolles, 1701), cast any doubts on his legitimacy. Byron complained of the omission from the notes to the first edition of Don Juan, of his corrections of BaconвҖҷs вҖңApophthegmsвҖқ (see Letters, 1901, v. Appendix VI. pp. 597вҒ вҖ“вҒ 600), in a letter to Murray, dated January 21, 1821вҒ вҖ”vide ibid., p. 220.] вҶ©

[Gibbon.] вҶ©

Because he kept them wrapt up in his closet, he
Ruled fair wives and twelve hundred whores, unseen,
More easily than Christian kings one queen.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

Then ended many a fair SultanaвҖҷs trip:
The Public knew no more than does this rhyme;
No printed scandals flewвҒ вҖ”the fish, of course,
Were betterвҒ вҖ”while the morals were no worse.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

No sign of its depression anywhere.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[вҖңWe attempted to visit the Seven Towers, but were stopped at the entrance, and informed that without a firman it was inaccessible to strangers.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ It was supposed that Count Bulukof, the Russian minister, would be the last of the Moussafirs, or imperial hostages, confined in this fortress; but since the year 1784В M. Ruffin and many of the French have been imprisoned in the same place; and the dungeonsвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ were gaping, it seems, for the sacred persons of the gentlemen composing his Britannic MajestyвҖҷs mission, previous to the rupture between Great Britain and the Porte in 1809.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Hobhouse, Travels in Albania, 1858, ii. 311, 312.] вҶ©

[вҖңThe princessвҖқ (Asma Sultana, daughter of Achmet III.) вҖңcomplained of the barbarity which, at thirteen years of age, united her to a decrepit old man, who, by treating her like a child, had inspired her with nothing but disgust.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Memoirs of Baron de Toil, 1786, i. 74. See, too, MГ©moires, etc., 1784, i. 84, 85.] вҶ©

[The connection between вҖңhornsвҖқ and Heaven, to which Byron twice alludes, is not very obvious. The reference may be to the Biblical вҖңhorn of salvation,вҖқ or to the symbolical horns of Divine glory as depicted in the Moses of Michel Angelo. Compare Mazeppa, lines 177, 178, Poetical Works, 1901, iv. 213.] вҶ©

вёәвҒ with solemn air and wise.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

Virginity in these unhappy climes.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[This stanza, which Byron composed in bed, February 27, 1821 (see Extracts from a Diary, Letters, 1901, v. 209), is not in the first edition. On discovering the omission, he wrote to Murray: вҖңUpon what principle have you omittedвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ one of the concluding stanzas sent as an addition?вҒ вҖ”because it ended, I suppose, withвҒ вҖ”

вҖҳAnd do not link two virtuous souls for life
Into that moral centaur, man and wife?вҖҷ

Now, I must say, once for all, that I will not permit any human being to take such liberties with my writings because I am absent. I desire the omissions to be replaced (except the stanza on Semiramis)вҒ вҖ”particularly the stanza upon the Turkish marriages.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Letter to Murray, August 31, 1821, ibid., p. 351.] вҶ©

Meanwhile as Homer sometimes sleeps, much more
The modern muse may be allowed to snore.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[Two MSS. (A, B) are extant, A in ByronвҖҷs handwriting, B a transcription by Mrs.В Shelley. The variants are marked respectively MS. A., MS. B.

Motto: вҖңThinkest thou that because thou art virtuous there shall be no more cakes and ale? Aye! and ginger shall be hot in the mouth too.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Twelfth Night, or What You Will, Shakespeare, act ii. sc. 3, lines 109вҒ вҖ“вҒ 112.вҒ вҖ”[MS. B.]

This motto, in an amended form, which was prefixed to the First Canto in 1833, appears on the title-page of the first edition of Cantos VI., VII., VIII., published by John Hunt in 1823.] вҶ©

[See Shakespeare, Julius CГҰsar, act iv. sc. 3, lines 216, 217.] вҶ©

[Jacob Behmen (or Boehm) stands for вҖңmystic.вҖқ Byron twice compares him with Wordsworth (see Letters, 1899, iii. 239, 1900, iv. 238).] вҶ©

Man with his head reflects (as Spurzheim tells),
But Woman with the heartвҒ вҖ”or something else.

or,

ManвҖҷs pensive part is (now and then) the head,
WomanвҖҷs the heart or anything instead.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. A. Alternative reading.]

вҶ©

Like to a CometвҖҷs tailвҒ вҖ”.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. A. erased.]

вҶ©

OвҖҷerbalance all the CГҰsarвҖҷs victories.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. A.]

Outbalance all the CГҰsarвҖҷs victories.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. B.]

In the Shelley copy вҖңoвҖҷerbalanceвҖқ has been erased and вҖңoutbalanceвҖқ inserted in ByronвҖҷs handwriting. The lines must have been intended to run thusвҒ вҖ”

вҖҳT is not his conquests keep his name in fashion
But Actium lost; for CleopatraвҖҷs eyes
Outbalance all the CГҰsarвҖҷs victories.

вҶ©

I wish that they had been eighteenвҒ вҖ”.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. A. erased.]

вҶ©

[To Mary Chaworth. Compare вҖңOur union would have healed feudsвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ it would have joined lands broad and rich; it would have joined at least one heart.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Detached Thoughts, 1821, Letters, 1901, v. 441.] вҶ©

[Cato gave up his wife Martia to his friend Hortensius; but, on the death of the latter, took her back again. This conduct was censured by CГҰsar, who observed that Cato had an eye to the main chance. вҖңIt was the wealth of Hortensius. He lent the young man his wife, that he might make her a rich widow.вҖқвҒ вҖ”LanghorneвҖҷs Plutarch, 1838, pp. 539, 547.] вҶ©

[Othello, act i. sc. i, lines 19вҒ вҖ“вҒ 24.] вҶ©

вёәвҒ though with greater latitude.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. A.]

вҶ©

вёәвҒ with one foolish woman wed.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. B.]

вҶ©

[The famous bed, measuring twelve feet square, to which an allusion is made by Shakespeare in Twelfth Night, act iii. sc. 2, line 44, was formerly preserved at the SaracenвҖҷs Head at Ware, in Hertfordshire. The bed was removed from Ware to the Rye House in 1869.] вҶ©

His Highness the sublimest of mankind,
The greatest, wisest, bravest, [and the] best,
Proved by his edicts somewhat blind,
Who saw his virtues as they saw the restвҒ вҖ”
His Highness quite connubially inclined
Had deigned that night to be GulbeyazвҖҷ guest.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. A.]

вҶ©

See Waverley [chap. xx.] вҶ©

May look like what I need not mention here

вҖ”вҒ [MS. A.]

вҶ©

Are better signs if such things can be signed.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. A.]

вҶ©

[For St.В Francis of Assisi, and the вҖңseven great balls of snow,вҖқ of which вҖңthe greatestвҖқ was вҖңhis wife,вҖқ see The Golden Legend, 1900, v. 221, vide ante, p. 32, note 1.] вҶ©

[The words medio, etc., are to be found in Ovid., Metam., lib. ii. line 137; the doctrine, Virtus est medium vitiorum, in Horace, Epist., lib. i, ep. xviii. line 9.] вҶ©

In the damned line (вҖҳt is worth, at least, a curse)
Which I have examined too close.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

Self-love that whetstone of Don CupidвҖҷs art.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. A.]

вҶ©

вёәвҒ with love despairs.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. A. erased.]

вҶ©

[Lady NoelвҖҷs will was proved February 22, 1812. She left to the trustees a portrait of ByronвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ with directions that it was not to be shown to his daughter Ada till she attained the age of twenty-one; but that if her mother was still living, it was not to be so delivered without Lady ByronвҖҷs consent.вҒ вҖ”Letters, 1901, vi. 42, note 1.] вҶ©

Which diddles youвҒ вҖ”.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. A. erased.]

вҶ©

IвҖҷm a philosopher; GвҒ вҖ”d damn them all.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. B.]

вҶ©

Bills, women, wives, dogs, horses and mankind.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. B. erased.]

вҶ©

Is more than I know, and, so, damn them both.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. A. erased.]

вҶ©

When we lie downвҒ вҖ”wife, spouse, or bachelor
By what we love not, to sigh for the light.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. A. erased.]

вҶ©

By their infernal bedfellowвҒ вҖ”.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. A. erased.]

вҶ©

[The comparison of Queen Caroline to snow may be traced to an article in the Times of August 23, 1820: вҖңThe Queen may now, we believe, be considered as triumphing! For the first three years at least of her MajestyвҖҷs painful peregrinations, she stands before her husbandвҖҷs admiring subjects вҖҳas white as unsunned snows.вҖҷвҖҠвҖқ Political bards and lampoonists of the kingвҖҷs party thanked the Times for вҖңgiving them that word.вҖқ] вҶ©

[According to Gronow (Reminiscences, 1889, i. 62), a practical joke of Dan MackinnonвҖҷs (vide ante, p. 69, footnote) gave Byron a hint for this scene in the harem: вҖңLord Wellington was curious about visiting a convent near Lisbon, and the lady abbess made no difficulty. Mackinnon hearing this contrived to get clandestinely within the sacred wallsвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ at all events, when Lord Wellington arrived Dan Mackinnon was to be seen among the nuns, dressed out in their sacred costume, with his whiskers shaved; and, as he possessed good features, he was declared to be one of the best-looking among those chaste dames. It was supposed that this adventure, which was known to Lord Byron, suggested a similar episode in Don Juan.вҖқ] вҶ©

[CaligulaвҒ вҖ”vide Suetonius, De XII. CГҰs., C. CГҰs. Calig., cap, xxx., вҖңInfensus turbГҰ faventi adversus studium exclamavit: вҖҳUtinam populus Romanus unam cervicem haberet!вҖҷвҖҠвҖқ] вҶ©

My wish were general but no worse.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. A. erased.]

вҶ©

That Womankind had only oneвҒ вҖ”say heart.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. A. erased.]

вҶ©

The ladies of the Seraglio. вҶ©

[Demetrius Cantemir, hospodar of Moldavia. His work, the History of the Growth and Decay of the Othman Empire, was translated into English by N. Tyndal, 1734. He died in 1723.] вҶ©

[Baron de Tott, in his Memoirs concerning the State of the Turkish Empire (1786, i. 72), gives the title of this functionary as Kiaya Kadun, i.e. Mistress or Governess of the Ladies.] вҶ©

[The repetition of the same rhyme-word was noted in BlackwoodвҖҷs Edinburgh Magazine, July, 1823, vol. xiv. p. 90.] вҶ©

[вҖңI guess, вҖҳt was frightful there to see
A lady so richly clad as sheвҒ вҖ”
Beautiful exceedingly.вҖқ

Christabel, Part I. lines 66вҒ вҖ“вҒ 68.]

вҶ©

вҖңIt is in the adjacent climates of Georgia, Mingrelia, and Circassia, that nature has placed, at least to our eyes, the model of beauty, in the shape of the limbs, the colour of the skin, the symmetry of the features, and the expression of the countenance: the men are formed for action, the women for love.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Gibbon, [Decline and Fall, etc., 1825, iii 126.] вҶ©

Padisha is the Turkish title of the Grand Signior. вҶ©

[Katinka was the name of the youngest sister of Theresa, the вҖңMaid of Athens.вҖқвҒ вҖ”See letter to H. Drury, May 3, 1810, Letters, 1898, i. 269, note 1; and Poetical Works, 1900, iii. 15, note 1.

It is probable that the originals of Katinka and DudГ№ were two Circassians who were presented for sale to Nicolas Ernest Kleeman (see his Voyage de Vienne, etc., 1780, pp. 142, 143) at Kaffa, in the Crimea. Of the first he writes, вҖңElle me baisa la main, et par lвҖҷordre de son maГ®tre, elle se promena en long et en large, pour me faire remarquer sa taille mince et aisГ©e. Elle avoit un joli petit pied.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ Quand elle a en ГҙtГ© son voile elle a prГ©sentГ© Г  mes yeux une beautГ© trГЁs-attrayante; ses cheveux Г©toient blonds argentГ©s; elle avoit de grands yeux bleux, le nez un peu long, et les lГЁvres appГ©tissantes. Sa figure Г©toit rГ©guliГЁre, son teint blanc, dГ©licat, les joues couvertes dвҖҷun charmant vermilion.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ La seconde Г©toit un peu petite, assez grasse, et avoit les cheveux roux, lвҖҷair sensuel et revenant.вҖқ Kleeman pretended to offer terms, took notes, and retired. But the Circassians are before us still.] вҶ©

[Macbeth, act ii. sc. 2, line 36.] вҶ©

By which no doubt its Baptism came to pass.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. A. erased.]

вҶ©

The Devil in Hell might melt but never settle.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. A. erased.]

вҶ©

[Hence the title of the satire, The Age of Bronze.] вҶ©

For WomanвҖҷs silence startles more than thunder.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. A. erased.]

вҶ©

[Compare Beppo, stanza xxii. line 2, Poetical Works, 1901, iv. 166, note 1.] вҶ©

With no less true and feminine surprise.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. A. erased.]

вҶ©

[Julius CГҰsar, act iii. sc. II, line 216.] вҶ©

[вҖңNel mezzo del cammin di nostra vita
Mi ritrovai per una selva oscura,вҖқ etc.

Inferno, Canto I, lines I, 2.]

вҶ©

Himself in an age when men grow good,
As LifeвҖҷs best half is doneвҒ вҖ”.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. A. erased.]

вҶ©

But out of reachвҒ вҖ”a most provoking sight.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. A. erased.]

вҶ©

That ere her unreluctant lips could ope.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. A.]

вҶ©

[One of the advocates employed for Queen Caroline in the House of Lords spoke of some of the most puzzling passages in the history of her intercourse with Bergami, as amounting to вҖңodd instances of strange coincidence.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Ed. 1833, xvi. 160.] вҶ©

At least as red as the FlamingoвҖҷs breast.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. A. erased.]

вҶ©

[Byron used Kaff for Caucasus, vide ante, English Bards, etc., line 1022, Poetical Works, 1898, i. 378, note 3. But there may be some allusion to the fabulous Kaff, вҖңanciently imagined by the Asiatics to surround the world, to bind the horizon on all sides.вҖқ There was a proverb вҖңFrom Kaf to Kaf,вҖқ i.e. вҖңthe wide world through.вҖқ See, too, DвҖҷHerbelotвҖҷs BibliothГЁque Orientale, 1697, art. вҖңCaf.вҖқ] вҶ©

[See L.A. Seneca, De IrГў, lib. ii. cap. 25.] вҶ©

Oh thou her lawful grandson Alexander
Let not this quality offendвҒ вҖ”.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. A. erased.]

вҶ©

[Compare The Age of Bronze, lines 434, sq., Poetical Works, 1901, v. 563, note 1.] вҶ©

To call a man a whoresonвҒ вҖ”.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. A. erased.]

вҶ©

But a manвҖҷs grandmother is deemed fair game.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. A.]

вҶ©

[It is probable that Byron knew that there was a вҖңhint of illegitimacyвҖқ in his own pedigree. John Byron of Clayton, grandfather of Richard the second Lord Byron, was born, out of wedlock, to Elizabeth, daughter of William Costerden, of Blakesley, in Lancashire, widow to George Halgh of Halgh (sic), and second wife of Sir John Byron of Clayton, вҖңlittle Sir John with the great beard.вҖқ He succeeded to Newstead and the Lancashire estates, not as heir-at-law, but by deed of gift. (See letter to Murray, October 20, 1820, Letters, 1901, v. 99, note 2.)] вҶ©

[Aubry de la Motraye, in describing the interior of the Grand SigniorвҖҷs palace, into which he gained admission as the assistant of a watchmaker who was employed to regulate the clocks, says that the eunuch who received them at the entrance of the harem, conducted them into a hall: вҖңCette salle est incrustee de porcelaines fines; et le lambris dorГ© et azurГ© qui orne le fond dвҖҷune coupole qui regne au-dessus, est des plus riches.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ Une fontaine artificielle et jaillissante, dont le bassin est dвҖҷun prГ©tieux marbre verd qui mвҖҷa paru serpentin ou jaspe, sвҖҷГ©levoit directement au milieu, sous le dГҙme.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ Je me trouvai la tГӘte si pleine de Sophas de prГ©tieux plafonds, de meubles superbes, en un mot, dвҖҷune si grande confusion de matГ©riaux magnifiques,вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ quвҖҷil seroit difficile dвҖҷen donner une idГ©e claire.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Voyages, 1727, i. 220, 222.] вҶ©

[вҖңIl nвҖҷya point de ReligieusesвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ point de novices, plus soumises Г  la volontГ© de leur abbesse que ces filles [les Odaliques] le sont Г  leurs maitresses.вҖқвҒ вҖ”A. de la Motraye, Voyages, 1727, i. 338.] вҶ©

вё»though seen not heard
For it is silent.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. A. erased.]

вҶ©

[вҖңHow fares my Kate? What! sweeting, all amort?вҖқвҒ вҖ”Taming of the Shrew, act iv. sc. 3, line 36. вҖңAmortвҖқ is said to be a corruption of Г  la mort. Byron must have had in mind his silent ecstasy of grief when the Countess Guiccioli endeavoured to break the announcement of AllegraвҖҷs death (April, 1822). вҖңвҖҠвҖҳI understand,вҖҷ said he; вҖҳit is enough; say no more.вҖҷ A mortal paleness spread itself over his face, his strength failed him, and he sunk into a seat. His look was fixed, and the expression such that I began to fear for his reason; he did not shed a tearвҖқ (Life, p. 368).] вҶ©

[вҖңHis guilty soul, at enmity with gods and men, could find no rest; so violently was his mind torn and distracted by a consciousness of guilt. Accordingly his countenance was pale, his eyes ghastly, his pace one while quick, another slow [citus modo, modo tardus incessus]; indeed, in all his looks there was an air of distraction.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Sallust, Catilina, cap. xv. sf.] вҶ©

[вҖңThese [the seventh and eighth] Cantos contain a full detail (like the storm in Canto Second) of the siege and assault of Ismael, with much of sarcasm on those butchers in large business, your mercenary soldiery.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ With these things and these fellows it is necessary, in the present clash of philosophy and tyranny, to throw away the scabbard. I know it is against fearful odds; but the battle must be fought; and it will be eventually for the good of mankind, whatever it may be for the individual who risks himself.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Letter to Moore, August 8, 1822, Letters, 1901, vi. 101.] вҶ©

[Byron attributes this phrase to Orator Henley (Letters, 1898, i. 227); and to Bayes in the Duke of BuckinghamвҖҷs play, The Rehearsal (Letters, 1901, v. 80).] вҶ©

Of Fenelon, of Calvin and of Christ.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[Compare Childe Harold, Canto II. stanza vii. line 1, Poetical Works, 1899, ii. 103, note 2.] вҶ©

Picking a pebble on the shore of Truth.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[вҖңSir Isaac Newton, a little before he died, said, вҖҳI donвҖҷt know what I may seem to the world; but, as to myself, I seem to have been only like a boy playing on the sea shore, and diverting myself in now and then finding a smoother pebble or a prettier shell than ordinary whilst the great ocean of truth lay all undiscovered before me.вҖҷвҖҠвҖқвҒ вҖ”Spence, Anecdotes (quoting Chevalier Ramsay), 1858, p. 40.] вҶ©

From fools who dread to know the truth of Life.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[Compare вҖңInscription on the Monument of a Newfoundland Dog,вҖқ lines 7, sq., Poetical Works, 1898, i. 280.] вҶ©

[Aleksandr Vasilievitch SuvГіroff (1729вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1800) opened his attack on Ismail, November 30, 1790. His forces, including Kossacks, exceeded 27,000В men.вҒ вҖ”Essai sur lвҖҷHistoire Ancienne et Moderne de la Nouvelle Russie, par le Marquis Gabriel de Castelnau, 1827, ii. 201.] вҶ©

[вҖңIsmaГ«l est situГ© sur la rive gauche du bras gauche (i.e. the ilia) du Danube.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Ibid..] вҶ©

[вҒ вёәвҖқГ  peu prГЁs Г  quatre-vingts verstes de la mer: elle a prГЁs de trois milles toises de tour.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Hist. de la Nouvelle Russie, ii. 201.] вҶ©

[вҖңOn a compris dans ces fortifications un faubourg moldave, situГ© Г  la gauche de la ville, sur une hauteur qui la domine: lвҖҷouvrage a Г©tГ© terminГ© par un Grec. Pour donner une idГ©e des talens de cet ingГ©nieur, il suffira de dire quвҖҷil fit placer les palissades perpendiculairement sur le parapet, de maniГЁre quвҖҷelles favorisaient les assiГ©geans, et arrГӘtaient le feu des assiГ©gГ©s.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Ibid., p. 202.] вҶ©

[вҖңLe rempart en terre est prodigieusement Г©levГ© Г  cause de lвҖҷimmense profondeur du fossГ©; il est cependant absolument rasant: il nвҖҷy a ni ouvrage avancГ©, ni chemin couvert.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Ibid., p. 202.] вҶ©

[Casemate is a work made under the rampart, like a cellar or cave, with loopholes to place guns in it, and is bomb proof.вҒ вҖ”Milit. Dict.] вҶ©

[When the breastwork of a battery is only of such height that the guns may fire over it without being obliged to make embrasures, the guns are said to fire in barbet.вҒ вҖ”Ibid.] вҶ©

[вҖңUn bastion de pierres, ouvert par une gorge trГЁs-Г©troite, et dont les murailles son fort Г©paisses, a une batterie casematГ©e et une Г  barbette; il dГ©fend la rive du Danube. Du cГҙtГ© droit de la ville est un cavalier de quarante pieds dвҖҷГ©lГ©vation Г  pic, garni de vingt-deux piГЁces de canon, et qui dГ©fend la partie gauche.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Hist. de la Nouvelle Russie, ii. 202.] вҶ©

[вҖңDu cГҙtГ© du fleuve, la ville est absolument ouverte; les Turcs ne croyaient pas que les Russes pussent jamais avoir une flotille dans le Danube.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Ibid., p. 203.] вҶ©

[Meknop [supposed to be a corruption of McNab], etc., in line three, are real names: Strongenoff stands for Strogonof, Tschitsshakoff for Tchitchagof, and, perhaps, Chokenoff for Tchoglokof.] вҶ©

вёәвҒ these discords of damnation.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[вҖңLa premiГЁre attaque Г©tait composГ©e de trois colonnes, commandГ©es par les lieutenans-generaux Paul Potiemkin, Serge Lwow, les gГ©nГ©raux-majors Maurice Lascy, ThГ©odore Meknop.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ Trois autres colonnesвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ avaient pour chefs le comte de SamoГҜlow, les gГ©nГ©raux ГҠlie de Bezborodko, Michel Koutousow; les brigadiers Orlow, Platow, Ribaupierre.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ La troisiГЁme attaque par eau nвҖҷavait que deux colonnes, sous les ordres des gГ©nГ©raux-majors Ribas et ArsГ©niew, des brigadiers Markoff et TchГ©pГ©ga,вҖқ etc.вҒ вҖ”Hist. de la Nouvelle Russie, ii. 207.

CompareвҒ вҖ”

вҖңOscharoffsky and Rostoffsky,
And all the others that end in-offsky.
вӢ®
And Kutousoff he cut them off,вҖқ etc.

SoutheyвҖҷs March to Moscow, 1813.]

вҶ©

[Count Boris Petrowitch Scheremetov, Russian general, died 1819; Prince Alexis Borisovitch Kourakin (1759вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1829), and Count Alexis Iwanowitch Moussine-Pouschkine (1744вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1817) were distinguished statesmen; Chrematoff is, perhaps, a rhyming double of Scherematoff, and Koklophti вҖңa match-pieceвҖқ to Koclobski.] вҶ©

[Captain Smith, in the songвҒ вҖ”

вҖңA Captain bold, in Halifax,
That dwelt in country quarters,
SeducвҖҷd a maid who hangвҖҷd herself
One Monday in her garters.вҖқ

See George ColmanвҖҷs farce, Love Laughs at Locksmiths, 1818, p. 31.] вҶ©

[CompareвҒ вҖ”

вҖңWhile to my shame I see
The imminent death of twenty thousand men,
That for a fantasy and trick of fame
Go to their graves like beds.вҖқ

Hamlet, act iv. sc. 4, lines 56вҒ вҖ“вҒ 59.]

вҶ©

The Conquest seemed not difficultвҒ вҖ”.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[вҖңOn sвҖҷГ©tait proposГ© deux buts Г©galement avantageux, par la construction de deux batteries sur lвҖҷГ®le qui avoisine IsmaГ«l: le premier, de bombarder la place, dвҖҷen abattre les principaux Г©difices avec du canon de quarante-huit, effet dвҖҷautant plus probable, que la ville Г©tant bГўtie en amphithГ©Гўtre, presque aucun coup ne serait perdu.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Hist. de la Nouvelle Russie, ii. 203.] вҶ©

[вҖңLe second objet Г©tait de profiter de ce moment dвҖҷalarme pour que la flottille, agissant en mГӘme temps, put dГ©truire celle des Turcs. Un troisiГЁme motif, et vraisemblablement le plus plausible, Г©tait de jeter la consternation parmi les Turcs, et de les engager Г  capituler.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Hist. de la Nouvelle Russie, ii. 203.] вҶ©

Unless they are as game as bull-dogs or even tarriers.

or,

A thing which sometimes hath occurred to warriors,
Unless they happened to be as game as tarriers.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. A. Alternative reading.]

Unless they are Game as bull-dogs or even terriers.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. B.]

(Byron erased the reading of MS. B. and superscribed the reading of the text.) вҶ©

[вҖңUne habitude blГўmable, celle de mГ©priser son ennemi, fut la cause.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Ibid., p. 203.] вҶ©

[вҖқвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ du dГ©faut de perfection dans la construction des batteries; on voulait agir promptement, et on nГ©gligea de donner aux ouvrages la soliditГ© quвҖҷils exigaient.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Ibid., p. 203.] вҶ©

[вҖңLe mГӘme esprit fit manquer lвҖҷeffet de trois brГ»lots; on calcula mal la distance; on se pressa dвҖҷallumer la mГ©che, ils brГ»lГЁrent au milieu du fleuve, et quoiquвҖҷil fГ»t six heures du matin, les Turcs, encore couchГ©s, nвҖҷen prirent aucun ombrage.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Hist. de la Nouvelle Russie, ii. 203.] вҶ©

[вҖң1er Dec. 1790. La flottille russe sвҖҷavanГ§a vers les sept heures; il en Г©tait neuf lorsquвҖҷelle se trouva Г  cinquante toises de la ville [dвҖҷIsmaГ«l]: elle souffrit, avec une constance calme, un feu de mitraille et de mousqueterie.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰвҖқвҒ вҖ”Ibid., p. 204.] вҶ©

[вҖқвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ prГЁs de six heuresвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ les batteries de terre secondaient la flottille; mais on reconnut alors que les canonnades ne suffiraient pas pour rГ©duire la place, on fit la retraite Г  une heure. Un lanГ§on sauta pendant lвҖҷaction, un autre dГ©riva par la force du courant, et fut pris par lвҖҷennemi.вҖқвҖҠвҖҷвҒ вҖ”Hist. de la Nouvelle Russie, ii. 204.] вҶ©

[For Delhis, see Poetical Works, 1899, ii., note 1.] вҶ©

[вҖңLes Turcs perdirent beaucoup de monde et plusieurs vaisseaux. A peine la retraite des Russes fut-elle remarquГ©e, que les plus braves dвҖҷentre les ennemis se jetГЁrent dans de petites barques et essayГЁrent une descente: le Comte de Damas les mit en fuite, et leur tua plusieurs officiers et grand nombre de soldats.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Hist. de la Nouvelle Russie, p. 204.] вҶ©

[вҖңOn ne tarirait pas si on voulait rapporter tout ce que les Russes firent de mГ©morable dans cette journГ©e; pour conter les hauts faits dвҖҷarmes, pour particulariser toutes les actions dвҖҷГ©clat, il faudrait composer des volumes.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Ibid., p. 204.] вҶ©

[вҖңParmi les Г©trangers, le prince de Ligne se distingua de maniГЁre Г  mГ©riter lвҖҷestime gГ©nГ©rale; de vrais chevaliers franГ§ais, attirГ©s par lвҖҷamour de la gloire, se montrГЁrent dignes dвҖҷelle: les plus marquans Г©taient le jeune Duc de Richelieu, les Comtes de Langeron et de Damas.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Ibid., p. 204.

Andrault, Comte de Langeron, born at Paris, January 13, 1763, on the outbreak of the Revolution (1790) took service in the Russian Army. He fought against the Swedes in 1790, and the Turks in 1791, and, after serving as a volunteer in the army of the Duke of Brunswick (1792вҒ вҖ“вҒ 93), returned to Russia, and was raised to the rank of general in 1799. He commanded a division of the Russian Army in the German campaign of 1813, and entered Paris with BlГјcher, March 30, 1814. He was afterwards Governor of Odessa and of New Russia; and, a second time, fought against the Turks in 1828. He died at St.В Petersburg, July 4, 1831. Joseph Elizabeth Roger, Comte de Damas dвҖҷAntigny, born at Paris, September 4, 1765, owed his commission in the Russian Army to the influence of the Prince de Ligne. He fought against the Turks in 1787вҒ вҖ“вҒ 88, and was distinguished for bravery and daring. At the Restoration in 1814 he re-entered the French Army, was made Governor of Lyons; shared the temporary exile of Louis XVIII. at Ghent in 1815, and, in the following year, as commandant of a division, took part in repressing the revolutionary disturbances in the central and southern departments of France. He died at Cirey, September 3, 1823.вҒ вҖ”La Grande EncyclopГ©die.] вҶ©

[Charles Joseph, Prince de Ligne, was born at Brussels, May 12, 1735. In 1782 he visited St.В Petersburg as envoy of the Emperor Joseph II., won CatherineвҖҷs favour, and was appointed Field Marshal in the Russian Army. In 1788 he was sent to assist Potemkin at the siege of Ochakof. His MГ©langes Militaires, etc., were first published in 1795. He died in November, 1814.

Josef de Ribas (1737-c. 1797).] вҶ©

[вҖңLвҖҷAmiral de RibasвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ dГ©clara, en plein conseil, que ce nвҖҷГ©tait quвҖҷen donnant lвҖҷassaut quвҖҷon obtiendrait la place: cet avis parut hardi; on lui opposa mille raisons, auxquelles il rГ©pondit par de meilleures.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Hist. de la Nouvelle Russie, ii, 205.] вҶ©

[Prince (Gregor Alexandrovitch) Potemkin, born 1736, died October 15, 1791. вҖңHe alighted from his carriage in the midst of the highway, threw himself on the grass, and died under a treeвҖқ (Life of Catherine II., by W. Tooke, 1880, iii. 324). His character has been drawn by Louis Philippe, Comte de SГ©gur, who, writes Tooke (ibid., p. 326), вҖңlived a long time in habits of intimacy with him, and was so obliging as to delineate it at our solicitation.вҖқ вҖңIn his person were collected the most opposite defects and advantages of every kind. He was avaricious and ostentatious,вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ haughty and obliging, politic and confiding, licentious and superstitious, bold and timid, ambitious and indiscreet; lavish of his bounties to his relations, his mistresses, and his favourites, yet frequently paying neither his household nor his creditors. His consequence always depended on a woman, and he was always unfaithful to her. Nothing could equal the activity of his mind, nor the indolence of his body. No dangers could appal his courage; no difficulties force him to abandon his projects. But the success of an enterprise always brought on disgust.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ Everything with him was desultory; business, pleasure, temper, carriage. His presence was a restraint on every company. He was morose to all that stood in awe of him, and caressed all such as accosted him with familiarity.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ None had read less than he; few people were better informed.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ One while he formed the project of becoming Duke of Courland; at another he thought of bestowing on himself the crown of Poland. He frequently gave intimations of an intention to make himself a bishop, or even a simple monk. He built a superb palace, and wanted to sell it before it was finished. In his youth he had pleased her [Catherine] by the ardour of his passion, by his valour, and by his masculine beauty.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ Become the rival of Orloff, he performed for his sovereign whatever the most romantic passion could inspire. He put out his eye, to free it from a blemish which diminished his beauty. Banished by his rival, he ran to meet death in battle, and returned with glory.вҖқ] вҶ©

[вҖңCe projet, remis Г  un autre jour, Г©prouva encore les plus grandes difficultГ©s; son courage les surmonta: il ne sвҖҷagГӯssait que de dГ©terminer le Prince Potiemkin; il y rГ©ussit. Tandis quвҖҷil se dГ©menait pour lвҖҷexГ©cution de projet agrГ©Г©, on construisait de nouvelles batteries; on comptait, le 12 dГ©cembre, quatre-vingts piГЁces de canon sur le bord du Danube, et cette journГ©e se passa en vives canonnades.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Histoire de la Nouvelle Russie, ii. 205.] вҶ©

Into all aspirants for martial praise.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[вҖңLe 13e, une partie des troupes Г©tait embarquГ©e; on allait lever le siГЁge: un courrier arrive.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ Ce courrier annonce, de la part du prince, que le marГ©chal Souwarow va prendre le commandement des forces rГ©unies sous IsmaГ«l.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Ibid., p. 205.] вҶ©

[вҖңLa lettre du Prince Potiemkin Г  Souwarow est trГЁs courte; elle peint le caractere de ces deux personnages. La voici dans toute sa teneur: вҖҳVous prendrez IsmaГ«l Г  quel frix que ce soit!вҖҷвҖңвҒ вҖ”Hist, de la Nouvelle Russie, ii. 205.] вҶ©

[вҖң[Le courrier] est tГ©moin des cris de joie du Turc, qui se croyait Г  la fin de ses maux.вҖқ-Ibid., p. 205.] вҶ©

[вҖңBeat,вҖқ as in вҖңdead-beat,вҖқ is occasionally used for вҖңbeaten.вҖқвҒ вҖ”See N.E.D., art. вҖңBeat,вҖқ 10.] вҶ©

[вҖңLe 16e, on voit venir de loin deux hommes courant Г  toute bride: on les prit pour des Kozaks; lвҖҷun Г©tait Souwarow, et lвҖҷautre son guide, portant un paquet gros comme le poing, et renfermant le bagage du gГ©nГ©ral.вҖқ-Hist, de la Nouvelle Russie, ii. 205.

M. de Castelnau in his description of the arrival of SuvГіroff on the field of battle (Hist, de la N.R., 1827, ii. pp, 205, 206) summarizes the Journal of the Duc de Richelieu. The original passage runs as follows:вҒ вҖ”

вҖңLвҖҷarrivГ©e du comte Souvorow produisit un grand effet parmi les troupes.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ La maniГЁre dвҖҷГӘtre plus que simple, puis-quвҖҷil logeait sous une canonniГЁre, et quвҖҷil nвҖҷavait pas mГӘme de chaises dans sa tente, son affabilitГ©, sa bonhomie lui conciliaient lвҖҷaffection de tous les individus de son armГ©e. Cet homme singulier qui ressemble plus Г  un chef de cosaques ou de Tartares, quвҖҷau gГ©nГ©ral dвҖҷune armГ©e europГ©enne, est douГ© dвҖҷune intrГ©piditГ© et dвҖҷune hardiesse peu communes.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ La maniГЁre de vivre, de sвҖҷhabiller et de parler du comte Souvorow, est aussi singuliГЁre que ses opinions militaires.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ Il mangeait dans sa tente assis par terre autour dвҖҷune natte sur laquelle il prenait le plus dГ©testable repas. LвҖҷaprГЁs-midi, un semblable repas lui servait de souper, il sвҖҷendormait ensuite pendant quelques heures, passait une partie de la nuit Г  chanter, et a la pointe du jour il sortait presque nu et se roulait sur lвҖҷherbe assurant que cet exercice lui Г©tait necessaire pour le prГ©server des rhumatismes.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ Sa maniГЁre de sвҖҷexprimer dans toutes les langues est aussi singuliГЁre que toute sa faГ§on dвҖҷГӘtre, ses phrases sont incohГ©rentes, et sвҖҷil nвҖҷest pas insensГ©, il dit et fait du moins tout ce quвҖҷil faut pour le paraГ®tre; mais il est heureux et cette qualitГ© dont le Cardinal Mazarin faisait tant de cas, est, Г  bon droit, fort estimГ©e de lвҖҷImpГ©ratrice et du Prince PotemkinвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ Le moment de lвҖҷarrivГ©e du Comte Souvorow fut annoncГ© par une dГ©charge gГ©nГ©rale des batteries ou camp et de la flotte.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Journal de mon Voyage en Allemagne. Soc, Imp. dвҖҷHist de Russie, 1886, tom. liv. pp. 168, 169.] вҶ©

That sage John BullвҒ вҖ”.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

That fool John BullвҒ вҖ”.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[вҖңLa premiГЁre attaque Г©tait composГ©e de trois colonnesвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ Trois autres colonnes, destinГ©es a la seconde attaque, avaient pour chefs, etc.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ La troisiГЁme attaque par eau nвҖҷavait que deux colonnes.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Hist, de la Nouvelle Russie, ii. 207.] вҶ©

[вҖңOn construisit de nouvelles batteries le 18e.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ On tint un conseil de guerre, on y examina les plans pour lвҖҷassaut proposГ©s par M. de Ribas, ils rГ©unirent tous les souffrages.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Ibid., p. 208.] вҶ©

For once by some odd sort of magnanimity.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

Bellona shook her spear with much sublimity.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

Fact: Suwaroff did this in person. вҶ©

вёәвҒ and neither swerve nor spill.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[вҖңLe 19e et le 20e, Souwarow exerГ§ailes soldats; il leur montra comment il fallait sвҖҷy prendre pour escalader; il enseigna aux recrues la maniГЁre de donner le coup de baГҜonnette.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Ibid., p. 208.] вҶ©

[вҖңPour ces exercices dвҖҷun nouveau genre, il se servit de fascines disposГ©es de maniГЁre a reprГ©senter un Turc.вҖқ-Hist, de la Nauvelle Russie, ii. 208.] вҶ©

At which your wise men laughed, but all their Wit is
Lost, for his repartee was taking cities.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

For some were thinking of their wives and families,
And others of themselves (as poet Samuel is).

вҖ”вҒ [MS. Alternative reading.]

And others of themselves (as my friend Samuel is).

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[For a detailed account of SuvГіroffвҖҷs personal characteristics, see The Life of Field-Marshal Souvaroff, by L.M.P. Tranchant de Laverne, 1814, pp. 267вҒ вҖ“вҒ 291; and SuvГіroff, by Lieut.-Colonel Spalding, 1890, pp. 222вҒ вҖ“вҒ 229.

ByronвҖҷs epithet вҖңbuffoonвҖқ (line 5) may, perhaps, be traced to the following anecdote recorded by Tranchant de Laverne (p. 281): вҖңDuring the first war of PolandвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ he published, in the order of the day, that at the first crowing of the cock the troops would march to attack the enemy, and caused the spy to send word that the Russians would be upon them some time after midnight. But about eight oвҖҷclock Souvarof ran through the camp, imitating the crowing of a cock.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ The enemy, completely surprised, lost a great number of men.вҖқ

For his вҖңprayingвҖқ (line 6), vide ibid., pp. 272, 273: вҖңHe made a short prayer after each meal, and again when going to bed. He usually performed his devotions before an image of St.В Nicholas, the patron saint of Russia.вҖқ

вҖңHalf-dirtвҖқ (line 5) is, however, a calumny (ibid. p. 272): вҖңIt was his custom to rise at the earliest dawn; several buckets of cold water were thrown over his naked body.вҖқ

The same writer (p. 268) repudiates the charges of excessive barbarity and cruelty brought against SuvГіroff by C.F.P. Masson, in his MГ©moires Secrets sur la Russie (vide, e.g., ed. 1800, i. 311): вҖңSouvorow ne scroit que le plus ridicule bouffon, sвҖҷil nвҖҷГ©toit pas montrГ© le plus barbare guerrier. CвҖҷest un monstre, qui renferme dans le corps dвҖҷun singe lвҖҷГўme dвҖҷun chien de boucher. Attila, son compatriote, et donвҖҷt il descend, peut-ГӘtre ne fut ni si heureux, ni si fГ©roce.вҖқ

SuvГіroff did not regard himself as вҖңhalf-demon.вҖқ вҖңYour pencil,вҖқ he reminded the artist MГјller, вҖңwill delineate the features of my face. These are visible: but my inner man is hidden. I must tell you that I have shed rivers of blood. I tremble, but I love my neighbour. In my whole life I have made no one unhappy; not an insect hath perished by my hand. I was little; I was big. In fortuneвҖҷs ebb and flow, relying on God, I stood immovableвҒ вҖ”even as now.вҖқ (SuvГіroff, 1890, p. 228, note.)] вҶ©

[See, for instance, The Storm, in вҖңSouvarofвҖҷs Catechism,вҖқ Appendix (pp. 299вҒ вҖ“вҒ 305) to the Life, etc., by Tranchant de Laverne, 1814: вҖңBreak down the fence.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ Fly over the walls! Stab them on the ramparts!вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ Fire down the streets! Fire briskly!вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ Kill every enemy in the streets! Let the cavalry hack them!вҖқ etc.] вҶ©

[The вҖңtuskвҖқ of the plough is the coulter or share. Compare вҖңDens vomerisвҖқ (Virg., Georg., i. 22).] вҶ©

Of thine imaginary deathless bough
The unebbing sea of blood and tears must flow.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

Entailed upon HumanityвҖҷs estate.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

As a brookвҖҷs stream to cope with OceanвҖҷs flood shed
But still we moderns equal you in bloodshed.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

As in a GeneralвҖҷs letter when well whacked
Whatever deeds be done I will relate вҖҷem,
With some small variations in the text
Of killed and wounded who will not be missed.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

Whose leisure hours are wasted on an harlot.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

The desperate death-cry and the BattleвҖҷs roar.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

End of Canto 7. 1822.вҒ вҖ”[MS.] вҶ©

[вҖңLa nuit Г©tait obscure; un brouillard Г©pais ne nous permettait de distinguer autre chose que le feu de notre artillerie, dont lвҖҷhorizon Г©tait embrasГ© de tous cГҙtГ©s: ce feu, partant du milieu du Danube, se rГ©flГ©chissait sur les eaux, et offrait un coup dвҖҷoeil trГЁs-singulier.вҖқ-Hist. de la Nouvelle Russie, ii. 209.] вҶ©

[вҖңГҖ peine eut-on parcouru lвҖҷespace de quelques toises au-delГ  des batteries, que les Turcs, qui nвҖҷavaient point tirГ© pendant toute la nuit sвҖҷapperГ§evant de nos mouvemens, commencГЁrent de leur cГҙtГ© un feu trГЁs-vif, qui embrasa le reste de lвҖҷhorizon: mais ce fut bien autre chose lorsque, avancГ©s davantage, le feu de la mousqueterie commenГ§a dans toute lвҖҷГ©tendue du rempart que nous appercevions. Ce fut alors que la place parut Г  nos yeux comme un volcan dont le feu sortait de toutes parts.вҖқ-Hist. de la Nouvelle Russie, ii. 209.] вҶ©

[вҖңUn cri universel dвҖҷallah, qui se rГ©pГ©tait tout autour de la ville, vint encore rendre plus extraordinaire cet instant, dont il est impossible de se faire une idГ©e.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Ibid., p. 209.] вҶ©

Allah Hu! is properly the war-cry of the Mussulmans, and they dwell on the last syllable, which gives it a wild and peculiar effect.

[See The Giaour, line 734, Poetical Works, 1900, iii. 120, note 1; see, too, Siege of Corinth, line 713, ibid., p. 481.] вҶ©

[вҖңToutes les colonnes Г©taient en mouvement; celles qui attaquaient par eau commandГ©es par le gГ©nГ©ral ArsГ©niew, essuyГЁrent un feu Г©pouvantable, et perdirent avant le jour un tiers de leurs officiers.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Hist. de la Nouvelle Russie, ii. 209.] вҶ©

вҖңBut Thy[*] most dreaded instrument,
In working out a pure intent,
Is ManвҒ вҖ”arrayed for mutual slaughterвҒ вҖ”
Yea, Carnage is thy daughter!вҖқ

WordsworthвҖҷs Thanksgiving Ode (January 18, 1816), stanza xii. lines 20, 23.

[*]To wit, the DeityвҖҷs: this is perhaps as pretty a pedigree for murder as ever was found out by Garter King at Arms.вҒ вҖ”What would have been said, had any free-spoken people discovered such a lineage?

[Wordsworth omitted the lines in the last edition of his poems, which was revised by his own hand.] вҶ©

The Duc de RichelieuвҒ вҖ”.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[вҖңLe Prince de Ligne fut blessГ© au genou; le Duc de Richelieu eut une balle entre le fond de son bonnet et sa tГӘte.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Hist. de la Nouvelle Russie, ii. 210.

For the gallantry of Prince Charles de Ligne (died September 14, 1792) eldest son of Prince Charles Joseph de Ligne (1735вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1814), see The Prince de Ligne, 1899, ii. 46.

Armand Emanuel du Plessis, Duc de Richelieu, born 1767, a grandson of Louis FranГ§ois Duc de Richelieu, the Marshal of France (1696вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1780), served under Catherine II., and afterwards under the Czar Paul. On the restoration of Louis XVIII. he entered the KingвҖҷs household; and after the battle of Waterloo took office as President of the Council and Minister for Foreign Affairs. His Journal de mon Voyage en Allemagne, which was then unpublished, was placed at the disposal of the Marquis de Castelnau (see Hist. de la Nouvelle Russie, 1827, i. 241). It has been printed in full by the SociГ©tГ© ImpГ©riale dвҖҷHistoire de Russie, 1886, tom. liv. pp. 111вҒ вҖ“вҒ 198. See for further mention of the manuscript, Le Duc de Richelieu, par Raoul de Cisternes, 1898, Preface, p. 3, note 1. He died May 17, 1822, two months before Cantos VI., VII., VIII. were completed.] вҶ©

[вҖңLe brigadier Markow, insistant pour quвҖҷon emportГўt le prince blessГ©, reГ§ut un coup de fusil qui lui fracassa le pied.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Hist. de la Nouvelle Russie, ii. 210.] вҶ©

[вҖңTrois cents bouches Г  feu vomissaient sans interruption, et trente mille fusils alimentaient sans relГЎche une grГӘle de balles.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Ibid., p. 210.] вҶ©

[вҖңLes troupes, dГ©ja dГ©barquГ©es, se portГЁrent ГЎ droite pour sвҖҷemparer dвҖҷune batterie; et celles dГ©barquГ©es plus bas, principalement composГ©es des grenadiers de Fanagorie, escaladaient le retranchement et la palissade.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Hist. de la Nouvelle Russie, ii. 210.] вҶ©

A fact: see the Waterloo Gazettes. I recollect remarking at the time to a friend:вҒ вҖ”вҖқThere is fame! a man is killed, his name is Grose, and they print it Grove.вҖқ I was at college with the deceased, who was a very amiable and clever man, and his society in great request for his wit, gaiety, and вҖңChansons Г  boire.вҖқ

[In the London Gazette Extraordinary of June 22, 1815, Captain Grove, 1st Guards, is among the list of killed. In the supplement to the London Gazette, published July 3, 1815, the mistake was corrected, and the entry runs, вҖң1st Guards, 3d Batt. Lieut.В Edward Grose, (Captain).вҖқ I am indebted to the courtesy of the Registrar of the University of Cambridge for the information that Edward Grose matriculated at St.В JohnвҖҷs College as a pensioner, December 7, 1805. Thanks to the вҖңmisprintвҖқ in the Gazette, and to Byron, he is вҖңa name for ever.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Vir nullГў non donatus lauru!] вҶ©

[At the Battle of Mollwitz, April 10, 1741, вҖңthe king vanishes for sixteen hours into the regions of Myth вҖҳinto Fairyland,вҖҷвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ of the kingвҖҷs flightвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ the king himself, who alone could have told us fully, maintained always rigorous silence, and nowhere drops the least hint. So that the small fact has come down to us involved in a great bulk of fabulous cobwebs, mostly of an ill-natured character, set a-going by Voltaire, Valori, and others.вҖқвҒ вҖ”CarlyleвҖҷs Frederick the Great, 1862, iii. 314, 322, sq.] вҶ©

See General Valancey and Sir Lawrence Parsons.

[Charles Vallancey (1721вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1812), general in the Royal Engineers, published an вҖңEssay on the Celtic Language,вҖқ etc., in 1782. вҖңThe language [the Iberno-Celtic],вҖқ he writes (p. 4), вҖңwe are now going to explain, had such an affinity with the Punic, that it may be said to have been, in a great degree, the language of Hanibal (sic), Hamilcar, and of Asdrubal.вҖқ Sir Laurence Parsons (1758вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1841), second Earl of Rosse, represented the University of Dublin 1782вҒ вҖ“вҒ 90, and afterwards KingвҖҷs County, in the Irish House of Commons. He was an opponent of the Union. In a pamphlet entitled Defence of the Antient History of Ireland, published in 1795, he maintains (p. 158) вҖңthat the Carthaginian and the Irish language being originally the same, either the Carthaginians must have been descended from the Irish, or the Irish from the Carthaginians.вҖқ] вҶ©

The Portuguese proverb says that вҖңhell is paved with good intentions.вҖқвҒ вҖ”[See Vision of Judgment, stanza xxxvii. line 8, Poetical Works, 1901, iv. 499, note 2.] вҶ©

At least the sharp faints of that вҖңburning marle.вҖқ

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[вҖңThe Nervii marched to the number of sixty thousand, and fell upon CГҰsar, as he was fortifying his camp, and had not the least notion of so sudden an attack. They first routed his cavalry, and then surrounded the twelfth and the seventh legions, and killed all the officers. Had not CГҰsar snatched a buckler from one of his own men, forced his way through the combatants before him, and rushed upon the barbarians; or had not the tenth legion, seeing his danger, ran from the heights where they were posted, and mowed down the enemyвҖҷs ranks, not one Roman would have survived the battle.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Plutarch, CГҰsar, LanghorneвҖҷs translation, 1838, p. 502.] вҶ©

[вҖңAs near a field of corn, a stubborn assвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ
EвҖҷen so great Ajax son of Telamon.вҖқ

The Iliad, Lord DerbyвҖҷs translation, bk. xi. lines 639, 645.]

вҶ©

Nor care a single damn about his corps.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[вҖңNвҖҷapercevant plus le commandant du corps dont je faisais partie, et ignorant oГ№ je devais porter mes pas, je crus reconnaГ®tre le lieu oГ№ le rempart Г©tait situГ©; on y faisait un feu assez vif, que je jugeai ГӘtre celuiвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ du gГ©nГ©ral-major de Lascy.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Hist. de la Nouvelle Russie, ii. 210. The speaker is the Duc de Richelieu. See, for original, his Journal de mon Voyage, etc., Soc. Imp. dвҖҷHist. de Russie, tom. liv. p. 179] вҶ©

For he was dizzy, busy, and his blood
Lightening along his veins, and where he heard
The liveliest fire, and saw the fiercest flood
Of Friar BaconвҖҷs mild discovery, shared
By Turks and Christians equally, he could
No longer now resist the attraction of gunpowder
But flew to where the merry orchestra played louder.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

Gunpowder is said to have been discovered by this friar. [N.B. Though Friar Bacon seems to have discovered gunpowder, he had the humanity not to record his discovery in intelligible language.] вҶ©

вёәвҒ whose short breath, and long faces
Kept always pushing onwards to the Glacis.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[I Henry IV., act iii. sc. 1, line 53.] вҶ©

And that mechanic impulseвҒ вҖ”.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[Hamlet, act iii, sc. 1, lines 79, 80.] вҶ©

[вҖңTalus: the slope or inclination of a wall, whereby, reclining at the top so as to fall within its base, the thickness is gradually lessened according to the height.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Milit. Dict.] вҶ©

[вҖңAppelant ceux des chasseurs qui Г©taient autour de moi en assez grand nombre, je mвҖҷavanГ§ai et reconnus ne mвҖҷГӘtre point trompГ© dans mon calcul; cвҖҷГ©tait en effet cette colonne qui Г  lвҖҷinstant parvenait au sommet du rempart. Les Turcs de derriГЁre les travers et les flancs des bastions voisins fasaient sur elle un feu trГЁs-vif de canon et de mousqueterie. Je gravis, avec les gens qui mвҖҷavaient suivi, le talus intГ©rieur du rempart.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Hist. de la Nouvelle Russie, ii. 210.] вҶ©

[Baron Menno van Coehoorn (circ. 1641вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1704), a Dutch military engineer, the contemporary and rival of Vauban, invented a mortar which bore his name. He was the author of a celebrated work on fortification, published in 1692.] вҶ©

[вҖңCe fut dans cet instant que je reconnus combien lвҖҷignorance du constructeur des palissades Г©tait importante pour nous; car, comme elles Г©taient placГ©es au milieu du parapet,вҖқ etc.вҒ вҖ”Hist. de la Nouvelle Russie, ii. 211.] вҶ©

They were but two feet above the level.вҒ вҖ”[MS.]

[вҖңIl y avait de chaque cГҙtГ© neuf Г  dix pieds sur lesquels on pouvait marcher; et les soldats, aprГЁs ГӘtre montГ©s, avaient pu se ranger commodГ©ment sur lвҖҷespace extГ©rieur et enjamber ensuite les palissades, qui ne sвҖҷГ©levaient que dвҖҷГ -peu-prГЁs deux pieds au-dessus du niveau de la terre.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Ibid., p. 211.] вҶ©

[Friederich Wilhelm, Baron von BГјlow (1755вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1816), was in command of the 4th corps of the Prussian Army at Waterloo. August Wilhelm Antonius Neidhart von Gneisenau (1760вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1831) was chief of staff, and after BlГјcher was disabled by a fall at Ligny, assumed temporary command, June 16вҒ вҖ“вҒ 17, 1815. He headed the triumphant pursuit of the French on the night of the battle. For BlГјcherвҖҷs official account of the battles of Ligny and Waterloo (subscribed by Gneisenau), see W.H. MaxwellвҖҷs Life of the Duke of Wellington, 1841, iii. 566вҒ вҖ“вҒ 571; and for WellingtonвҖҷs acknowledgment of BlГјcherвҖҷs вҖңcordial and timely assistance,вҖқ see Dispatches, 1847, viii. 150. See, too, The Life of Wellington, by the Right Hon.В Sir Herbert Maxwell, Bart., 1899, ii. 88, et passim.] вҶ©

вёәвҒ as feminine of feature.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

Led him onвҒ вҖ”although he was the gentlest creature,
As kind in heart as feminine of feature.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[PistolвҖҷs вҖңBezonianвҖқ is a corruption of bisognosoвҒ вҖ”a rogue, needy fellow. Byron, quoting from memory, confuses two passages. In 2 Henry VI., act iv. sc. 1, line 134, Suffolk says, вҖңGreat men oft die of vile bezonians;вҖқ in 2 Henry IV., act v. sc. 3, line 112, Pistol says, вҖңUnder which King, Besonian? speak or die.вҖқ] вҶ©

[вҖңLe GГ©nГ©ral Lascy, voyant arriver un corps, si Г -propos Г  son secours, sвҖҷavanГ§a vers lвҖҷofficier qui lвҖҷavait conduit, et, le prenant pour un Livonien, lui fit, en allemand, les complimens les plus flatteurs; le jeune militaire (le Duc de Richelieu) qui parlait parfaitement cette langue, y rГ©pondit avec sa modestie ordinaire.вҖқ-Hist. de la Nouvelle Russie, ii. 211.] вҶ©

[The Task, bk. i. line 749. It was pointed out to Cowper that the same thought had been expressed by Isaac Hawkins Browne, in The Fire-side, a Pastoral Soliloquy, lines 15, 16 (Poems, ed. 1768, p. 125)вҒ вҖ”

вҖңI have said it at home, I have said it abroad,
That the town is ManвҖҷs world, but that this is of God.вҖқ

There is a parallel passage in M.T. Varro, Rerum Rusticarum, lib. iii. I. 4, вҖңNee minim, quod divina natura dedit agros, ars humami aedificavit urbes.вҖқвҒ вҖ”See The Task, etc., ed. by H.T. Griffith, 1896, ii. 234.] вҶ©

[Sulla spoke of himself as the вҖңfortunate,вҖқ and in the twenty-second book of his Commentaries, finished only two days before his death, вҖңhe tells us that the Chaldeans had predicted, that after a life of glory he would depart in the height of his prosperity.вҖқ He was fortunate, too, with regard to his funeral, for, at first, a brisk wind blew which fanned the pile into flame, and it was not till the fire had begun to die out that the rain, which had been expected throughout the day, began to fall in torrents.вҒ вҖ”LanghorneвҖҷs Plutarch, 1838, pp. 334, 335. See, too, Ode to Napoleon Buonaparte, stanza vii. Poetical Works, 1900, in. 308, note I.] вҶ©

[Daniel Boone (1735вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1820) was the grandson of an English settler, George Boone, of Exeter. His great work in life was the conquest of Kentucky. Following in the steps of another pioneer, John Finley, he left his home in North Carolina in May, 1769, and, after numerous adventures, effected a settlement on the Kentucky river. He constructed a fort, which he named Boonesborough, and carried on a protracted campaign with varying but final success against the Indians. When Kentucky was admitted into the Union, February 4, 1791, he failed to make good his title to his property at Boonesborough, and withdrew to Mount Pleasant, beyond the Ohio. Thence, in 1795, he removed to Missouri, then a Spanish possession. Napoleon wrested Missouri from the Spaniards, only to sell the territory to the United States, with the result that in 1810 he was confirmed in the possession of 850 out of the 8000 acres which he had acquired in 1795. вҖңBoone was then seventy-five years of age, hale and strong. The charm of the hunterвҖҷs life clung to him to the last, and in his eighty-second year he went on a hunting excursion to the mouth of the Kansas river.вҖқвҒ вҖ”AppletonвҖҷs Encyclopedia, etc., art. вҖңBoone.вҖқ His fine and gracious nature reveals itself in his autobiography (The Adventures of Colonel Daniel Boon, Formerly a Hunter; Containing a Narrative of the Wars of Kentucky; ImlayвҖҷs North America, 1793, ii. 52вҒ вҖ“вҒ 54). вҖңOne day,вҖқ he writes (pp. 330, sq.), вҖңI undertook a tour through the country, and the diversity and beauties of natureвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ expelled every gloomy and vexatious thought. Just at the close of day the gentle gales retired, and left the place to the disposal of a profound calm. Not a breeze shook the most tremulous leaf. I had gained the summit of a commanding ridge, and, looking round with astonishing delight, beheld the ample plains, the beauteous tracts below. On the other hand, I surveyed the famous river Ohio, that rolled in silent dignity, marking the western boundary of Kentucky with inconceivable grandeur.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ All things were still. I kindled a fire near a fountain of sweet water, and feasted on the loins of a buck, which a few hours before I had killed.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ No populous city, with all the varieties of commerce and stately structures, could afford so much pleasure to my mind as the beauties of nature I found here.вҖқ (See, too, The Kentucky Pioneers, by John Brown, HarperвҖҷs New Monthly Magazine, 1887, vol. lxxv. pp. 48вҒ вҖ“вҒ 71.)] вҶ©

[For John Kyrle, вҖңthe Man of RossвҖқ (1635вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1724), see PopeвҖҷs Moral Essays, epist. iii. lines 249вҒ вҖ“вҒ 284. See, too, Letters of S.T. Coleridge, 1895 (letter to R. Southey, July 13, 1794), i. 77.] вҶ©

[Byron seems to have derived his knowledge of CatherineвҖҷs vie intime from the MГ©moires Secrets sur la Russie, of C.F.P. Masson, which were published in Amsterdam in 1800, and translated into English in the same year.] вҶ©

[Michailo Smolenskoi Koutousof (1743вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1813), who was raised to eminence through the influence of Potemkin, was in command of the Austro-Russian Army at Austerlitz. During the retreat from Moscow he repulsed Napoleon at Malo-yaroslavetz, and pursued the French to Kalisz. Tolstoi introduces Koutousof in his novel, War and Peace, and dwells on his fatalism.] вҶ©

[вҖңParmi les colonnes, une de celles qui souffrirent le plus Г©tait commandГ©e par le gГ©nГ©ral Koutouzow (aujourdвҖҷhui Prince de Smolensko). Ce brave militaire rГ©unit lвҖҷintrГ©piditГ© Г  un grand nombre de connaissances acquises; il marche au feu avec la mГӘme gaГ®etГ© quвҖҷil va Г  une fГӘte; il sait commander avec autant de sang froid quвҖҷil dГ©ploie dвҖҷesprit et dвҖҷamabilitГ© dans le commerce habituel de la vie.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Hist. de la Nouvelle Russie, ii. 212.] вҶ©

[вҖңCe brave Koutouzow se jeta dans le fossГ©, fut suivi des siens, et ne pГ©nГ©tra jusquвҖҷau haut du parapet quвҖҷaprГЁs avoir Г©prouvГ© des difficultГ©s incroyables. (Le brigadier de Ribaupierre perdit la vie dans cette occasion: il avail fixГ© lвҖҷestime gГ©nГ©rale, et sa mort occasionna beaucoup de regrets.) Les Turcs accoururent en grand nombre; cette multitude repoussa deux fois le gГ©nГ©ral jusquвҖҷau fossГ©.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Ibid., p. 212.] вҶ©

[вҖңQuelques troupes russes, emportГ©es par le courant, nвҖҷayant pu dГ©barquer sur le terrain quвҖҷon leur avait prescrit,вҖқ etc.вҒ вҖ”Ibid., p. 213.] вҶ©

[вҖңA вҖҳCavalierвҖҷ is an elevation of earth, situated ordinarily in the gorge of a bastion, bordered with a parapet, and cut into more or fewer embrasures, according to its capacity.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Milit. Dict.] вҶ©

[вҖқвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ longГЁrent le rempart, aprГЁs la prise du cavalier, et ouvrirent la porte dite de Kilia aux soldats du gГ©nГ©ral Koutouzow.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Hist, de la Nouvelle Russie, ii. 213.] вҶ©

[вҖңIl Г©tait rГ©servГ© aux Kozaks de combler de leurs corps la partie du fossГ© oГ№ ils combattaient; leur colonne avail Г©tГ© divisГ©e entre MM.В Platow et dвҖҷOrlowвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰвҖқвҒ вҖ”Ibid., p. 213.] вҶ©

[вҖқвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ la premiГЁre partie, devant se joindre Г  la gauche du gГ©nГ©ral ArsГ©niew, fut foudroyГ©e par le feu des batteries, et parvint nГ©anmoins au haut du rempart.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Ibid., p. 213.] вҶ©

[вҖңLes Turcs la laissГЁrent un peu sвҖҷavancer, dans la ville, et firent deux sorties par les angles saillans des bastions.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Ibid., p. 213.] вҶ©

Fatal to warriors as to womenвҒ вҖ”these.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[вҖңAlors, se trouvant prise en queue, elle fut Г©crasГ©e; cependant le Lieutenant-colonel YesouskoГҜ, qui commandait la rГ©serve composГ©e dвҖҷun bataillon du rГ©giment de Polozk, traversa le fossГ© sur les cadavres des KozaksвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰвҖқвҒ вҖ”Hist. de la Nouvell Russia, ii. 212.] вҶ©

[вҖқвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ et extermina tous les Turcs quвҖҷil eut en tГӘte: ce brave homme fut tuГ© pendant lвҖҷaction.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Ibid., p. 213.] вҶ©

[вҖңLвҖҷautre partie des Kozaks, quвҖҷ Orlow commandait, souffrit de la maniГЁre la plus cruelle: elle attaqua Г  maintes reprises, fut souvent repoussГ©e, et perdit les deux tiers de son monde (cвҖҷest ici le lieu de placer une observation, que nous prenons dans les mГ©moires qui nous guident; elle fait remarquer combien il est raal vu de donner beaucoup de cartouches aux soldats qui doivent emporter un poste de vive force, et par consГ©quent oГ№ la baГҜonnette doit principalement agir; ils pensent ne devoir se servir de cette derniere arme, que lorsque les cartouches sont epuisГ©es: dans cette persuasion, ils retardent leur marche, et restent plus long-temps exposГ©s au canon et Г  la mitraille de lвҖҷennemi).вҖқвҒ вҖ”Ibid., p. 214.] вҶ©

[вҖңLa jonction de la colonne de MeknopвҒ вҖ”(le gГ©nГ©ral fut nial secondГ© et tuГ©)вҒ вҖ”ne put sвҖҷeffectuer avec celle qui lвҖҷavoisinait,вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ ces colonnes attaquГЁrent un bastion, et Г©prouvГЁrent une rГ©sistance opiniГўtre; raais bientГҙt des cris de victoire se font entendre de toutes parts, et le bastion est emportГ©: le sГ©raskier dГ©fendait cette partie.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Hist. de la Nouvelle Russie, ii. 214.] вҶ©

[вҖқвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ un officier de marine Anglais veut le faire prisonnier, et reГ§oit un coup de pistolet qui lвҖҷГ©tend roide mort.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Ibid., p. 214.] вҶ©

[вҖңLes Russes passent trois mille Turcs au fil de lвҖҷГ©pГ©e; seize baГҜonnettes percent Г  la fois le sГ©raskier.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Ibid., p. 214.] вҶ©

[вҖңLa ville est emportГ©e; lвҖҷimage de la mort et de la dГ©solation se reprГ©sente de tous les cГҙtГ©s le soldat furieux nвҖҷГ©coute plus la voix de ses officiers, il ne respire que le carnage; altГ©rГ© de sang, tout est indiffГ©rent pour lui.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Hist. de la Nouvelle Russie, ii. 214.] вҶ©

As do the subtle snakeвҖҷs denounced of old.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

Which most of all doth man characterise.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. Alternative reading.]

вҶ©

As Autumn winds disperse the yellow leaves.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[See The Blues, ecl. i. line 25, Poetical Works, 1901, iv. 574, note 3.] вҶ©

[вҖңJe sauvai la vie Г  une fille de dix ans, donвҖҷt lвҖҷinnocence et la candeur formaient un contraste bien frappant avec la rage de tout ce qui mвҖҷenvironnait. En arrivant sur le bastion oГ№ commenГ§a le carnage, jвҖҷaperГ§us un groupe de quatre femmes Г©gorgГ©es, entre lesquelles cet enfant, dвҖҷune figure charmante, cherchait un asile contre la fureur de deux Kozaks qui Г©taient sur le point de la massacrer,вҖқвҒ вҖ”Duc de Richelieu. (See Hist. de la Nouvelle Russie, ii. 217.)] вҶ©

[вҖңWho never mentions Hell to ears polite.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Pope, Moral Essays, ep. iv, line 150.] вҶ©

[вҖңCe spectacle mвҖҷattira bientГҙt, et je nвҖҷhГ©sitai pas, comme on peut le croire, Г  prendre entre mes bras cette infortunГ©e, que les barbares voulaient y poursuivre encore. JвҖҷeus bien de la peine Г  me retenir et Г  ne pas percer ces misГ©rables du sabre que je tenais suspendu sur leur tГӘte:вҒ вҖ”je me contentai cependant de les Г©loigner, non sans leur prodiguer les coups et les injures quвҖҷils mГ©ritaient.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰвҖқвҒ вҖ”Duc de Richelieu, vide Hist, de la Nouvelle Russie, ii. 217.] вҶ©

[вҖқвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ JвҖҷeus le plaisir dвҖҷapercevoir que ma petite prisonniГЁre nвҖҷavait dвҖҷautre mal quвҖҷune coupure legere que lui avail faite au visage le mГӘme fer qui avail percГ© sa mГ©re.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Duc de Richelieu, ibid.

The Turks clamoured for the child, and Richelieu was forced to give way. But in the original the story ends unhappily.

вҖңJe fus obligГ© de cГ©der ГЎ leurs instances et ГЎ celles de lвҖҷofficier qui parlementait avec eux;вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ ce ne fut pas sans de grandes difficultГ©s et sans une promesse expresse de la parl de cet officier [Colonel Ribas] de me la faire rendre aussitГҙt que les Tures auraient mis bas les armes. Je me sГ©parai donc de cet enfant qui mвҖҷГ©tait dГ©jГ  devenu trГЁs-cher, et mГӘme a prГ©sent, je ne puis penser ГЎ ce moment sans amertume, puisque malgrГ© toutes les recherches et les peines que je me donnai pour la retrouver, il me fut impossible dвҖҷy rГ©ussir, el je nвҖҷai que trop sujet de craindre quвҖҷelle nвҖҷait pГ©ri malheureusement.вҖқвҒ вҖ”SociГ©tГ© ImpГ©riale dвҖҷHistoire de Russie, tom. liv. p. 185.] вҶ©

[Sir Walter Scott (Quarterly Review, October, 1816, vol. xvi. p. 177) says that a вҖңbrother-poetвҖқ compared ByronвҖҷs features to the sculpture of a beautiful alabaster vase, only seen to perfection when lighted up from within. Byron alludes to this comparison in his Detached Thoughts, October 15, 1821, Letters, 1901, v. 408. It may be noted that Lorenzo Bartolini, the Italian sculptor who took a bust of Byron at Pisa, in the spring of 1822, had been employed by Napoleon, in 1814, to design marble vases for a terrace at Elba, which were to be illuminated at night вҖңfrom within.вҖқ] вҶ©

A Russian military order. вҶ©

[вҖңLe sultan pГ©rit dans lвҖҷaction en brave homme, digne dвҖҷun meilleur destin; ce fut lui qui rallia les Turcs lorsque lвҖҷennemi pГ©nГ©tra dans la placeвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ ce sultan, dвҖҷune valeur Г©prouvГ©e, surpassait en gГ©nГ©rositГ© les plus civilisГ©s de sa nation; cinq de ses fils combattaient Г  ses cГҙtГ©s, il les encourageait par son exemple.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Hist. de la Nouvelle Russie, ii. 215.] вҶ©

[вҖңWhen Charles XII. reached Bender, August 1, 1709, he refused, in the first instance, to cross the river Dniester, and on yielding to the representations of the Turks, he declined to enter the town, but decided on remaining encamped on an island, in spite of the assurances of the inhabitants that it was occasionally flooded.вҖқ But, perhaps, Byron had in mind VoltaireвҖҷs remarks on CharlesвҖҷs OpiniГўtretГ©. (See Histoire de Charles XII., 1772, p. 377. See, too, Charles XII., by Oscar Browning, 1899, pp. 231вҒ вҖ“вҒ 234.)] вҶ©

вёәвҒ like celestial patience.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

Because a hunchbackвҒ вҖ”.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

In battle to old age and ugliness.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

In one immortal glance, and then he died.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[вҖңTous cinq furent tous tuГ©s sous ces yeux: il ne cessa point de se battre, rГ©pondit par des coups de sabre aux propositions de se rendre, et ne fut atteint du coup mortel quвҖҷaprГЁs avoir abattu de sa main beaucoup de Kozaks des plus acharnГ©e Г  sa prise; le reste de sa troupe fut massacrГ©.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Hist. de la Nouvelle Russie, ii. 215.] вҶ©

[вҖңQuoique les Russes fussent rГ©pandus dans la ville, le bastion de pierre rГ©sistait encore; il Г©tait dГ©fendu par un vicillard, pacha Г  trois queues, et commandant les forces rГ©unies Г  IsmaГ«l. On lui proposa une capitulation; il demanda si le reste de la ville Г©tait conquis; sur cette rГ©ponse, il autorisa quelques-uns de ces officiers Г  capituler avec M. de Ribas.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Hist. de la Nouvelle Russie, ii. 215.] вҶ©

[вҖңPendant ce colloque, il resta Г©tendu sur des tapis placГ©s sur les ruines de la forteresse, fumant sa pipe avec la mГӘme tranquillitГ© et la mГӘme indiffГ©rence que sвҖҷil eГ»t Г©tГ© Г©tranger Г  tout ce qui se passait.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Ibid., p. 215.] вҶ©

Of burning cities, those full moons of slaughter
Was imaged back in blood instead of water.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. Alternative reading.]

вҶ©

Would you do less, вҖңpro focis et pro arisвҖң?

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[CompareвҒ вҖ”

вҖңSpreadвҒ вҖ”spread for Vitellius, the royal repast,
Till the gluttonous despot be stuffed to the gorge!вҖқ

The Irish Avatar, stanza 20, Poetical Works, 1891, iv. 559.]

вҶ©

[вҖңOn Г©gorgea indistinctement, on saccagea la place; et la rage du vainqueurвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ se rГ©pandit comme un torrent furieux qui a renversГ© les digues qui le rГ©tenaient: personne obtint de grГўce, et trente huit mille huit cent soixante Turcs pГ©rirent dans cette journГ©e de sang.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Hist. de la Nouvelle Russie, ii. 216.] вҶ©

вёәвҒ of my peroration.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

вёәвҒ the cause I cannot guessвҒ вҖ”
I hardly think it was commiseration.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

In the original RussianвҒ вҖ”

вҖңSlava bogu! slava vam!
KrГ©post vzata i ya tam;вҖқ

a kind of couplet; for he was a poet.

[J.H. CastГ©ra (Vie de Catherine II., 1797, ii. 374) relates this incident in connection with the fall of Turtukey (or Tutrakaw) in Bulgaria, giving the words in French, вҖңGloire Г  Dieu! Louange Г  Catherine! Toutoukai est pris. Souwaroff y est entrГ©.вҖқ W. Tooke (Life of Catherine II., 1800, iii. 278). CastГ©raвҖҷs translator, gives the original Russian with an English version. But according to Spalding (SuvГіroff, 1890, pp. 42, 43), the words, which were written on a scrap of paper, and addressed to Soltikoff, ran thus: вҖңYour Excellency, we have conquered. Glory to God! Glory to you! Alexander SuvГіroff.вҖқ When Ismail was taken he wrote to Potemkin, вҖңThe Russian standard floats above the walls of Ismail,вҖқ and to the Empress, вҖңProud Ismail lies at your MajestyвҖҷs feet.вҖқ The tenour of the poetical message on the fall of Tutrakaw recalls the triumphant piety of the Emperor William I. of Germany. See, too, for вҖңmad SuwarrowвҖҷs rhymes,вҖқ Canto IX. stanza lx. lines 1вҒ вҖ“вҒ 4.] вҶ©

[Stanzas i.-viii., which are headed вҖңDon Juan, Canto III., July 10, 1819,вҖқ are in the handwriting of (?) the Countess Guiccioli. Stanzas ix., x., which were written on the same sheet of paper, are in ByronвҖҷs handwriting. The original MS. opens with stanza xi., вҖңDeath laughs,вҖқ etc. (See letter to Moore, July 12, 1822, Letters, 1901, vi. 96.)] вҶ©

[вҖңFaut quвҖҷ lord Villain-ton ait tout pris;
NвҖҷy a plus dвҖҷ argent dans cвҖҷ gueux de Paris.вҖқ

De BГ©ranger, вҖңComplainte dвҖҷune de ces Demoiselles a lвҖҷOccasion des Affaires du Temps (FГ©vrier, 1816),вҖқ Chansons, 1821, ii. 17.

Compare a retaliatory epigram which appeared in a contemporary newspaperвҒ вҖ”

вҖңThese French petit-maГ®tres who the spectacle throng,
Say of WellingtonвҖҷs dress quвҖҷil fait vilain ton!
But, at Waterloo, Wellington made the French stare
When their army he dressed Г  la mode Angleterre!вҖң]

вҶ©

Oh Wellington (or вҖңVilaintonвҖқ)вҒ вёә.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. B.]

вҶ©

Query, Ney?вҒ вҖ”PrinterвҖҷs Devil. [Michel Ney, Duke of Elchingen, вҖңthe bravest of the braveвҖқ (see Ode from the French, stanza i. Poetical Works, 1900, iii. 431), born January 10, 1769, was arrested August 5, and shot December 7, 1815.] вҶ©

[The story of the attempted assassination (February 11, 1818) of the Duke of Wellington, which is dismissed by Alison in a few words (Hist. of Europe (1815вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1852), 1853, i. 577, 578), occupies many pages of the Supplementary Despatches (1865, xii. 271вҒ вҖ“вҒ 546). Byron probably drew his own conclusions as to the Kinnaird-Marinet incident, from the Letter to the Duke of Wellington on the Arrest of M. Marinet, by Lord Kinnaird, 1818. The story, which is full of interest, may be briefly recounted. On January 30, 1818, Lord Kinnaird informed Sir George Murray (Chief of the Staff of the Army of Occupation) that a person, whose name he withheld, had revealed to him the existence of a plot to assassinate the Duke of Wellington. At 12.30В a.m., February 11, 1818, the Duke, on returning to his Hotel, was fired at by an unknown person; and then, but not till then, he wrote to urge Lord Clancarty to advise the Prince Regent to take steps to persuade or force Kinnaird to disclose the name of his informant. A Mr.В G.W. Chad, of the Consular Service, was empowered to proceed to Brussels, and to seek an interview with Kinnaird. He carried with him, among other documents, a letter from the Duke to Lord Clancarty, dated February 12, 1818. A postscript contained this intimation: вҖңIt may be proper to mention to you that the French Government are disposed to go every length in the way of negotiation with the person mentioned by Lord Kinnaird, or others, to discover the plot.вҖқ

Kinnaird absolutely declined to give up the name of his informant, but, acting on the strength of the postscript, which had been read but not shown to him, started for Paris with вҖңthe great unknown.вҖқ Some days after their arrival, and while Kinnaird was a guest of the Duke, the man was arrested, and discovered to be one Nicholle or Marinet, who had been appointed receveur under the restored government of Louis XVIII., but during the Cent jours had fled to Belgium, retaining the funds he had amassed during his term of office. Kinnaird regarded this action of the French Government as a breach of faith, and in a вҖңMemorialвҖқ to the French Chamber of Peers, and his Letter, maintained that the DukeвҖҷs postscript implied a promise of a safe conduct for Marinet to and from Paris to Brussels. The Duke, on the other hand, was equally positive (see his letter to Lord Liverpool, May 30, 1818) вҖңthat he never intended to have any negotiations with anybody.вҖқ Kinnaird was a вҖңdog with a bad name.вҖқ He had been accused (see his Letter to the Earl of Liverpool, 1816, p. 16) of вҖңthe promulgation of dangerous opinions,вҖқ and of intimacy вҖңwith persons suspected.вҖқ The Duke speaks of him as вҖңthe friend of RevolutionistsвҖқ! It is evident that he held the dangerous doctrine that a promise to a rogue is a promise, and that the authorities took a different view of the ethics of the situation. It is clear, too, that the DukeвҖҷs postscript was ambiguous, but that it did not warrant the assumption that if Marinet went to Paris he should be protected. The air was full of plots. The great Duke despised and was inclined to ignore the pistol or the dagger of the assassin; but he believed that вҖңmischief was afoot,вҖқ and that вҖңgreat personagesвҖқ might or might not be responsible. He was beset by difficulties at every turn, and would have been more than mortal if he had put too favourable a construction on the scruples, or condoned the imprudence of a вҖңfriend of Revolutionists.вҖқ] вҶ©

[The reference may be to the Duke of WellingtonвҖҷs intimacy with Lady Frances Wedderburn Webster. Byron had вҖңpassed that wayвҖқ himself (see Letters, 1898, ii. 251, note i, 323, etc.), and could hardly attack the Duke on that score.] вҶ©

[вҖңThou art the best oвҖҷ the cut-throats.вҖқ

Macbeth, act iii. sc. 4, line 17.]

вҶ©

[вҖңI have supped full of horrors.вҖқ

Macbeth, act v. sc. 5, line 13.]

вҶ©

Vide speeches in Parliament, after the battle of Waterloo. вҶ©

[вҖңI at this time got a post, being for fatigue, with four others. We were sent to break biscuit, and make a mess for Lord WellingtonвҖҷs hounds. I was very hungry, and thought it a good job at the time, as we got our own fill, while we broke the biscuitвҒ вҖ”a thing I had not got for some days. When thus engaged, the Prodigal Son was never once out of my mind; and I sighed, as I fed the dogs, over my humble situation and my ruined hopes.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Journal of a Soldier of the 71st Regiment, 1806 to 1815 (Edinburgh, 1822), pp. 132, 133.] вҶ©

[вҖңWe are assured that Epaminondas died so poor that the Thebans buried him at the public charge; for at his death nothing was found in his house but an iron spit.вҖқвҒ вҖ”PlutarchвҖҷs Fabius Maximus, LanghorneвҖҷs translation, 1838, p. 140. See, too, Cornelius Nepos, Epam., cap. iii. вҖңPaupertatem adeo facilГЁ perpessus est, ut de Republica nihil prГҰter gloriam ceperit.вҖқ] вҶ©

[For PittвҖҷs refusal to accept ВЈ100,000 from the merchants of London towards the payment of his debts, or ВЈ30,000 from the KingвҖҷs Privy Purse, see Pitt, by Lord Rosebery, 1891. p. 231.] вҶ©

To you this one unflattering Muse inscribes.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

He strips from man his mantle (which is dear
Though beautiful in youth) his carnal skin.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[Hamlet, act iii. sc. i, line 56.] вҶ©

[вҖңO dura messorum ilia!вҖқ etc.-Hor., Epod. iii. 4.] вҶ©

Ye iron gutsвҒ вҖ”.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[вҖңCe nвҖҷest quвҖҷГ  lвҖҷГ©dition de 1635 quвҖҷon voit paraГ®tre la devise que Montaigne avait adoptГ©e, le que sais-je? avec lвҖҷemblГЁme des balances.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ Ce que sais-je que Pascal a si sГ©vГЁrement analysГ© se lit au chapitre douze du livre ii; il caractГ©rise parfaitement la philosophie de Montaigne; il est la consГ©quence de cette maxime quвҖҷil avait inscrite en grec sur les solives de sa librairie: вҖҳIl nвҖҷest point de raisonnement au quel on nвҖҷoppose un raissonnement contraire.вҖҷвҖҠвҖқвҒ вҖ”Oeuvres deвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ Montaigne, 1837, вҖңNotice Bibliographique,вҖқ p. xvii.] вҶ©

[Concerning the Pyrrhonists or Sceptics and their master Pyrrho, who held that Truth was incomprehensible (inprensibilis), and that you may not affirm of aught that it be rather this or that, or neither this nor that (ОҝбҪҗ Ојбҫ¶О»О»ОҝОҪ ОҝбҪ•П„ПүПӮ бј”ПҮОөО№ П„ПҢОҙОө бјў бјҗОәОөОҜОҪПүПӮ бјў ОҝбҪҗОҙОөП„ОӯПҒПүПӮ), see Aul. Gellii Noct. Attic., lib. xi. cap. v.] вҶ©

See Othello, [act ii. sc. 3, lines 206, 207: вҖңWell, GodвҖҷs above all, and there be souls must be saved; and there be souls must not be savedвҒ вҖ”LetвҖҷs have no more of this.вҖқ] вҶ©

[Hamlet, act v. sc. 2, lines 94, 98, 102.] вҶ©

[For вҖңLycanthropy,вҖқ see вҖңThe SoldierвҖҷs StoryвҖқ in the SatyricГҙn of Petronius Arbiter, cap. 62; see, too, Letters on Demonology, etc., by Sir W. Scott, 1830, pp. 211, 212.] вҶ©

[In respect of suavity and forbearance Melancthon was the counterpart of Luther. John Arrowsmith (1602вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1657), in his Tractica Sacra, describes him as вҖңVir in quo cum pietate doctrina, et cum utrГўque candor certavit.вҖқ] вҶ©

Like Moses or like Cobbett who have neвҖҷer.

Moses and Cobbet proclaim themselves the вҖңmeekest of men.вҖқ See their writings.вҒ вҖ”[MS.]

Like Moses who was вҖңvery meekвҖқ had neвҖҷer.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[See his вҖңCorrespondance avec LвҖҷImpГ©ratrice de Russie,вҖқ Oeuvres ComplГЁtes de Voltaire, 1836, x. 393вҒ вҖ“вҒ 477. M. Waliszewski, in his Story of a Throne, 1895, i. 224, has gathered a handful of these flowers of speech: вҖңShe is the chief person in the world.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ She is the fire and life of nations.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ She is a saint.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ She is above all saints.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ She is equal to the mother of God.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ She is the divinity of the North.вҒ вҖ”Te Catherinam laudamus, te Dominam confitemur, etc., etc.вҖң] вҶ©

Of everything that ever cursed a nation.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[вҖңIt is still more difficult to say which form of government is the worstвҒ вҖ”all are so bad. As for democracy, it is the worst of the whole; for what is (in fact) democracy?вҒ вҖ”an Aristocracy of Blackguards.вҖқвҒ вҖ”See вҖңMy DictionaryвҖқ (May 1, 1821), Letters, 1901, v. 405, 406.] вҶ©

Though priests and slaves may join the servile cry.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

In Greece I never saw or heard these animals; but among the ruins of Ephesus I have heard them by hundreds.

[See Childe Harold, Canto IV. stanza cliii. line 6, Poetical Works, 1899, ii. 441; and Siege of Corinth, line 329, ibid., 1900, iii. 462, note 1.] вҶ©

Whereas the others hunt for rascal spiders.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

Which still are strongly fluttering to be free.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[Compare The Age of Bronze, line 576, sq., Poetical Works, 1901, v. 570.] вҶ©

[Nadir Shah, or Thamas Kouli Khan, born November, 1688, invaded India, 1739вҒ вҖ“вҒ 40, was assassinated June 19, 1747.] вҶ©

вёәвҒ went mad and was
Killed because what he swallowed would not pass.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

He was killed in a conspiracy, after his temper had been exasperated by his extreme costivity to a degree of insanity.

[To such a height had his madness (attributed to melancholia produced by dropsy) attained, that he actually ordered the Afghan chiefs to rise suddenly upon the Persian guard, and seize theвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ chief nobles; but the project being discovered, the intended victims conspired in turn, and a body of them, including NadirвҖҷs guard, and the chief of his own tribe of Afshar, entered his tent at midnight, and, after a momentвҖҷs involuntary pauseвҒ вҖ”when challenged by the deep voice at which they had so often trembledвҒ вҖ”rushed upon the king, who being brought to the ground by a sabre-stroke, begged for life, and attempted to rise, but soon expired beneath the repeated blows of the conspirators.вҒ вҖ”The Indian Empire, by R. Montgomery Martin (1857), i. 172.] вҶ©

[Compare Childe Harold, Canto I. stanza lxvii. line 5, Poetical Works, 1899, ii. 64, note 3.] вҶ©

Or the substrataвҒ вҖ”.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[Compare Preface to Cain, Poetical Works, 1901, V. 210, note 1.] вҶ©

[Vide ante, Canto VIII. stanza cxxvi. line 9, p. 368.] вҶ©

[Hamlet, act i. sc. 5, line 189.] вҶ©

I never know whatвҖҷs next to comeвҒ вҖ”.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[It is possible that the phrase вҖңpainted snowsвҖқ was suggested by TookeвҖҷs description of the winter-garden of the Taurida Palace: вҖңThe genial warmth,вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ the voluptuous silence that reigns in this enchanting garden, lull the fancy into sweet romantic dreams: we think ourselves in the groves of Italy, while torpid nature, through the windows of this pavilion, announces the severity of a northern winterвҖқ (The Life, etc., 1800, iii. 48).] вҶ©

OвҖҷer limits which mightilyвҒ вҖ”:

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

вёәвҒ in Youth and GloryвҖҷs pillory.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[In his Notes sur le Don Juanisme (Mercure de France, 1898, xxvi. 66), M. Bruchard says that this phrase defines and summarizes the Byronic Don Juan.] вҶ©

The Empress smiled while all the Orloff frownedвҒ вҖ”
A numerous family, to whose heart or hand
Mild Catherine owed the chance of being crowned,.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[C.F.P. Masson, in his MГ©moires Secrets, etc., 1880, i. 150вҒ вҖ“вҒ 178, gives a list of twelve favourites, and in this Canto, Don Juan takes upon himself the characteristics of at least three, LanskoГҜ, Zoritch (or Zovitch), and Plato Zoubof. For example (p. 167), вҖңZoritchвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ est le seul Г©tranger quвҖҷelle ait osГ© crГ©er son favori pendant son regne. CвҖҷГ©toit un Servien Г©chappГ© du bagne de Constantinople oГ№ il Г©toit prisonnier: il parut, pour la premiГЁre fois, en habit de hussard Г  la cour. Il Г©blouit tout le monde par sa beautГ©, et les vielles dames en parlent encore comme dвҖҷun Adonis.вҖқ M. Waliszewski, in his Romance of an Empress (1894), devotes a chapter to вҖңPrivate Life and FavouritismвҖқ (ii. 234вҒ вҖ“вҒ 286), in which he graphically describes the election and inauguration of the Vremienchtchik, вҖңthe man of the moment,вҖқ paramour regnant, and consort of the Empress pro hac vice: вҖңвҖҠвҖҳWe may observe in Russia a sort of interregnum in affairs, caused by the displacement of one favourite and the installation of his successor.вҖҷвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ The interregnums are, however, of very short duration. Only one lasts for several months, between the death of LanskoГҜ (1784) and the succession of Iermolof.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ There is no lack of candidates. The place is good.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ Sometimes, too, on the height by the throne, reached at a bound, these spoilt children of fate grow giddy.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ It is over in an instant, at an evening reception it is noticed that the Empress has gazed attentively at some obscure lieutenant, presented but just beforeвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ next day it is reported that he has been appointed aide-de-camp to her Majesty. What that means is well known. Next day he finds himself in the special suite of rooms.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ The rooms are already vacated, and everything is prepared for the new-comer. All imaginable comfort and luxuryвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ await him; and, on opening a drawer, he finds a hundred thousand roubles [about ВЈ20,000], the usual first gift, a foretaste of Pactolus. That evening, before the assembled court, the Empress appears, leaning familiarly on his arm, and on the stroke of ten, as she retires, the new favourite follows herвҖқ (ibid., pp. 246вҒ вҖ“вҒ 249).] вҶ©

[After the death or murder of her husband, Peter III., Catherine Alexievna (1729вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1796) (born Sophia Augusta), daughter of the Prince of Anhalt Zerbst, was solemnly crowned (September, 1762) Empress of all the Russias.] вҶ©

And almost died for the scarce-fledged Lanskoi.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

He was the grande passion of the grande Catherine. See her Lives under the head of вҖңLanskoi.вҖқ

[Lanskoi was a youth of as fine and interesting a figure as the imagination can paint. Of all CatherineвҖҷs favourites, he was the man whom she loved the most. In 1784 he was attacked with a fever, and perished in the arms of her Majesty. When he was no more, Catherine gave herself up to the most poignant grief, and remained three months without going out of her palace of Tzarsko-selo. She afterwards raised a superb monument to his memory. (See Life of Catherine II., by W. Tooke, 1800, iii. 88, 89.)] вҶ©

[Ten months after the death of Lanskoi, the Empress consoled herself with Iermolof, described, by Bezborodky, as вҖңa modest refined young man, who cultivates the society of serious people.вҖқ In less than a year this excellent youth is, in turn, displaced by Dmitrief Mamonof. His petit nom was Red Coat, and, for a time, he is a вҖңpriceless creature.вҖқ вҖңHe has,вҖқ says Catherine, вҖңtwo superb black eyes, with eyebrows outlined as one rarely sees; about the middle height, noble in manner, easy in demeanour.вҖқ But Mamonof suffered from вҖңscruples of conscience,вҖқ and, after a while, with CatherineвҖҷs consent and blessing, was happily married to the Princess Shtcherbatof, a maid of honour, and not, as Byron supposed, a rival вҖңman of the moment.вҖқвҒ вҖ”See The Story of a Throne, by K. Waliszewski, 1895, ii. 135, sq.] вҶ©

This was written long before the suicide of that person. [For вҖңhis parts of speechвҖқ compareвҒ вҖ”

вҖқвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ that long mandarin
C-stle-r-agh (whom Fum calls the Confucius of Prose)
Was rehearsing a speech upon EuropeвҖҷs repose
To the deep double bass of the fat IdolвҖҷs nose.вҖқ

MooreвҖҷs Fum and Hum, The Two Birds of Royalty.]

вҶ©

[Compare Beppo, stanza xvii. line 8, Poetical Works, 1901, iv. 165. See, too, letter to Hoppner, December 31, 1819, Letters, 1900, iv. 393.] вҶ©

Beneath his chiselвҒ вҖ”

or,

Beneath his touchesвҒ вҖ”.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

вёәвҒ and bound fair Helen in a bond.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

Hor., Sat., lib. i. sat. iii. lines 107, 108. вҶ©

That Riddle which all read, none understand.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

вёәвҒ thou Sea which lavest LifeвҖҷs sand.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[вҖңFortune and victory sit on thy helm.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Richard III., act v, sc. 3, line 79.] вҶ©

[вҖңCatherine had been handsome in her youth, and she preserved a gracefulness and majesty to the last period of her life. She was of a moderate stature, but well proportioned; and as she carried her head very high, she appeared rather tall. She had an open front, an aquiline nose, an agreeable mouth, and her chin, though long, was not mis-shapen. Her hair was auburn, her eyebrows black and rather thick, and her blue eyes had a gentleness which was often affected, but oftener still a mixture of pride. Her physiognomy was not deficient in expression; but this expression never discovered what was passing in the soul of Catherine, or rather it served her the better to disguise it.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Life of Catherine II., by W. Tooke, iii. 381 (translated from Vie de Catherine II. (J.H. CastГ©ra), 1797, ii. 450).] вҶ©

[вҖңHis fortune swells him: вҖҷTis rank, heвҖҷs married.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Sir Giles Overreach, in MassingerвҖҷs New Way to pay Old Debts, act v. sc. 1.] вҶ©

[Hamlet, act iii. sc. iv. lines 58, 59.] вҶ©

[вҖңNot CГҰsarвҖҷs empress would I deign to prove;
No! make me mistress to the man I love.вҖқ

Pope, Eloisa to Abelard, lines 87, 88.]

вҶ©

OвҖҷer whom an Empress her Crown-jewels scattering
Was wed with something better than a ring.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[вҖңSeveral persons who lived at the court affirm that Catherine had very blue eyes, and not brown, as M. RulhiГЁres has stated.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Life of Catherine II., by W. Tooke, 1800, iii. 382.] вҶ©

[The historic Catherine (ГҰt. 62) was past her meridian in the spring of 1791.] вҶ©

Her figure, and her vigour, and her rigour.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

In its sincere beginning, or dull end.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

For such all women are just then, no doubt.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

Of such sensations, in the drowsy drear
AfterвҒ вҖ”which shadows the, sayвҒ вҖ”second year.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

Of that sad heavy, drowsy, doubly drear
After, which shadows the firstвҒ вҖ”say, year.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[Stanza lxxvi. is not in the MS.] вҶ©

A Russian estate is always valued by the number of the slaves upon it. вҶ©

[The вҖңProtassovaвҖқ (born 1744) was a cousin of the Orlofs. She survived Catherine by many years, and was, writes M. Waliszewski (The Story of a Throne, 1895, ii. 193), вҖңpresent at the Congress of Vienna, covered with diamonds like a reliquary, and claiming precedence of every one.вҖқ She is named lвҖҷГ©prouveuse in a note to the MГ©moires Secrets, 1800, i. 148.] вҶ©

And not be dazzled by its early glare.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

End of Canto 9th, Augt. Sept., 1822. B. вҶ©

In a most natural whirling of rotation.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

Since AdamвҒ вҖ”gloriously against an apple.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[вҖңNeither Pemberton nor Whiston, who received from Newton himself the history of his first Ideas of Gravity, records the story of the falling apple. It was mentioned, however, to Voltaire by Catherine Barton (afterwards Mrs.В Conduit), NewtonвҖҷs niece. We saw the apple tree in 1814.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ The tree was so much decayed that it was taken down in 1820вҖқ (Memoirs, etc., of Sir Isaac Newton, by Sir David Brewster, 1855, i. 27, note 1). Voltaire tells the story thus (ГүlГ©ments de la Philosophie de Newton, Partie III. chap, iii.): вҖңUn jour, en lвҖҷannГ©e 1666 [1665], Newton, retirГ© Г  la campagne, et voyant tomber des fruits dвҖҷun arbre, Г  ce que mвҖҷa contГ© sa niГЁce (Madame Conduit), se laissa aller Г  une mГ©ditation profonde sur la cause qui entraГ®ne ainsi tous les corps dans une ligne qui, si elle Г©tait prolongГ©e, passerait Г  peu prГЁs par le centre de la terre.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Oeuvres ComplГЁtes, 1837, v. 727.] вҶ©

To the then unploughed starsвҒ вҖ”.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[Compare ChurchillвҖҷs Grave, line 23, Poetical Works, 1901, iv. 47, note 1.] вҶ©

[Shelley entitles him вҖңThe Pilgrim of Eternity,вҖқ in his Adonais (stanza xxx. line 3), which was written and published at Pisa in 1821.] вҶ©

[Byron left Pisa (Palazzo Lanfranchi on the Arno) for the Villa Saluzzo at Genoa, in the autumn of 1822.] вҶ©

Malicious peopleвҒ вҖ”.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[вҖңWe think the abuse of Mr.В SoutheyвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ by far too savage and intemperate. It is of ill example, we think, in the literary world, and does no honour either to the taste or the temper of the noble author.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Edinburgh Review, February, 1822, vol. xxxvi. p. 445.

вҖңI have read the recent article of JeffreyвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ I suppose the long and the short of it is, that he wishes to provoke me to reply. But I wonвҖҷt, for I owe him a good turn still for his kindness by-gone. Indeed, I presume that the present opportunity of attacking me again was irresistible; and I canвҖҷt blame him, knowing what human nature is.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Letter to Moore, June 8, 1822, Letters, 1901, vi. 80.] вҶ©

вҖ”that essence of all Lie.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

вҖңReformers,вҖқ or rather вҖңReformed.вҖқ The Baron Bradwardine in Waverley is authority for the word. [The word is certainly in ButlerвҖҷs Hudibras, Part II. Canto 2вҒ вҖ”

вҖңAlthough your Church be opposite
To mine as Black Fryars are to White,
In Rule and Order, yet I grant
You are a Reformado Saint.вҖқ]

вҶ©

[Stanza XV. is not in the MS. The вҖңlegal broom,вҖқ sc. Brougham, was an afterthought.] вҶ©

Query, suit?вҒ вҖ”PrinterвҖҷs Devil. вҶ©

[It has been argued that when вҖңgreat CГҰsar fellвҖқ he wore his вҖңrobeвҖқ to muffle up his face, and that, in like manner, Jeffrey sank the critic in the lawyer. A вҖңdeal likelierвҖқ interpretation is that Jeffrey wore вҖңhis gownвҖқ right royally, as CГҰsar wore his вҖңtriumphal robe.вҖқ (See PlutarchвҖҷs Julius CГҰsar, LanghorneвҖҷs translation, 1838, p. 515.)] вҶ©

[вҖңI donвҖҷt like to bore you about the Scotch novels (as they call them, though two of them are English, and the rest half so); but nothing can or could ever persuade me, since I was the first ten minutes in your company, that you are not the man. To me these novels have so much of вҖҳAuld Lang SyneвҖҷ (I was bred a canny Scot till ten years old), that I never move without them.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Letter to Sir W. Scott, January 12, 1822, Letters, 1901, vi. 4, 5.] вҶ©

[Compare The Island, Canto II. lines 280вҒ вҖ“вҒ 297.] вҶ©

The brig of Don, near the вҖңauld tounвҖқ of Aberdeen, with its one arch, and its black deep salmon stream below, is in my memory as yesterday. I still remember, though perhaps I may misquote, the awful proverb which made me pause to cross it, and yet lean over it with a childish delight, being an only son, at least by the motherвҖҷs side. The saying as recollected by me was this, but I have never heard or seen it since I was nine years of age:вҒ вҖ”

вҖңBrig of Balgounie, blackвҖҷs your waвҖҷ,
WiвҖҷ a wifeвҖҷs ae son, and a mearвҖҷs ae foal,
Doun ye shall faвҖҷ!вҖқ

[See for illustration of the Brig oвҖҷ Balgownie, with its single Gothic arch, Letters, 1901 [L.P.], v. 406. ] вҶ©

[вҖңLand of brown heath and shaggy wood,
Land of the mountain and the flood,вҖқ etc.

Lay of the Last Minstrel, Canto VI. stanza ii.]

вҶ©

Some thirty years before at fair eighteen.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

or,

Seven and twentyвҒ вҖ”which, it does not matterвҒ вҖ”
Wrinkles, those damnedst democrats, wonвҖҷt flatter.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

Tiberius Gracchus, being tribune of the people, demanded in their name the execution of the Agrarian law; by which all persons possessing above a certain number of acres were to be deprived of the surplus for the benefit of the poor citizens. вҶ©

вҖңMi ritrovai per una selva oscura.вҖқ

Inferno, Canto I. line 2.

вҶ©

Hut where we travellers bait with dim reflection.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

Is when he learns to limit his expenses.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

вё»till the ice
Cracked, she would neвҖҷer believe in thaws for vice.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

A metaphor taken from the вҖңforty-horse powerвҖқ of a steam-engine. That mad wag, the Reverend Sydney Smith, sitting by a brother clergyman at dinner, observed afterwards that his dull neighbour had a вҖңtwelve-parson powerвҖқ of conversation. вҶ©

[In a letter to his sister, October 25, 1804 (Letters, 1898, i. 40), Byron mentions an auntвҒ вҖ”вҖңthe amiable antiquated Sophia,вҖқ and asks, вҖңIs she yet in the land of the living, or does she sing psalms with the Blessed in the other world?вҖқ This was his fatherвҖҷs sister, Sophia Maria, daughter of Admiral the Hon.В John Byron. But his вҖңgood old auntвҖқ is, more probably, the Hon.В Mrs.В Frances Byron, widow of George (born April 22, 1730) son of the fourth, and brother of the вҖңWickedвҖқ lord. She was the daughter and co-heiress of Ellis Levett, Esq., and lived вҖңat Nottingham in her own house.вҖқ She died, aged 86, June 13, 1822, not long before this Canto was written. She is described in the obituary notice of the GentlemanвҖҷs Magazine, June, 1822, vol. 92, p. 573, as вҖңDaughter of Vice-Admiral the Hon.В John Byron (who sailed round the world with Lord Anson), grandfather of the present Lord Byron.вҖқ But that is, chronologically, impossible. Byron must have retained a pleasing recollection of the ear-trumpet and the spectacles, and it gratified his kindlier humour to embalm their owner in his verse.] вҶ©

[See CollinsвҖҷs Peerage, 1779, vii. 120. It is probable that Byron was lineally descended from Ralph de Burun, of Horestan, who is mentioned in Doomsday Book (sect. xi.) as holding eight lordships in Notts and five in Derbyshire, but with regard to Ernysius or Erneis the pedigree is silent. (See Pedigree of George Gordon, Sixth Lord Byron, by Edward Bernard, 1870.)] вҶ©

вҖңHyde.вҖқвҒ вҖ”I believe a hyde of land to be a legitimate word, and, as such, subject to the tax of a quibble. вҶ©

And humbly hope that the same God which hath given
Us land on earth, will do no less in Heaven.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

PerhapsвҒ вҖ”but dвҒ вҖ”n perhapsвҒ вҖ”.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[For the illness (вҖңa scarlet fever, complicated by angina, both aggravated by premature exhaustionвҖқ) and death of LanskoГҜ, see The Story of a Throne, by K. Waliszewsky, 1895, ii. 131, 133. For the rumour that he was poisoned by Potemkin, see MГ©moires Secrets, etc. [by C.F.P. Masson], 1800, i. 170.] вҶ©

[Matthew Baillie (1761вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1823), the nephew of William Hunter, the brother of Agnes and Joanna Baillie, was a celebrated anatomist. He attended Byron (1799вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1802), when an endeavour was made to effect a cure of the muscular contraction of his right leg and foot. He was consulted by Lady Byron, in 1816, with regard to her husbandвҖҷs supposed derangement, but was not admitted when he called at the house in Piccadilly. He is said to have вҖңavoided technical and learned phrases; to have affected no sentimental tenderness, but expressed what he had to say in the simplest and plainest termsвҖқ (Annual Biography, 1824, p. 319). Jekyll (Letters, 1894, p. 110) repeats or invents an anecdote that вҖңthe old king, in his mad fits, used to say he could bring any dead people to converse with him, except those who had died under BaillieвҖҷs care, for that the doctor always dissected them into so many morsels, that they had not a leg to walk to Windsor with.вҖқ It is hardly necessary to say that John Abernethy (1764вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1831) вҖңexpressed what he had to sayвҖқ in the bluntest and rudest terms at his disposal.] вҶ©

The empress went to the Crimea, accompanied by the Emperor Joseph, in the yearвҒ вҖ”I forget which.

[The Prince de Ligne, who accompanied Catherine in her progress through her southern provinces, in 1787, gives the following particulars: вҖңWe have crossed during many days vast, solitary regions, from which her Majesty has driven Zaporogua, Budjak, and Nogais Tartars, who, ten years ago, threatened to ravage her empire. All these places were furnished with magnificent tents for breakfasts, lunches, dinners, suppers, and sleeping-roomsвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ deserted regions were at once transformed into fields, groves, villages:вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ The Empress has left in each chief town gifts to the value of a hundred thousand roubles. Every day that we remained stationary was marked with diamonds, balls, fireworks, and illuminations throughout a circuit of ten leagues.вҖқвҒ вҖ”The Prince de Ligne, His Memoirs, etc., translated by Katharine Prescott Wormeley, 1899, ii. 31.] вҶ©

Man, midst thy mouldy mammoths, Cuvier.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

Who like sour fruit to sharpen up the tides
Of their salt veins, and stir their stagnancy.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

In the Empress AnneвҖҷs time, Biren, her favourite, assumed the name and arms of the вҖңBironsвҖқ of France; which families are yet extant with that of England. There are still the daughters of Courland of that name; one of them I remember seeing in England in the blessed year of the Allies (1814)вҒ вҖ”the Duchess of S.вҒ вҖ”to whom the English Duchess of Somerset presented me as a namesake.

[вҖңErnest John Biren was born in Courland [in 1690]. His grandfather had been head groom to James, the third Duke of Courland, and obtained from his master the present of a small estate in land.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ In 1714 he made his appearance at St.В Petersburg, and solicited the place of page to the Princess Charlotte, wife of the Tzarovitch Alexey; but being contemptuously rejected as a person of mean extraction, retired to Mittau, where he chanced to ingratiate himself with Count Bestuchef, Master of the Household to Anne, widow of Frederic William, Duke of Courland, who resided at Mittau. Being of a handsome figure and polite address, he soon gained the good will of the duchess, and became her secretary and chief favourite. On her being declared sovereign of Russia, Anne called Biren to Petersburg, and the secretary soon became Duke of Courland, and first minister or rather despot of Russia. On the death of Anne, which happened in 1740, Biren, being declared regent, continued daily increasing his vexations and cruelties, till he was arrested, on the 18th of December, only twenty days after he had been appointed to the regency; and at the revolution that ensued he was exiled to the frozen shores of the Oby.вҖқ Catherine II., by W. Tooke, 1800, i. 160, footnote. He was recalled in 1763, and died in 1772.

In a letter to his sister, dated June 18, 1814, Byron gives a slightly different version of the incident, recorded in his note (vide supra): вҖңThe Duchess of Somerset also, to mend matters, insisted on presenting me to a Princess Biron, Duchess of Hohen-God-knows-what, and another person to her two sisters, Birons too. But I flew off, and would not, saying I had had enough of introductions for that night at least.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Letters, 1899, iii. 98. The вҖңdaughters of CourlandвҖқ must have been descendants of вҖңPierre, dernier Duc de Courlande, De la Maison de Biron,вҖқ viz. Jeanne CathГ©rine, born June 24, 1783, who married, in 1801, FranГ§ois Pignatelli de Belmonte, Duc dвҖҷAcerenza, and DorothГ©e, born August 21, 1793, who married, in 1809, Edmond de Talleyrand PГ©rigord, Duc de Talleyrand, nephew to the Bishop of Autun. (See Almanach de Gotha, 1848, pp. 109, 110.)] вҶ©

[NapoleonвҖҷs exclamation at the ElysГ©e Bourbon, June 23, 1815. вҖңWhen his civil counsellors talked of defence, the word wrung from him the bitter ejaculation, вҖҳAh! my old guard! could they but defend themselves like you!вҖҷвҖҠвҖқвҒ вҖ”Life of Napoleon Buonaparte, by Sir Walter Scott, Prose Works, 1846, ii. 760.] вҶ©

Who now that he is dead has not a foe;
The last expired in cut-throat Castlereagh.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[Immanuel Kant, born at KГ¶nigsberg, in 1729, became Professor and Rector of the University, and died at KГ¶nigsberg in 1804.] вҶ©

[вҖңThe castled crag of Drachenfels
Frowns oвҖҷer the wide and winding Rhine,вҖқ etc.

Childe Harold, Canto III.]

вҶ©

St.В Ursula and her eleven thousand virgins were still extant in 1816, and may be so yet, as much as ever. вҶ©

[вҖңWe left Ratzeburg at 7 oвҖҷclock Wednesday evening, and arrived at LГјneburgвҒ вҖ”i.e. 35 English milesвҒ вҖ”at 3 oвҖҷclock on Thursday afternoon. This is a fair specimen! In England I used to laugh at the вҖҳflying waggons;вҖҷ but compared with a German Post-Coach, the metaphor is perfectly justifiable, and for the future I shall never meet a flying waggon without thinking respectfully of its speed.вҖқвҒ вҖ”S.T. Coleridge, March 12, 1799, Letters of S.T.C., 1895, i. 278.] вҶ©

[See for German oaths, вҖңExtracts from a Diary,вҖқ January 12, 1821, Letters, 1901, v. 172.] вҶ©

With вҖңSchnappsвҖқвҒ вҖ”Democritus would cease to smile,
By German, post-boys driven a mile.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

With вҖңSchnappsвҖқвҒ вҖ”and spite of вҖңDamвҖҷem,вҖқ вҖңdogвҖқ and вҖңlogвҖқ
Launched at their heads jog-jog-jog-jog-jog-jog.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[The French Inscription (see Memorial Inscriptions, etc., by Joseph Meadows Cowper, 1897, p. 134) on the Black PrinceвҖҷs monument is thus translated in the History of Kent (John WeeversвҖҷ Funerall Monuments, 1636, pp. 205, 206)вҒ вҖ”

вҖңWho so thou be that passeth by
Where this corps entombed lie,
Understand what I shall say,
As at this time, speake I may.
Such as thou art, sometime was I.
Such as I am, shalt thou be.
I little thought on thвҖҷ oure of death,
So long as I enjoyГ©d breath.
Great riches here did I possess,
Whereof I made great nobleness;
I had gold, silver, wardrobes, and
Great treasure, horses, houses, land.
But now a caitife poore am I,
Deepe in the ground, lo! here I lie;
My beautie great is all quite gone,
My flesh is wasted to the bone.
My house is narrow now and throng,
Nothing but Truth comes from my tongue.
And if ye should see me this day,
I do not think but ye would say,
That I had never beene a man,
So much altered now I am.вҖқ]

вҶ©

вёәвҒ of higher stations,
And for their pains get smarter puncturations.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[See Childe Harold, Canto I. stanza xxxii. line 2, Poetical Works, 1899, ii. 93, note 16.] вҶ©

[See The Prince (Il Principe), chap. xvii., by NiccolГІ Machiavelli, translated by Ninian Hill Thomson, 1897, p. 121: вҖңBut above all [a Prince] must abstain from the property of others. For men will sooner forget the death of their father than the loss of their patrimony.вҖқ] вҶ©

[India; America.] вҶ©

[Elizabeth Fry (1780вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1845) began her visits to Newgate in 1813. In 1820 she corresponded with the Princess Sophie of Russia, and at a later period she was entertained by Louis Philippe, and by the King of Prussia at Kaiserwerth. She might have, she may have, admonished George IV. вҖңwith regard to all good things.вҖқ] вҶ©

[See The Age of Bronze, line 768, Poetical Works, 1901, v. 578, note 1.] вҶ©

[вҖңO for a blast of that dread horn,
On Fontarabian echoes borne,
That to King Charles did come,
When Rowland brave, and Olivier,
And every paladin and peer,
On Roncesvalles died.вҖқ

Marmion, Canto VI. stanza xxxiii. lines 7вҒ вҖ“вҒ 12.]

вҶ©

Like an old Roman trumpet ere a battle.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

B. Genoa, Oct. 6th, 1822. End of Canto 10th. вҶ©

[Berkeley did not deny the reality of existence, but the reality of matter as an abstract conception. вҖңIt is plain,вҖқ he says (On the Principles of Human Knowledge, sect. ix.), вҖңthat the very notion of what is called matter or corporeal substance, involves a contradiction in it.вҖқ Again, вҖңIt were a mistake to think that what is here said derogates in the least from the reality of things.вҖқ His contention was that this reality depended, not on an abstraction called matter, вҖңan inert, extended unperceiving substance,вҖқ but on вҖңthose unextended, indivisible substances or spirits, which act, and think, and perceive them [unthinking beings].вҖқвҒ вҖ”Ibid., sect. xci., The Works of George Berkeley, D.D., 1820, i. 27, 69, 70.] вҶ©

[Tempest, act v. sc. i, line 95.] вҶ©

[вҖңI have been very unwellвҒ вҖ”four days confined to my bed in вҖҳthe worst innвҖҷs worst roomвҖҷ at Lerici, with a violent rheumatic and bilious attack, constipation, and the devil knows what.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Letter to Murray, October 9, 1822, Letters, 1901, vi. 121. The same letter contains an announcement that he had вҖңa fifth [Canto of Don Juan] (the 10th) finished, but not transcribed yet; and the eleventh begun.вҖқ] вҶ©

Or Rome, or TiberвҒ вҖ”Naples or the sea.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[Vide ante, Canto I. stanza xiv. lines 7, 8.] вҶ©

[вҖңFalstaff. Let us be DianaвҖҷs foresters, gentlemen of the shade, minions of the moon: and let men say, we be men of good government; being governed, as the sea is, by our noble and chaste mistress the moon, under whose countenance weвҒ вҖ”steal.вҖқ-I Henry IV., act i. sc. 2, lines 24вҒ вҖ“вҒ 28.] вҶ©

[Gin. Hence the antithesis of вҖңAll MaxвҖқ in the East to AlmackвҖҷs in the West. (See Life in London, by Pierce Egan, 1823, pp. 284вҒ вҖ“вҒ 290.)] вҶ©

[According to the Vocabulary of the Flash Language, compiled by James Hardy Vaux, in 1812, and published at the end of his Memoirs, 1819, ii. 149вҒ вҖ“вҒ 227, a kiddy, or вҖңflash-kiddy,вҖқ is a thief of the lower orders, who, when he is breeched by a course of successful depredation dresses in the extreme of vulgar gentility, and affects a knowingness in his air and conversation. A вҖңswellвҖқ or вҖңrank swellвҖқ (вҖңreal swellвҖқ appears in EganвҖҷs Life in London) is the more recent вҖңtoff;вҖқ and вҖңflashвҖқ is вҖңfly,вҖқ вҖңdown,вҖқ or вҖңawake,вҖқ i.e. knowing, not easily imposed upon.] вҶ©

[Hamlet, act v. sc. 1, line 21.] вҶ©

[вҖңKenвҖқ is a house, s.c. a thievesвҖҷ lodging-house; вҖңspellken,вҖқ a play-house; вҖңhigh toby-spiceвҖқ is robbery on horseback, as distinguished from вҖңspice,вҖқ i.e. footpad robbery; to вҖңflash the muzzleвҖқ is to show off the face, to swagger openly; вҖңblowingвҖқ or вҖңblowenвҖқ is a doxy or trull; and вҖңnuttyвҖқ is, conjointly, amorous and fascinating.] вҶ©

Poor Tom was once a knowing one in town.
Not a mere kiddy, but a real one.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

The advance of science and of language has rendered it unnecessary to translate the above good and true English, spoken in its original purity by the select mobility and their patrons. The following is a stanza of a song which was very popular at least in my early days:вҒ вҖ”

вҖңOn the high toby-spice flash the muzzle,
In spite of each gallows old scout;
If you at the spellken canвҖҷt hustle,
YouвҖҷll be hobbled in making a clout.
Then your blowing will wax gallows haughty,
When she hears of your scaly mistake,
SheвҖҷll surely turn snitch for the fortyвҒ вҖ”
That her Jack may be regular weight.вҖқ

If there be any gemman so ignorant as to require a traduction, I refer him to my old friend and corporeal pastor and master, John Jackson, Esq., Professor of Pugilism; who, I trust, still retains the strength and symmetry of his model of a form, together with his good humour, and athletic as well as mental accomplishments.

[Gentleman Jackson was of good renown. вҖңServility,вҖқ says Egan (Life in London, 1823, p. 217), вҖңis not known to him. Flattery he detests. Integrity, impartiality, good-nature, and manliness, are the corner-stones of his understanding.вҖқ Byron once said of him that вҖңhis manners were infinitely superior to those of the Fellows of the College whom I meet at the high tableвҖқ (J.W. Clark, Cambridge, 1890, p. 140). (See, too, letter to John Jackson, September 18, 1808, Letters, 1898, i. 189, note 2; Hints from Horace, line 638, Poetical Works, 1898, i. 433, note 3.) As to the stanza quoted by Egan (Anecdotes of the Turf, 1827, p. 44), but not traduced or interpreted, вҖңTo be hobbled for making a cloutвҖқ is to be taken into custody for stealing a handkerchief, to вҖңturn snitchвҖқ is to inform, and the вҖңfortyвҖқ is the ВЈ40 offered for the detection of a capital crime, and shared by the police or Bow Street runners. Dangerous characters were let alone and tacitly encouraged to continue their career of crime, until the measure of their iniquity was full, and they вҖңweighed forty.вҖқ If Jack was clumsy enough to be detected in a trifling theft, his вҖңblowenвҖқ would go over to the enemy, and betray him for the sake of the Government reward (see Classical Dictionary of the Vulgar Tongue, by Francis Grose, 1823, art. вҖңWeigh fortyвҖқ).] вҶ©

[Don Juan must have driven by Pleasant Row, and passed within hail of Paradise Row, on the way from Kennington to Westminster Bridge. (See CaryвҖҷs New Pocket Plan of London, Westminster, and Southwark, 1819.) But, perhaps, there is more in the names of streets and places than meets the eye. Here, as elsewhere, there is, or there may be, вҖңa paltering with us in a double sense.вҖқ] вҶ©

Through rows called вҖңParadise,вҖқ by way of showing
Good Christians that to which they all are going.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[Compare Childe Harold, Canto 1. stanza lxix. line 8, var. ii., Poetical Works, 1899, ii. 66, note 2.] вҶ©

вёәвҒ distilling into the re-kindling glass.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[The streets of London were first regularly lighted with gas in 1812.] вҶ©

[Thomas Pennant, in Some Account of London, 1793, p. 444, writes down the Mansion House (1739вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1752) as вҖңdamnedвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ to everlasting fame.вҖқ] вҶ©

[Fifty years ago вҖңthe lights of PiccadillyвҖқ were still regarded as one of the вҖңsightsвҖқ of London. Byron must often have looked at them from his house in Piccadilly Terrace.] вҶ©

[Joseph FranГ§ois Foulon, army commissioner, provoked the penalty of the вҖңlanternвҖқ (i.e. an improvised gallows on the yard of a lamp-post at the corner of the Rue de la Vannerie) by his heartless sneer, вҖңEh bien! si cette canaille nвҖҷa pas de pain, elle mangera du foin.вҖқ He was hanged, July 22, 1789. See The Tale of Two Cities, by Charles Dickens, cap. xxii.; see, too, CarlyleвҖҷs French Revolution, 1839, i. 253: вҖңWith wild yells, Sansculottism clutches him, in its hundred hands: he is whirledвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ to the вҖҳLanterne,вҖҷвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ pleading bitterly for lifeвҒ вҖ”to the deaf winds. Only with the third rope (for two ropes broke, and the quavering voice still pleaded), can he be so much as got hanged! His Body is dragged through the streets; his Head goes aloft on a pike, the mouth filled with grass: amid sounds as of Tophet, from a grass-eating people.вҖқ] вҶ©

вҖңHells,вҖқ gaming-houses. What their number may now be in this life, I know not. Before I was of age I knew them pretty accurately, both вҖңgoldвҖқ and вҖңsilver.вҖқ I was once nearly called out by an acquaintance, because when he asked me where I thought that his soul would be found hereafter, I answered, вҖңIn Silver Hell.вҖқ вҶ©

At length the boys drew up before a door,
From whence poured forth a tribe of well-clad waiters;
(While on the pavement many a hungry wвҒ вҖ”re
With which the moralest of cities caters
For gentlemen whose passions may boil oвҖҷer,
Stood as the unpacking gathered more spectators,)
And Juan found himself in an extensive
Apartment;вҒ вҖ”fashionable but expensive.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

вҖҷTwas one of the delightfullest hotels.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[Perhaps GrillionвҖҷs Hotel (afterwards GrillionвҖҷs Club) in Albemarle Street. In 1822 diplomats patronized more than one hotel in and near St.В JamesвҖҷs Street, but among the вҖңDepartures from GrillionвҖҷs Hotel,вҖқ recorded in the Morning Chronicle of September, 17, 1822, appositely enough, is that of H.E. Don Juan Garcia, del Rio.] вҶ©

вёәвҒ of his loves and wars;
And as romantic heads are pretty painters,
And ladies like a little spice of Mars.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

The false attempt at TruthвҒ вҖ”.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[CompareвҒ вҖ”

вҖңLo! Erin, thy Lord!
Kiss his foot with thy blessingвҖқвҒ вёәвҒ

The Irish Avatar, stanza 14, Poetical Works, 1901, iv. 558.]

вҶ©

Kiss handsвҒ вҖ”or feetвҒ вҖ”or what Man by and by
Will kiss, not in sad metaphorвҒ вҖ”but earnest,
Unless on TyrantsвҖҷ sternsвҒ вҖ”we turn the sternest.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

вҖңAnentвҖқ was a Scotch phrase meaning вҖңconcerningвҖқвҒ вҖ”вҖңwith regard to: вҖңit has been made English by the Scotch novels; and, as the Frenchman said, вҖңIf it be not, ought to be English.вҖқ [See, for instance, The Abbot, chap. xvii. 132.] вҶ©

But вҖңDammeвҖҷsвҖқ simpleвҒ вҖ”dashingвҒ вҖ”free and daring
The purest blasphemyвҒ вҖ”.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

About such general mattersвҒ вҖ”but particular
A poemвҖҷs progress should be perpendicular.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[Macbeth, act iii. sc. 4, line 63.] вҶ©

Blushed, too, but it was hidden by their rouge.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

The natural and the prepared ceruse.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

вҖңDrapery Misses.вҖқвҒ вҖ”This term is probably anything now but a mystery. It was, however, almost so to me when I first returned from the East in 1811вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1812. It means a pretty, a high-born, a fashionable young female, well instructed by her friends, and furnished by her milliner with a wardrobe upon credit, to be repaid, when married, by the husband. The riddle was first read to me by a young and pretty heiress, on my praising the вҖңdraperyвҖқ of the вҖңuntocheredвҖқ but вҖңpretty virginitiesвҖқ (like Mrs.В Anne Page) of the then day, which has now been some years yesterday: she assured me that the thing was common in London; and as her own thousands, and blooming looks, and rich simplicity of array, put any suspicion in her own case out of the question, I confess I gave some credit to the allegation. If necessary, authorities might be cited; in which case I could quote both вҖңdraperyвҖқ and the wearers. Let us hope, however, that it is now obsolete. вҶ©

[Compare Hints from Horace, line 173, Poetical Works, 1898, i. 401, note 1.] вҶ©

[In his so-called вҖңDedicationвҖқ of Marino Faliero to Goethe, Byron makes fun of the вҖңnineteen hundred and eighty-seven poets,вҖқ whose names were to be found in A Biographical Dictionary of Living Authors, etc. (See Introduction to Marino Faliero, Poetical Works, 1901, iv. 340, 341, note 1.)] вҶ©

A paper potentateвҒ вҖ”.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[See вҖңIntroduction to Cain,вҖқ Poetical Works, 1901, v. 204.] вҶ©

With turnkey Southey for my Hudson Lowe.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

Beneath the reverend Cambyses Croly.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[The Reverend George Croly, D.D. (1780вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1860), began his literary career as dramatic critic of the Times. вҖңCroly,вҖқ says H.C. Robinson (Diary, 1869, i. 412), вҖңis a fierce-looking Irishman, very lively in conversation, and certainly has considerable talents as a writer; his eloquence, like his person, is rather energetic than eloquentвҖқ (hence the epithet вҖңCambyses,вҖқ i.e. вҖңKing CambysesвҖҷ veinвҖқ in var. iii.). вҖңHe wrote tragedies, comedies, and novels; and, at last, settled down as a preacher, with the rank of doctor, but of what faculty I do not knowвҖқ (ibid., footnote, H.C.R., 1847). He wrote, inter alia, Paris in 1815, a poem; Catiline, A Tragedy, 1822; and Salathiel, a novel, 1827. In lines 7, 8, Byron seems to refer to The Angel of the World, An Arabian Poem, published in 1820.] вҶ©

[I Henry IV., act ii. sc. 4, line 197.] вҶ©

[Stanza lviii. was first published in 1837. The reference is to Henry Hart Milman (1791вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1868). Byron was under the impression that Milman had influenced Murray against continuing the publication of Don Juan. Added to this surmise, was the mistaken belief that it was Milman who had written the article in the Quarterly, which вҖңkilled John Keats.вҖқ Hence the virulence of the attack.

вҖңDull DorusвҖқ is obscure, but compare Propertius, Eleg. III. vii. 44, where Callimachus is addressed as вҖңDore poeta.вҖқ He is the вҖңox of verse,вҖқ because he had been recently appointed to the Professorship of Poetry at Oxford. The вҖңroaring RomansвҖқ are вҖңThe soldieryвҖқ who shout вҖңAll, All,вҖқ in CrolyвҖҷs Catiline, act v. sc. 2.] вҶ©

Then thereвҖҷs my gentle BarryвҒ вҖ”who they say.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[Jeffrey, in his review of A Sicilian Story, etc., Bryan Waller Procter (Barry Cornwall), 1787вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1874 (Edinburgh Review, January, 1820, vol. 33, pp. 144вҒ вҖ“вҒ 155), compares Diego de Montilla, a poem in ottava rima, with Don Juan, favourably and unfavourably: вҖңThere is no profligacy and no horrorвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ no mocking of virtue and honour, and no strong mixtures of buffoonery and grandeur.вҖқ But it may fairly match with Byron and his Italian models вҖңas to the better qualities of elegance, delicacy, and tenderness.вҖқ See, too, BlackwoodвҖҷs Edinburgh Magazine, March, 1820, vol. vi. pp. 153, 647.] вҶ©

[See Preface to the Vision of Judgment, Poetical Works, 1901, iv. 484, note 3.] вҶ©

[CrokerвҖҷs article in the Quarterly (April, 1818 [pub. September], vol. xix. pp. 204вҒ вҖ“вҒ 208) did not вҖңkill John Keats.вҖқ See letter to George and Georgiana Keats, October, 1818 (Letters, etc., 1895, p. 215). Byron adopts ShelleyвҖҷs belief that the Reviewer, вҖңmiserable man,вҖқ вҖңone of the meanest,вҖқ had вҖңwantonly defaced one of the noblest specimens of the workmanship of God.вҖқ See Preface to Adonais, and stanzas xxxvi., xxxvii.] вҶ©

And weakly mind, to let that all celestial Particle.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

or,

вҖҳT is strange the mind should let such phrases quell its
Chief Impulse with a few, frail, paper pellets.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

вҖңDivinГҰ particulam aurГҰвҖқ [Hor., Sat. ii. 2. 79] вҶ©

[For вҖңthe crowd of usurpersвҖқ who started up in the reign of Gallienus, and were dignified with the honoured appellation of вҖңthe thirty tyrants,вҖқ see GibbonвҖҷs Decline and Fall, 1825, i. 164.] вҶ©

[King Lear, act iv. sc. 6, line 15.] вҶ©

[вҖңIllita Nesseo misi tibi texta veneno.вҖқ

Ovid., Heroid. Epist. ix. 163.]

вҶ©

[A вҖңbower,вҖқ in MooreвҖҷs phrase, signifies a solitude Г  deux; e.g. вҖңHereвҖҷs the Bower she lovвҖҷd so much.вҖқ

вҖңCome to me, love, the twilight star
Shall guide thee to my bower.вҖқ

Moore.]

вҶ©

[Compare The Waltz, lines 220вҒ вҖ“вҒ 229, et passim, Poetical Works, 1898, i. 501.] вҶ©

Scotch for goblin. вҶ©

Handsome but blasГ©вҒ вёәвҒ

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[The sentiment is reiterated in The Night Thoughts, and is the theme of Resignation, which was written and published when Young was more than eighty years old. ] вҶ©

And fresher, since without a breath of air.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

Where are the thousand lovely innocents?

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[вҖңI haveвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ writtenвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ to express my willingness to accept the, or almost any mortgage, any thing to get out of the tremulous Funds of these oscillating times. There will be a war somewhere, no doubtвҒ вҖ”and whatever it may be, the Funds will be affected more or less; so pray get us out of them with all proper expedition. It has been the burthen of my song to you three years and better, and about as useful as better counsels.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Letter of Byron to Kinnaird, January 18, 1823, Letters, 1901, vi. 162, 163.] вҶ©

[For William Pole Tylney Long Wellesley (1788вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1857), see The Waltz, line 21, Poetical Works, 1898, i. 484, note 1. He was only on the way to being вҖңdiddledвҖқ in 1822, but the prophecy (suggested, no doubt, by the announcement of the sale of furniture, etc., at Wanstead House, in the Morning Chronicle, July 8, 1822) was ultimately fulfilled. Samuel Whitbread, born 1758, committed suicide July 6, 1815. Sir Samuel Romilly, born 1758, committed suicide November 2, 1818.] вҶ©

[According to Charles Greville, George the Third made two willsвҒ вҖ”the first in 1770, the second, which he never signed, in 1810. By the first will he left вҖңall he had to the Queen for her life, Buckingham House to the Duke of Clarence,вҖқ etc., and as Buckingham House had been twice sold, and the other legatees were dead, a question arose between the King and the Duke of York as to the right of inheritance of their fatherвҖҷs personal property. George IV. conceived that it devolved upon him personally, and not on the Crown, and вҖңconsequently appropriated to himself the whole of the money and the jewels.вҖқ It is possible that this difference between the brothers was noised abroad, and that old stories of the destruction of royal wills were revived to the new kingвҖҷs discredit. (See The Greville Memoirs, 1875, i. 64, 65.)] вҶ©

[See MooreвҖҷs Fum and Hum, the Two Birds of Royalty, appended to his Fudge Family.] вҶ©

[Lady Caroline Lamb and Lady Frances Wedderburn Webster.] вҶ©

вёәвҒ their caps and curls at Dukes.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[The Congress at Verona, in 1822. See the Introduction to The Age of Bronze, Poetical Works, 1891, v. 537вҒ вҖ“вҒ 540.] вҶ©

[2 Henry IV., act iv. sc. 3, line 117.] вҶ©

[Hor., Od. I. xi. line 8.] вҶ©

[Macbeth, act v. sc. 5, line 24.] вҶ©

[1 Henry IV., act ii. sc. 4, line 463.] вҶ©

[See the Secret Memoirs and Manners of several Persons of Quality, of Both Sexes, from the New Atalantis, 1709, a work in which the authoress, Mrs.В Manley, satirizes the distinguished characters of her day. Warburton (Works of Pope, ed. 1751, i. 244) calls it вҖңa famous bookвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ full of court and party scandal, and in a loose effeminacy of style and sentiment, which well suited the debauched taste of the better vulgar.вҖқ Pope also alludes to it in the Rape of the Lock, iii. 165, 166вҒ вҖ”

вҖңAs long as Atalantis shall be read,
Or the small pillow grace a ladyвҖҷs bed.вҖқ

And Swift, in his ballad on вҖңCorinnaвҖқ (stanza 8)вҒ вҖ”

вҖңHer common-place book all gallant is,
Of scandal now a cornucopia,
She pours it out in Atalantis,
Or memoirs of the New Utopia.вҖқ

Works, 1824, xii. 302.]

вҶ©

[Oct. 17, 1822.вҒ вҖ”MS.] вҶ©

[See letter to Douglas Kinnaird, dated Genoa, January 18, 1823.] вҶ©

[Johnson would not believe that вҖңa complete miser is a happy man.вҖқ вҖңThat,вҖқ he said, вҖңis flying in the face of all the world, who have called an avaricious man a miser, because he is miserable. No, sir; a man who both spends and saves money is the happiest man, because he has both enjoyments.вҖқвҒ вҖ”BoswellвҖҷs Life of Johnson, 1876, p. 605.] вҶ©

[The Descamisados, or Sansculottes of the Spanish Revolution of 1820вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1823. For Spanish вҖңLiberals,вҖқ see Quarterly Review, April, 1823, vol. xxix. pp. 270вҒ вҖ“вҒ 276.] вҶ©

[Hamlet, act i. sc. 1, line 116.] вҶ©

[See The Age of Bronze, line 678, sq., Poetical Works, 1901, v. 573, note 3.] вҶ©

[Jacques Laffitte (1767вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1844), as Governor of the Bank of France, advanced sums to Parisians to meet their enforced contributions to the allies, and, in 1817, advocated liberal measures as a Deputy.] вҶ©

Were not worth one whereon their profile shines.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[вҖңThey say that вҖҳKnowledge is PowerвҖҷ;вҒ вҖ”I used to think so; but I now know that they meant MoneyвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ every guinea is a philosopherвҖҷs stone, or at least his touch-stone. You will doubt me the less, when I pronounce my pious beliefвҒ вҖ”that Cash is Virtue.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Letter to Kinnaird, February 6, 1822, Letters, 1901, vi. 11.] вҶ©

[Lay of the Last Minstrel, Canto III. stanza ii. lines 4вҒ вҖ“вҒ 6.] вҶ©

[See GodwinвҖҷs Essay Of Population, 1820 (pp. 18, 19, et passim), in which he renews his attack on MalthusвҖҷs Essay on the Principles of Population.] вҶ©

[вҖңWe have no notion that Lord B[yron] had any mischievous intention in these publicationsвҒ вҖ”and readily acquit him of any wish to corrupt the morals, or impair the happiness of his readersвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ but it is our dutyвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ to say, that much of what he has published appears to us to have this tendency.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ How opposite to this is the system, or the temper, of the great author of Waverley!вҖқвҒ вҖ”Edinburgh Review, February, 1822, vol. 36, p. 451.] вҶ©

вёәвҒ for his moral pen
Held up to me by Jeffrey as example.
Of which with profitвҒ вҖ”as youвҖҷll soon see by a sample.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[In the case of Murray v. Benbow (February 9, 1822), the Lord Chancellor (Lord Eldon) refused the motion for an injunction to restrain the defendant from publishing a pirated edition of Lord ByronвҖҷs poem of Cain (JacobвҖҷs Reports, p. 474, note). Hence (see var. i.) the allusion to вҖңLawвҖқ and вҖңEquity.вҖқ The вҖңsuitвҖқ and the вҖңappealвҖқ (vide ibid.) refer to legal proceedings taken, or intended to be taken, with regard to certain questions arising out of the disposition of property under Lady NoelвҖҷs will. (See letters to Charles Hanson, September 21, November 30, 1822, Letters, 1901, vi. 115, 146.)] вҶ©

That suit in ChanceryвҒ вҖ”have a Chancery suitвҒ вҖ”
In right good earnestвҒ вҖ”also an appeal
Before the Lords, whose ChancellorвҖҷs more acute
In Law than EquityвҒ вҖ”as I can feel
Because my Cases put his Lordship to вҖҳt
AndвҒ вҖ”though no doubt вҖҳt is for the Public weal,
His LordshipвҖҷs Justice is not that of SolomonвҒ вҖ”
Not that I deem our Chief Judge is a hollow man.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

See [William] MitfordвҖҷs Greece (1829, v. 314, 315), вҖңGrГҰcia Verax.вҖқ His great pleasure consists in praising tyrants, abusing Plutarch, spelling oddly, and writing quaintly; and what is strange, after all, his is the best modern history of Greece in any language, and he is perhaps the best of all modern historians whatsoever. Having named his sins, it is but fair to state his virtuesвҒ вҖ”learning, labour, research, wrath, and partiality. I call the latter virtues in a writer, because they make him write in earnest.

[Byron consulted Mitford when he was at work on Sardanapalus. (See Extracts from a Diary, January 5, 1821, Letters, 1901, v. 152, note 1.)] вҶ©

[Thomas Robert Malthus (1766вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1834) married, in 1804, Harriet, daughter of John Eckersall of Claverton House, near Bath. There were three children of the marriage, of whom two survived him. Byron may be alluding to the apocryphal story of вҖңhis eleven daughters,вҖқ related by J.L.A. Cherbuliez, in the Journal des Гүconomistes (1850, vol. xxv. p. 135): вҖңUn soirвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ il y avait cercle chez M. de Sismondi, Г  sa maison de campagne prГЁs de GenГЁve.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ Enfin, on annonce le rГ©vГ©rend Malthus et sa famille. Sa famille!вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ Alors on voit entrer une charmante jeune fille, puis une seconde, puis une troisiГЁme, puis une quatriГЁme, puisвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ Il nвҖҷy en avait, ma fois, pas moins de onze!вҖқ See Malthus and his Work, by James Bonar, 1885, pp. 412, 413. See, too, Nouveau Dictionnaire de LвҖҷГүconomie Politique, 1892, art. вҖңMalthus.вҖқ] вҶ©

[CompareвҒ вҖ”

вҖңHow commentators each dark passage shun,
And hold their farthing candle to the sun.вҖқ

Love of Fame, the Universal Passion, by Edward Young, Sat. vii. lines 97, 98.]

вҶ©

[Philo-progenitiveness. Spurzheim and Gall discover the organ of this name in a bump behind the ears, and say it is remarkably developed in the bull.] вҶ©

He played and paid, made love without much sin.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

Themselves on seldom yielding to temptation.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[Henry Hallam (1778вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1859) published his View of the State of Europe in the Middle Ages in 1818.] вҶ©

A drunken Gentleman of fortyвҖҷs sure.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

This line may puzzle the commentators more than the present generation. вҶ©

If he can hiccup nonsense at a ball.

or,

If he goes after dinner to a ball.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[As You Like It, act ii. sc. 7, line 156; and Hamlet, act ii. sc. 2, lines, 97, 98.] вҶ©

But first of little LeilahвҒ вҖ”.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[For the allusion to вҖңunsunned snows,вҖқ vide ante, p. 275, note 1.] вҶ©

[The reference may be to Hobhouse and the вҖңZoili of Albemarle Street,вҖқ who did their best to вҖңtutorвҖқ him with regard to вҖңblazing indiscretionsвҖқ in Don Juan.] вҶ©

ThatвҒ вҖ”but I will not listen, by your leave,
Unto a single syllableвҒ вёә.вҒ вҖ”[MS.]

вҶ©

[For another instance of this curious mistake, see letter to Hodgson, December 8, 1811, Letters, 1898, ii. 85; et ibid., p. 31, note 1.] вҶ©

Painted and gildedвҒ вҖ”or, as it will tell
More Muse-likeвҒ вҖ”sayвҒ вҖ”like CythereaвҖҷs shell.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[Vide ante, Preface to Cantos VI., VII., and VIII., p. 266.] вҶ©

[вҖңEnfin partout la bonne sociГ©tГ© rГ©gle tout.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Voltaire.] вҶ©

[вҖңThis game originated, I believe, in Germany.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ It is called the game of the goose, because at every fourth and fifth compartment of the table in succession a goose is depicted; and if the cast thrown by the player falls upon a goose, he moves forward double the number of his throwвҖқ (Sports and Pastimes, etc., by Joseph Strutt, 1801, p. 250).

Goldsmith, in his Deserted Village, among other вҖңparlour splendours,вҖқ mentions вҖңthe twelve good rules, the royal game of goose.вҖқ] вҶ©

Most young beginners may be taken so,
But those who have been a little used to roughing
Know how to end this half-and-half flirtation.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[вҖңIвҖҷll grow a talker for this gear.вҖқ

Merchant of Venice, act i. sc. 1, line 110.]

вҶ©

Country where warm young peopleвҒ вҖ”.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[Pope and Scott use the quasi-contracted вҖңgynocracyвҖқ for вҖңgynГҰcocracy.вҖқ (See N. Engl. Dict.)] вҶ©

Of white cliffsвҒ вҖ”and white bosomsвҒ вҖ”and blue eyesвҒ вҖ”
And stockingsвҒ вҖ”virtues, loves and Chastities.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[Hor., Epist., lib. 1, ep. xiv. line 43. The meaning is that Europe makes but little progress in the discovery and settlement of Africa, and, as it were, вҖңploughs the sands.вҖқ] вҶ©

Though many thousands both of birth and pluck too,
Have ventured past the jaws of Moor and Tiger.[*]

[*]Note. By particular licence, вҖңpositively for the last time, by desire,вҖқ etc., to be pronounced вҖңtydger.вҖқ Such is what Gifford calls вҖңthe necessity of rhyming.вҖқвҒ вҖ”[MS. erased.] вҶ©

[вҖңThough many degrees nearer our own fair and blue-eyed beauties in complexionвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ yet no people ever lost more by comparison than did the white ladies of Moorzuk [capital of Fezzan] with the black ones of Bornou and Soudan.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Narrative of TravelsвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ in Northern and Central Africa, 1822вҒ вҖ“вҒ 24, by Denham, Clapperton, and Oudney, 1828, ii. 133.] вҶ©

Above, all sunshine, and, below, all ice.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[Compare Prisoner of Chillon, lines 82вҒ вҖ“вҒ 85, Poetical Works, 1901, iv. 17.] вҶ©

The Russians, as is well known, run out from their hot baths to plunge into the Neva; a pleasant practical antithesis, which it seems does them no harm. вҶ©

But once there (few have felt this more than I).

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[Compare Childe Harold, Canto II. stanza lviii. line 9, Poetical Works, 1899, ii. 59, note 1.] вҶ©

[See PlutarchвҖҷs Caius Marius, LanghorneвҖҷs translation, 1838, pp. 304, 305.] вҶ©

That Lady who is not at home to all.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

For a description and print of this inhabitant of the polar region and native country of the Aurorae Boreales, see Sir E. ParryвҖҷs Voyage In Search of a North-West Passage, [1821, p. 257. The print of the Musk-Bull is drawn and engraved by W. Westall, A.R.A., from a sketch by Lieut.В Beechy. He is a вҖңfearful wild-fowl!вҖқ] вҶ©

[Charles, second Earl Grey, born March 13, 1764, succeeded to the peerage in 1807, died July 17, 1847.] вҶ©

[William Pitt, first Earl of Chatham, born November 15, 1708, died May 11, 1778.] вҶ©

[вҖңHis person was undoubtedly cast by Nature in an elegant and pleasing mould, of a just height, well-proportioned, and with due regard to symmetry.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ His countenance was handsome and prepossessing.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ His manners were captivating, noble, and dignified, yet unaffectedly condescending.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ Homer, as well as Virgil, was familiar to the Prince of Wales; and his memory, which was very tenacious, enabled him to cite with graceful readiness the favourite passages of either poet.вҖқвҒ вҖ”The HistoricalвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ Memoirs of Sir N.W. Wraxall, 1884, v. 353, 354.] вҶ©

[вҖңWaving myself, let me talk to you of the Prince Regent. He ordered me to be presented to him at a ball; and after some sayings peculiarly pleasing from royal lips, as to my own attempts, he talked to me of you and your immortalities; he preferred you to every other bard past and present.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ He spoke alternately of Homer and yourself, and seemed well acquainted with both.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ [All] this was conveyed in language which would only suffer by my attempting to transcribe it, and with a tone and taste which gave me a very high idea of his abilities and accomplishments, which I had hitherto considered as confined to manners certainly superior to those of any living gentleman.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Letter to Sir Walter Scott, July 6, 1812, Letters, 1898, ii. 134.] вҶ©

B. 10bre 7th 1822.вҒ вҖ”[MS.]

A sculptor projected to hew Mount Athos into a statue of Alexander, with a city in one hand, and, I believe, a river in his pocket, with various other similar devices. But AlexanderвҖҷs gone, and Athos remains, I trust ere long to look over a nation of freemen.

[It was an architect named Stasicrates who proposed to execute this imperial monument. But Alexander bade him leave Mount Athos alone. As it was, it might be christened вҖңXerxes, his Folly,вҖқ and, for his part, he preferred to regard Mount Caucasus, and the Himalayas, and the river Don as the symbolic memorials of his acts and deeds.вҒ вҖ”PlutarchвҖҷs Moralia. вҖңDe Alexandri Fortuna et Virtute,вҖқ Orat. II. cap. ii.] вҶ©

[The вҖңPolitical EconomyвҖқ Club was founded in April, 1821. James Mill, Thomas Tooke, and David Ricardo were among the original members, See Political Economy Club, Revised Report, 1876, p. 60.] вҶ©

[Stanzas lxxxviii. and lxxxix. are not in the MS.] вҶ©

Fy. 12th 1823. вҶ©

[The allusion is to the refrain of CanningвҖҷs verses on Pitt, вҖңThe Pilot that weathered the storm.вҖқ Compare, too, вҖңThe daring pilot in extremityвҖқ (i.e. the Earl of Shaftesbury), who вҖңsought the stormsвҖқ (DrydenвҖҷs Absalom and Achitophel, lines 159вҒ вҖ“вҒ 161).] вҶ©

[Johnson loved вҖңdear, dear Bathurst,вҖқ because he was вҖңa very good hater.вҖқвҒ вҖ”See BoswellвҖҷs Johnson, 1876, p. 78 (CrokerвҖҷs footnote).] вҶ©

[So, too, Charles Kingsley, in Westward Ho! ii. 299, 300, calls Don Quixote вҖңthe saddest of books in spite of all its wit.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Notes and Queries, Second Series, iii. 124.] вҶ©

By that great EpicвҒ вҖ”.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[вҖңYour husband is in his old lunes again.вҖқ Merry Wives of Windsor, act iv. sc. 2, lines 16, 17.] вҶ©

[вҖңDavus sum, non Oedipus.вҖқ Terence, Andria, act i. sc. 2, line 23.] вҶ©

[вҖңвҖҠвҖҳT is not in mortals to command success,
But weвҖҷll do more, SemproniusвҒ вҖ”weвҖҷll deserve it.вҖқ

AddisonвҖҷs Cato, act i. sc. 2, ed. 1777, ii. 77.]

вҶ©

[CompareвҒ вҖ”вҖңThe colt thatвҖҷs backed and burthened being young.вҖқ Venus and Adonis, lxx. line 5.] вҶ©

[To вҖңbreak square,вҖқ or вҖңsquares,вҖқ is to interrupt the regular order, as in the proverbial phrase, вҖңIt breaks no squares,вҖқ i.e. does no harmвҒ вҖ”does not matter. Compare Sterne, Tristram Shandy (1802), ii. v. 152, вҖңThis fault in Trim broke no squares with themвҖқ (N. Engl. Dict., art. вҖңBreak,вҖқ No.В 46). The origin of the phrase is uncertain, but it may, perhaps, refer to military tactics. Shakespeare (Henry V., act iv. sc. 2, line 28) speaks of вҖңsquares of battle.вҖқ] вҶ©

вҖңWith every thing that pretty bin,
My lady sweet, arise.вҖқ

Cymbeline, act ii. sc. 3, lines, 25, 26.

[So Warburton and Hanmer. The folio reads вҖңthat pretty is.вҖқ See KnightвҖҷs Shakespeare, Pictorial Edition, Tragedies, i. 203.] вҶ©

[The house which Byron occupied, 1815вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1816, No.В 13, Piccadilly Terrace, was the property of Elizabeth, Duchess of Devonshire.] вҶ©

The slightest obstacle which may encumber
The path downhill is something grand.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

Not even in fools who howsoever blind.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

That anything is new to a Chinese;
And such is EuropeвҖҷs fashionable ease.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

A hidden wine beneath an icy presence.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

Though this we hope has been reserved for this age.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[вҖңFor the creed of Zoroaster,вҖқ see Sir Walter Scott, Letters on Demonology and Witchcraft, 1830, pp. 87, 88. (See, too, Cain, act ii. sc. 2, line 404, Poetical Works, 1901, v. 254, note 2.)] вҶ©

вҖңArcades ambo.вҖқ [Virgil, Bucol., Ecl. vii. 4.] вҶ©

[So travel the rich.] вҶ©

вҖ”the noble host intends.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[вҖңJudicious drank, and greatly-daring dined.вҖқ Pope, Dunciad, iv. 318.] вҶ©

[ByronвҖҷs description of the place of his inheritance, which was to know him no more, is sketched from memory, but it unites the charm of a picture with the accuracy of a ground-plan. Eight years had gone by since he had looked his last on вҖңvenerable archвҖқ and вҖңlucid lakeвҖқ (see вҖңEpistle to Augusta,вҖқ stanza viii. lines 7, 8), but he had not forgotten, he could not forget, that enchanted and enchanting scene.

Newstead Abbey or Priory was founded by Henry II., by way of deodand or expiation for the murder of Thomas Becket. Lands which bordered the valley of the Leen, and which had formed part of Sherwood Forest, were assigned for the use and endowment of a chapter of вҖңblack canons regular of the order of St.В Augustine,вҖқ and on a site, by the river-side to the south of the forest uplands (stanza lv. lines 5вҒ вҖ“вҒ 8) the new stede, or place, or station, arose. It was a вҖңNorman AbbeyвҖқ (stanza lv. line 1) which the Black Canons dedicated to Our Lady, and, here and there, in the cloisters, traces of Norman architecture remain, but the enlargement and completion of the monastery was carried out in successive stages and вҖңtransition periods,вҖқ in a style or styles which, perhaps, more by hap than by cunning, Byron rightly named вҖңmixed GothicвҖқ (stanza lv. line 4). To work their mills, and perhaps to drain the marshy valley, the monks dammed the Leen and excavated a chain of lakesвҒ вҖ”the largest to the north-west, ByronвҖҷs вҖңlucid lake;вҖқ a second to the south of the Abbey; and a third, now surrounded with woods, and overlooked by the вҖңwicked lordвҖҷsвҖқ вҖңragged rockвҖқ below the Abbey, half a mile to the south-east. The вҖңcascade,вҖқ which flows over and through a stone-work sluice, and forms a rocky water-fall, issues from the upper lake, and is in full view of the west front of the Abbey. Almost at right angles to these lakes are three ponds: the Forest Pond to the north of the stone wall, which divides the garden from the forest; the square вҖңEagleвҖқ Pond in the MonksвҖҷ Garden; and the narrow stew-pond, bordered on either side with overhanging yews, which drains into the second or Garden Lake. Byron does not enlarge on this double chain of lakes and ponds, and, perhaps for the sake of pictorial unity, converts the second (if a second then existed) and third lakes into a river.

The Abbey, which, at the dissolution of monasteries in 1539, was handed over by Henry VIII. to Sir John Byron, вҖңsteward and warden of the forest of Shirewood,вҖқ was converted, here and there, more or less, into a baronial вҖңmansionвҖқ (stanza lxvi.). It is, roughly speaking, a square block of buildings, flanking the sides of a grassy quadrangle. Surrounding the quadrangle are two-storied cloisters, and in the centre a вҖңGothic fountainвҖқ (stanza lxv. line 1) of composite workmanship. The upper portion of the stonework is hexagonal, and is ornamented with a double row of gargoyles (all вҖңmonstersвҖқ and no вҖңsaints,вҖқ recalling, perhaps identical with, the вҖңseven deadly sinsвҖқ gargoyles, still in situ in the quadrangle of Magdalen College, Oxford); the lower half, which belongs to the seventeenth or eighteenth century, is hollowed into niches of a Roman or classical design. (In ByronвҖҷs time the fountain stood in a courtyard in front of the Abbey, but before he composed this canto it had been restored by Colonel Wildman to its original place within the quadrangle. Byron was acquainted with the change, and writes accordingly.) When the Byrons took possession of the Abbey the upper stories of the cloisters were converted, on three sides of the quadrangle, into galleries, and on the fourth, the north side, into a library. Abutting on the cloisters are the monastic buildings proper, in part transformed, but with вҖңmuch of the monasticвҖқ preserved. On the west, the front of the Abbey, the ground floor consists of the entrance hall and MonksвҖҷ Parlour, and, above, the GuestsвҖҷ Refectory or Banqueting-hall, and the PriorвҖҷs Parlour. On the south, the Xenodochium or Guesten Hall, and, above, the MonksвҖҷ Refectory, or Grand Drawing-room; on the south and east, on the ground floor, the PriorвҖҷs Lodgings, the Chapter House (вҖңthe exquisite small chapel,вҖқ stanza lxvi. line 5), the вҖңslypeвҖқ or passage between church and Chapter House; and in the upper story, the state bedrooms, named after the kings, Edward III., Henry VII., etc., who, by the terms of the grant of land to the Prior and Canons, were entitled to free quarters in the Abbey. During ByronвҖҷs brief tenure of Newstead, and for long years before, these вҖңhuge halls, long galleries, and spacious chambersвҖқ (stanza lxxvii. line 1) were half dismantled, and in a more or less ruinous condition. A few pictures remained on the walls of the Great Drawing-room, of the PriorвҖҷs Parlour, and in the apartments of the south-east wing or annexe, which dates from the seventeenth century (see the account of a visit to Newstead in 1812, in Beauties of England and Wales, 1813, xii. 401вҒ вҖ“вҒ 405). There are and were portraits, by Lely (stanza lxviii. line 7), of a Lady Byron, of Fanny Jennings, Duchess of Tyrconnel, вҖңloveliness personified,вҖқ of Mrs.В Hughes, and of Nell Gwynne; by Sir Godfrey Kneller, of William and Mary; by unnamed artists, of George I. and George II.; and by Ramsay, of George III. There are portraits of a fat Prior, William Sandall, with a jewelled reliquary; of вҖңSir John the Little with the Great Beard,вҖқ who ruled in the PriorвҖҷs stead; and there is the portrait, a votive tablet of penitence and remorse, вҖңof that Lord Arundel Who struck in heat the child he loved so wellвҖқ (see вҖңA Picture at Newstead,вҖқ by Matthew Arnold, Poetical Works, 1890, p. 177); but of portraits of judges or bishops, or of pictures by old masters, there is neither trace nor record.

But the characteristic feature of Newstead Abbey, so familiar that description seems unnecessary, and, yet, never quite accurately described, is the west front of the Priory Church, which is in line with the west front of the Abbey. вҖңHalf apart,вҖқ the southern portion of this front, which abuts on the windows of the PriorвҖҷs Parlour, and the room above, where Byron slept, flanks and conceals the west end of the north cloisters and library; but, with this exception, it is a screen, and nothing more. In the centre is the вҖңmighty windowвҖқ (stanza lxii. line 1), shorn of glass and tracery; above are six lancet windows (which Byron seems to have regarded as niches), and, above again, in a вҖңhigher nicheвҖқ (stanza lxi. line 1), is the crowned Virgin with the Babe in her arms, which escaped, as by a miracle, the вҖңfiery dartsвҖқвҒ вҖ”the shot and cannon-balls of the Cromwellian troopers. On either side of the central window are вҖңtwo blank windows containing tracery [вҖҳgeometrical decoratedвҖҷ]вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ carved [in relief] on the solid ashlar;вҖқ on either side of the window, and at the northern and southern extremities of the front, are buttresses with canopied niches, in each of which a saint or apostle must once have stood. Over the west door there is the mutilated figure of (?) the Saviour, but of twelve saints or twelve niches there is no trace. The вҖңgrand archвҖқ is an ivy-clad screen, and nothing more. Behind and beyond, in place of vanished nave, of aisle and transept, is the smooth green turf; and at the east end, on the site of the high altar, stands the urn-crowned masonry of BoatswainвҖҷs tomb.

Newstead Abbey was sold by Lord Byron to his old schoolfellow, Colonel Thomas Wildman, in November, 1817. The house and property were resold in 1861, by his widow, to William Frederick Webb, Esq., a traveller in many lands, the friend and host of David Livingstone. At his death the estate was inherited by his daughter, Miss Geraldine Webb, who was married to General Sir Herbert Charles Chermside, G.C.M.G., etc., Governor of Queensland, in 1899.

For Newstead Abbey, see Beauties of England and Wales, 1813, xii. Part I. 401вҒ вҖ“вҒ 405 (often reprinted without acknowledgment); Abbotsford and Newstead Abbey, by Washington Irving, 1835; Journal of the Archaeological Association (papers by T.J. Pettigrew, F.R.S., and Arthur Ashpitel, F.S.A.), 1854, vol. ix. pp. 14вҒ вҖ“вҒ 39; and A Souvenir of Newstead Abbey (illustrated by a series of admirable photographs), by Richard Allen, Nottingham, 1874, etc., etc.] вҶ©

[The woodlands were sacrificed to the needs or fancies of ByronвҖҷs great-uncle, the вҖңwicked Lord.вҖқ One splendid oak, known as the вҖңPilgrimвҖҷs Oak,вҖқ which stood and stands near the north lodge of the park, near the вҖңHut,вҖқ was bought in by the neighbouring gentry, and made over to the estate. Perhaps by the Druid oak Byron meant to celebrate this вҖңlast of the clan,вҖқ which, in his day, before the woods were replanted, must have stood out in solitary grandeur.] вҶ©

[Compare вҖңEpistle to Augusta,вҖқ stanza x. line 1, Poetical Works, 1901, iv. 68.] вҶ©

[The little wood which Byron planted at the south-east corner of the upper or вҖңStableвҖқ Lake, known as вҖңPoetвҖҷs Corner,вҖқ still slopes to the waterвҖҷs brink. Nor have the wild-fowl diminished. The lower of the three lakes is specially reserved as a breeding-place.] вҶ©

Its shriller echoвҒ вҖ”.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

Which sympathized with TimeвҖҷs and TempestвҖҷs march,
In gazing on that high and haughty Arch.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[See lines вҖңOn Leaving Newstead Abbey,вҖқ stanza 5, Poetical Works, 1898, i. 3, note 1.] вҶ©

But in the stillness of the moonвҒ вҖ”.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[Vide ante, The Deformed Transformed, Part I. line 532, Poetical Works, 1901, v. 497.] вҶ©

This is not a frolic invention: it is useless to specify the spot, or in what county, but I have heard it both alone and in company with those who will never hear it more. It can, of course, be accounted for by some natural or accidental cause, but it was a strange sound, and unlike any other I have ever heard (and I have heard many above and below the surface of the earth produced in ruins, etc., etc., or caverns).вҒ вҖ”[MS.]

[вҖңThe unearthly soundвҖқ may still be heard at rare intervals, but it is difficult to believe that the вҖңhuge archвҖқ can act as an ГҶolian harp. Perhaps the smaller lancet windows may vocalize the wind.] вҶ©

Prouder of such a toy than of their breed.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

Salvator Rosa. The wicked necessity of rhyming obliges me to adapt the name to the verse.вҒ вҖ”[MS.]

[CompareвҒ вҖ”

вҖңWhateвҖҷer Lorraine light touchвҖҷd with softening hue,
Or savage Rosa dashвҖҷd, or learned Poussin drew.вҖқ

ThomsonвҖҷs Castle of Indolence, Canto I. stanza xxxviii. lines 8, 9.]

вҶ©

If I err not, вҖңyour DaneвҖқ is one of IagoвҖҷs catalogue of nations вҖңexquisite in their drinking.вҖқ

[вҖңYour Dane, your German, and your swag-bellied HollanderвҒ вҖ”drink hoa! are nothing to your English.вҖқ вҖңIs your Englishman so exquisite in his drinking?вҖқ (So Collier and Knight. The Quarto reads вҖңexpertвҖқ).вҒ вҖ”Othello, act ii. sc. 3, lines 71вҒ вҖ“вҒ 74.] вҶ©

His bell-mouthed gobletвҒ вҖ”and his laughing group
Provoke my thirstвҒ вҖ”what ho! a flask of Rhenish.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

Hath yet at night the very best of wines.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[вҖңSea-coalвҖқ (i.e. Newcastle coal), as distinguished from вҖңcharcoalвҖқ and вҖңearth-coal.вҖқ But the qualification must have been unusual and old-fashioned in 1822. вҖңEarth-coalвҖқ is found in large quantities on the Newstead estate, and the Abbey, far below its foundations, is tunnelled by a coal-drift.] вҶ©

[See GrayвҖҷs omitted stanzaвҒ вҖ”

вҖңвҖҠвҖҳHere scatterвҖҷd oft, the earliest of the year,
By hands unseen, are showers of violets found;
The red-breast loves to build and warble here,
And little footsteps lightly print the ground.вҖҷ

As fineвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ as any in his Elegy. I wonder that he could have the heart to omit it.вҖқвҒ вҖ”вҖңExtracts from a Diary,вҖқ February 27, 1821, Letters, 1901, v. 210. The stanza originally preceded the Epitaph.] вҶ©

In Assyria. [See Daniel iii. 1.] вҶ©

вёәвҒ she hath the tame
Preserved within doorsвҒ вҖ”why not make them Game?

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[It is difficult, if not impossible, to furnish a clue to the names of all the guests at Norman Abbey. Some who are included in this ghostly вҖңhouse-partyвҖқ seem to be, and, perhaps, were meant to be, nomina umbrarum; and others are, undoubtedly, contemporary celebrities, under a more or less transparent disguise. A few of these shadows have been substantiated (vide infra, et post), but the greater part decline to be materialized or verified.] вҶ©

вёәвҒ the Countess Squabby.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[Perhaps Mary, widow of the eighth Earl of Cork and Orrery: вҖңDowager Cork,вҖқ вҖңOld Corky,вҖқ of Joseph JekyllвҖҷs Correspondence, 1894, pp. 83, 275.] вҶ©

[Mrs.В Rabbi may be Mrs.В Coutts, the Mrs.В Million of Vivian Grey (1826, i. 183), who arrived at вҖңChГўteau Desir in a crimson silk pelisse, hat and feathers, with diamond ear-rings, and a rope of gold round her neck.вҖқ] вҶ©

[Lie, lye, or ley, is a solution of potassium salts obtained by bleaching wood-ashes. Byron seems to have confused вҖңlieвҖқ with вҖңlee,вҖқ i.e. dregs, sediment.] вҶ©

[вҖңAroint thee, witch! the rump-fed ronyon cries.вҖқ Macbeth, act ii. sc. 3, line 6.] вҶ©

Or (to come to the point, like my friend Pulci).

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[Hor., Epist. Ad Pisones, line 343.] вҶ©

вёәвҒ by fear or flattery.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

Siria, i.e. bitch-star. вҶ©

I have seenвҒ вҖ”no matter whatвҒ вҖ”we now shall see.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[Parolles [see AllвҖҷs Well that Ends Well, passim] is Brougham (vide ante, the suppressed stanzas, Canto I. pp. 67вҒ вҖ“вҒ 69). It is possible that this stanza was written after the Canto as a whole was finished. But, if not, an incident which took place in the House of Commons, April 17, 1823, during a debate on Catholic Emancipation, may be quoted in corroboration of BroughamвҖҷs unreadiness with regard to the point of honour. In the course of his speech he accused Canning of вҖңmonstrous truckling for the purpose of obtaining office,вҖқ and Canning, without waiting for Brougham to finish, gave him the lie: вҖңI rise to say that that is falseвҖқ (Parl. Deb., N.S. vol. 8, p. 1091).

There was a вҖңscene,вҖқ which ended in an exchange of explanations and quasi-apologies, and henceforth, as a rule, parliamentary insults were given and received without recourse to duelling. Byron was not aware that the вҖңold orderвҖқ had passed or was passing. Compare Hazlitt, in The Spirit of the Age, 1825, pp. 302, 303: вҖңHe [Brougham] is adventurous, but easily panic-struck, and sacrifices the vanity of self-opinion to the necessity of self-preservationвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ himself the first to get out of harmвҖҷs way and escape from the danger;вҖқ and Mr.В Parthenopex Puff (W. Stewart Rose), in Vivian Grey (1826, i. 186, 187), вҖңOh! heвҖҷs a prodigious fellow! What do you think Booby says? he says, that Foaming Fudge [Brougham] can do more than any man in Great Britain; that he had one day to plead in the KingвҖҷs Bench, spout at a tavern, speak in the House, and fight a duelвҒ вҖ”and that he found time for everything but the last.вҖқ] вҶ©

There was, too, Henry BвҒ вёә.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[In his Journal for December 5, 1813, Byron writes: вҖңThe Duke of вёә called.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ His Grace is a good, noble, ducal personвҖқ (Letters, 1898, ii. 361). Possibly the earlier вҖңDuke of DashвҖқ was William Spencer, sixth Duke of Devonshire, an old schoolfellow of ByronвҖҷs, who was eager to renew the acquaintance (Letters, 1899, iii. 98, note 2); and, if so, he may be reckoned as one of the guests of вҖңNorman Abbey.вҖқ] вҶ©

[Gronow (Reminiscences, 1889, i. 234вҒ вҖ“вҒ 240) identifies the Chevalier de la Ruse with Casimir Comte de Montrond (1768вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1843), back-stairs diplomatist, wit, gambler, and man of fashion. He was the lifelong companion, if not friend, of Talleyrand, who pleaded for him: вҖңQui est-ce qui ne lвҖҷaimerait pas, il est si vicieux!вҖқ At one time in the pay of Napoleon, he fell under his displeasure, and, to avoid arrest, spent two years of exile (1812вҒ вҖ“вҒ 14) in England. вҖңHe was not,вҖқ says Gronow, вҖңa great talker, nor did he swaggerвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ or laugh at his own bons-mots. He was demure, sleek, sly, and dangerous.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ In the London clubs he went by the name of Old French.вҖқ He was a constant guest of the Duke of YorkвҖҷs at Oatlands, вҖңand won much at his whist-tableвҖқ (English Whist, by W.P. Courtney, 1894, p. 181). For his second residence in England, and for a sketch by DвҖҷOrsay, see A Portion of the Journal, etc., by Thomas Raikes, 1857, frontispiece to vol. iv., et vols. i.-iv. passim. See, for biographical notice, LвҖҷAmi de M. de Talleyrand, par Henri Welschinger, La Revue de Paris, 1895, Fev., tom. i. pp. 640вҒ вҖ“вҒ 654.] вҶ©

[Perhaps Sir James MackintoshвҒ вҖ”a frequent guest at Holland House.] вҶ©

[Possibly Colonel (afterwards Sir James) Macdonell [d. 1857], вҖңa man of colossal stature,вҖқ who occupied and defended the ChГўteau of Hougoumont on the night before the battle of Waterloo. (See Gronow, Reminiscences, 1889, i. 76, 77.)] вҶ©

[Sir George Prevost (1767вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1816), the Governor-General of British North America, and nominally Commander-in-chief of the Army in the second American War, contributed, by his excess of caution, supineness, and delay, to the humiliation of the British forces. The particular allusion is to his alleged inaction at a critical moment in the engagement of September 11, 1814, between Commodore Macdonough and Captain Downie in Plattsburg Bay. вҖңA letter was sent to Capt.В Downie, strongly urging him to come on, as the army had long been waiting for his co-operation.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ The brave Downie replied that he required no urging to do his duty.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ He was as good as his word. The guns were scaled when he got under way, upon hearing which Sir George issued an order for the troops to cook, instead of that of instant co-operation.вҖқвҒ вҖ”To Editor of the Montreal Herald, May 23, 1815, Letters of Veritas, 1815, pp. 116, 117. See, too, The Quarterly Review, July, 1822, vol. xxvii. p. 446.] вҶ©

[George Hardinge (1744вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1816), who was returned M.P. for Old Sarum in 1784, was appointed, in 1787, Senior Justice of the Counties of Brecon, Glamorgan, and Radnor. According to the GentlemanвҖҷs Magazine, 1816 (vol. lxxxvi. p. 563), вҖңIn conversation he had few equals.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ He delighted in pleasantries, and always afforded to his auditors abundance of mirth and entertainment as well as information.вҖқ Byron seems to have supposed that these вҖңpleasantriesвҖқ found their way into his addresses to condemned prisoners, but if the charges printed in his Miscellaneous Works, edited by John Nichols in 1818, are reported in full, he was entirely mistaken. They are tedious, but the вҖңwaggeryвҖқ is conspicuous by its absence.] вҶ©

With all his laurels growing upon one tree.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[John Philpot Curran (1750вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1817). вҖңDid you know Curran?вҖқ asked Byron of Lady Blessington (Conversations, 1834, p. 176); вҖңhe was the most wonderful person I ever saw. In him was combined an imagination the most brilliant and profound, with a flexibility and wit that would have justified the observation applied toвҒ вҖ”вҒ that his heart was in his head.вҖқ (See, too, Detached Thoughts, No.В 24, Letters, 1901, v. 421.)] вҶ©

[For Thomas Lord Erskine (1750вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1823), see Letters, 1898, ii. 390, note 5. See, too, Detached Thoughts, No.В 93, Letters, 1901, v. 455, 456. In his Spirit of the Age, 1825, pp. 297, 298, Hazlitt contrasts вҖңthe impassioned appeals and flashes of wit of a CurranвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ the golden tide of wisdom, eloquence, and fancy of a Burke,вҖқ with the вҖңdashing and graceful mannerвҖқ which concealed the poverty and вҖңdeadnessвҖқ of the matter of ErskineвҖҷs speeches.] вҶ©

вёәвҒ all classes mostly pull
At the same oarвҒ вҖ”.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[вҖңMrs.В Adams answered Mr.В Adams, that it was blasphemous to talk of Scripture out of church.вҖқ This dogma was broached to her husbandвҒ вҖ”the best Christian in any book.вҒ вҖ”See The History of the Adventures of Joseph Andrews, Bk. IV. chap. xi. ed. 1876, p. 324.] вҶ©

вёәвҒ in the ripe age.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[Probably Richard Sharp (1759вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1835), known as вҖңConversation Sharp.вҖқ Byron frequently met him in society in 1813вҒ вҖ“вҒ 14, and in вҖңExtracts from a Diary,вҖқ January 9, 1821, Letters, 1901, v. 161, describes him as вҖңthe Conversationist.вҖқ He visited Byron at the Villa Diodati in the autumn of 1816 (Life, p. 323).] вҶ©

[Hamlet, act i. sc. 5, line 22.] вҶ©

Nor bate (read bait)вҒ вёә.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[See letters to the Earl of Blessington, April 5, 1823, Letters, 1891, vi. 187.] вҶ©

But full of wisdomвҒ вҖ”.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

A sort of rose entwining with a thistle.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[Iliad, x. 341, sq.] вҶ©

It would have taught him humanity at least. This sentimental savage, whom it is a mode to quote (amongst the novelists) to show their sympathy for innocent sports and old songs, teaches how to sew up frogs, and break their legs by way of experiment, in addition to the art of anglingвҒ вҖ”the cruelest, the coldest, and the stupidest of pretended sports. They may talk about the beauties of nature, but the angler merely thinks of his dish of fish; he has no leisure to take his eyes from off the streams, and a single bite is worth to him more than all the scenery around. Besides, some fish bite best on a rainy day. The whale, the shark, and the tunny fishery have somewhat of noble and perilous in them; even net fishing, trawling, etc., are more humane and useful. But angling!вҒ вҖ”no angler can be a good man.

вҖңOne of the best men I ever knewвҒ вҖ”as humane, delicate-minded, generous, and excellent a creature as any in the worldвҒ вҖ”was an angler: true, he angled with painted flies, and would have been incapable of the extravagancies of I. Walton.вҖқ

The above addition was made by a friend in reading over the MS.вҒ вҖ”вҖңAudi alteram partem.вҖқвҒ вҖ”I leave it to counter-balance my own observation. вҶ©

B. Fy. 19th 1823.вҒ вҖ”[MS.] вҶ©

Fry. 23, 1814 (sic).вҒ вҖ”[MS.] вҶ©

[CompareвҒ вҖ”

вҖңOur little systems have their day;
They have their day and cease to be.вҖқ

TennysonвҖҷs In Memoriam.]

вҶ©

[With this open mind with regard to the future, compare Charles KingsleyвҖҷs вҖңreverent curiosityвҖқ (Letters and Memoirs, etc., 1883, p. 349).] вҶ©

[вҖңWe usually try which way the wind bloweth, by casting up grass or chaff, or such light things into the air.вҖқвҒ вҖ”BaconвҖҷs Natural History, No.В 820, Works, 1740, iii. 168.] вҶ©

[вҖңThe World was all before them.вҖқ Paradise Lost, bk. xii. line 646.] вҶ©

[вҖңBut why then publish?вҒ вҖ”Granville, the polite,
And knowing Walsh, would tell me I could write.вҖқ

Pope, Prologue to Satires, lines 135, 136.]

вҶ©

[Virg., Aen., ii. 91 вҖң(Haud ignota);вҖқ et ibid., line 6.] вҶ©

[Hor., Od. iii. 2. 26.] вҶ©

And though by no means overpowered with riches,
Would gladly place beneath it my last rag of breeches.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

Craning.вҒ вҖ”вҖңTo craneвҖқ is, or was, an expression used to denote a gentlemanвҖҷs stretching out his neck over a hedge, вҖңto look before he leaped;вҖқвҒ вҖ”a pause in his вҖңvaulting ambition,вҖқ which in the field doth occasion some delay and execration in those who may be immediately behind the equestrian sceptic. вҖңSir, if you donвҖҷt choose to take the leap, let me!вҖқвҒ вҖ”was a phrase which generally sent the aspirant on again; and to good purpose: for though вҖңthe horse and riderвҖқ might fall, they made a gap through which, and over him and his steed, the field might follow. вҶ©

The sulky Huntsman grimly said вҖңThe Frenchman
Was almost worthy to become his henchman.вҖқ

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

And what notвҒ вҖ”though he had ridden like a Centaur
When called next day declined the same adventure.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[Mr.В W. Ernst, in his Memoirs of the Life of Lord Chesterfield, 1893 (p. 425, note 2), quotes these lines in connection with a comparison between French and English sport, contained in a letter from Lord Chesterfield to his son, dated June 30, 1751: вҖңThe French manner of hunting is gentlemanlike; ours is only for bumpkins and boobies.вҖқ Elsewhere, however (The World, No.В 92, October 3, 1754), commenting on a remark of PascalвҖҷs, he admits вҖңthat the jolly sportsmanвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ improves his health, at least, by his exercise.вҖқ] вҶ©

[вҖқвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ as she skimmвҖҷd along,
Her flying feet unbathвҖҷd on billows hung.вҖқ

DrydenвҖҷs Virgil (Aen., vii. 1101, 1102).]

вҶ©

[See Poetical Works, 1898, i. 492, note 1.] вҶ©

[GuidoвҖҷs fresco of the Aurora, вҖңscattering flowers before the chariot of the sunвҖқ is on a ceiling of the Casino in the Palazzo Rospigliosi, in Rome.] вҶ©

[Byron described Count Alfred DвҖҷOrsay as having вҖңall the airs of a Cupidon dГ©chaГ®nГ©.вҖқ See letters to Moore and the Earl of Blessington, April 2, 1823, Letters, 1901, vi. 180, 185.] вҶ©

In SwiftвҖҷs or Horace WalpoleвҖҷs letters I think it is mentioned that somebody, regretting the loss of a friend, was answered by an universal Pylades: вҖңWhen I lose one, I go to the Saint JamesвҖҷs Coffee-house, and take another.вҖқ I recollect having heard an anecdote of the same kind.вҒ вҖ”Sir W.D. was a great gamester. Coming in one day to the Club of which he was a member, he was observed to look melancholy.вҒ вҖ”вҖңWhat is the matter, Sir William?вҖқ cried Hare, of facetious memory.вҒ вҖ”вҖңAh!вҖқ replied Sir W., вҖңI have just lost poor Lady D.вҖқвҒ вҖ”вҖңLost! What at? Quinze or Hazard?вҖқ was the consolatory rejoinder of the querist.

[The dramatis personae are probably Sir William Drummond (1770вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1828), author of the Academical Questions, etc., and Francis Hare, the wit, known as the вҖңвҖҠвҖҳSilent Hare,вҖҷ from his extreme loquacity.вҖқвҒ вҖ”GronowвҖҷs Reminiscences, 1889, ii. 98вҒ вҖ“вҒ 101.] вҶ©

They own that you are fairly dished at last.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

The famous Chancellor [Axel Oxenstiern (1583вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1654)] said to his son, on the latter expressing his surprise upon the great effects arising from petty causes in the presumed mystery of politics: вҖңYou see by this, my son, with how little wisdom the kingdoms of the world are governed.вҖқ

[The story is that his son John, who had been sent to represent him at the Congress of Westphalia, 1648, wrote home to complain that the task was beyond him, and that he could not cope with the difficulties which he was encountering, and that the Chancellor replied, вҖңNescis, mi fili, quantillГў prudentiГў homines regantur.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Biographie Universelle, art. вҖңOxenstierna.вҖқ] вҶ©

Who are our sureties that our moral pure is.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

And not to encourage whispering in the house.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[Once upon a time, Tiresias, who was shepherding on Mount Cyllene, wantonly stamped with his heel on a pair of snakes, and was straightway turned into a woman. Seven years later he was led to treat another pair of snakes in like fashion, and, happily or otherwise, was turned back into a man. Hence, when Jupiter and Juno fell to wrangling on the comparative enjoyments of men and women, the question was referred to Tiresias, as a person of unusual experience and authority. He gave it in favour of the woman, and Juno, who was displeased at his answer, struck him with blindness. But Jupiter, to make amends, gave him the вҖңliberty of prophesyingвҖқ for seven, some say nine, generations. (See Ovid, Metam., iii. 320; and Thomas MunckerвҖҷs notes on the Fabulae of Hyginus, No. lxxv. ed. 1681, pp. 126вҒ вҖ“вҒ 128.)] вҶ©

[Midsummer NightвҖҷs Dream, act ii. sc. i, line 168.] вҶ©

See La Nouvelle HГ©loГҜse. вҶ©

Hor., Epod., II. line 1. вҶ©

[The Latin proverb, Noscitur ex sociis, is not an Horatian maxim.] вҶ©

I, therefore, deal in generalsвҒ вҖ”which is wise.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[See SheridanвҖҷs Critic (вҖңTilburinaвҖқ loq.), act iii. s.f.] вҶ©

[For вҖңthe coxcomb CzarвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ the somewhat agГ©d youth,вҖқ see The Age of Bronze, lines 434вҒ вҖ“вҒ 483, Poetical Works, 1901, v. 563, note 1.] вҶ©

[Compare Sardanapalus, act i. sc. 2, line 1, ibid., p. 15, note 1.] вҶ©

[Compare Childe Harold, Canto III. stanza lxxi. line 3, Poetical Works, 1899, ii. 261, 300, note 17.] вҶ©

Or GermanyвҒ вҖ”she knew nought of all this
Impracticable, novel-reading trance.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

Even thereвҒ вҖ”as in relationship will hold,
And make the feeling of a finer mood.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[вҖңThese violent delights have violent ends,
And in their triumph die.вҖқ

Romeo and Juliet, act ii. sc. 6, lines 9, 10.]

вҶ©

Alas! I quote experienceвҒ вҖ”seldom yet
I had a paramourвҒ вҖ”and IвҖҷve had manyвҒ вҖ”
Whom I had not some reason to regretвҒ вҖ”
For whom I did not make myself a Zany.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

I also had a wifeвҒ вҖ”not to forget
The marriage stateвҒ вҖ”the best or worst of any,
Who was the very paragon of wives
Yet mad the misery of many
both our
several lives.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[Lady Holland, Lady Jersey, Madame de StaГ«l, and before and above all, his sister, Mrs.В Leigh.] вҶ©

I also had some female friendsвҒ вҖ”by GвҒ вҖ”d!
Or if the oath seem strongвҒ вҖ”I swear by Jove!

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

Who stuck to meвҒ вҖ”.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[Byron must have been among the first to naturalize the French milliard (a thousand millions), which was used by Voltaire.] вҶ©

[Othello, act i. sc. 3, line 140.] вҶ©

B. March 4th 1823.вҒ вҖ”[MS.] вҶ©

[It is impossible to persuade the metaphor to march вҖңon all-fours,вҖқ but, to drag it home, by a kind of вҖңfrogвҖҷs march,вҖқ the unfulfilled wants of the soul, the вҖңlurking thoughtsвҖқ are as it were bubbles, which we would fain вҖңbreak on the invisible OceanвҖқ of Passion or Emotion the begetter of bubblesвҒ вҖ”Passion which, like the visible Ocean, images Eternity and portrays, but not to the sensual eye, the beatific vision of the things which are not seen, and, even so, вҖңministers to the SoulвҖҷs delightвҖқ! But вҖңwho can tellвҖқ?] вҶ©

While all withoutвҖҷs indicative of rest.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

A thing on which dull Time should never print age,
For whom stern Nature should forego her debt.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[Ransom and Morland were ByronвҖҷs bankers. Douglas Kinnaird was a partner in the firm. (See Letters, 1898, ii. 85, note 2.)] вҶ©

Old Skeleton with ages for your booty.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[вҖңHe turned himself into all manner of forms with more ease than the chameleon changes his colour.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ Thus at Sparta he was all for exercise, frugal in his diet, and severe in his manners. In Asia he was as much for mirth and pleasure, luxury and ease.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Plutarch, Alcibiades, LanghorneвҖҷs translation, 1838, p. 150.] вҶ©

[For the phrase вҖңCupidon DГ©chaГ®nГ©,вҖқ applied to Count DвҖҷOrsay, vide ante, p. 526, note 4.] вҶ©

[Plautus, Truculentus, act ii. sc. 8, line 14.] вҶ©

[RaphaelвҖҷs вҖңTransfigurationвҖқ is in the Vatican.] вҶ©

As it is necessary in these times to avoid ambiguity, I say that I mean, by вҖңDiviner still,вҖқ Christ. If ever God was manвҒ вҖ”or man GodвҒ вҖ”he was both. I never arraigned his creed, but the useвҒ вҖ”or abuse made of it. Mr.В Canning one day quoted Christianity to sanction negro slavery, and Mr.В Wilberforce had little to say in reply. And was Christ crucified, that black men might be scourged? If so, He had better been born a Mulatto, to give both colours an equal chance of freedom, or at least salvation.

[In a debate in the House of Commons, May 15, 1823 (Parl. Deb., N.S. vol. ix. pp. 278, 279), Canning, replying to Fowell BuxtonвҖҷs motion for the Abolition of Slavery, said, вҖңGod forbid that I should contend that the Christian religion is favourable to slaveryвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ but if it be meant that in the Christian religion there is a special denunciation against slavery, that slavery and Christianity cannot exist togetherвҒ вҖ”I think that the honourable gentleman himself must admit that the proposition is historically false.вҖқ] вҶ©

вёәвҒ and One Name Greater still
Whose lot it was to be the most mistaken.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

To leave the world by bigot fashions shaken.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

Which never flatters either Whig or Tory.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[Martial, Epig., x. 46.] вҶ©

[вҖңFeebleвҖқ for вҖңfoibleвҖқ is found in the writings of Mrs.В Behn and Sir R. LвҖҷEstrange (N. Engl. Dict.).] вҶ©

But now I canвҖҷt tell when it will be done.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[The N. Engl. Dict. quotes W. HooperвҖҷs Rational Recreations (1794) as an earlier authority for the use of вҖңconcisionвҖқ in the sense of conciseness.] вҶ©

Who now are welteringвҒ вҖ”.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[вҖңThe cat will mew and dog will have his day.вҖқ Hamlet, act v. sc. 1, line 280.] вҶ©

I should not be the foremost to deride
Their faultвҒ вҖ”but quickly take a sword the other way,
And wax an Ultra-royalist, where Royalty
Had nothing left it but a desperate Loyalty.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[вҖңAnd hold no sin so deeply red
As that of breaking PriscianвҖҷs head.вҖқ

ButlerвҖҷs Hudibras, Part II. Canto II. lines 223, 224.]

вҶ©

[Brougham, in the famous critique of Hours of Idleness (Edinburgh Review, January, 1808, vol. xi. pp. 285вҒ вҖ“вҒ 289), was pleased вҖңto counsel him that he do forthwith abandon poetry and turn his talents, which are considerable, and his opportunities, which are great, to better account.вҖқ Others, however, gave him encouragement. See, for instance, a review by J.H. Markland, who afterwards made his name as editor of the Roxburgh Club issue of the Chester Mysteries (whence, perhaps, Byron derived his knowledge of вҖңMysteries and MoralitiesвҖқ), which concludes thus: вҖңHeartily hoping that the вҖҳillness and depression of spirits,вҖҷ which evidently pervade the greater part of these effusions, are entirely dispelled; confident that вҖҳGeorge Gordon, Lord ByronвҖҷ will have a conspicuous niche in the future editions of вҖҳRoyal and Noble Authors,вҖҷ etc.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Gent. Mag., 1807, vol. lxxvii. p. 1217.] вҶ©

To marshal onwards to the Delphian Height.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[вҖңThree small vessels were apparently all that Columbus had requested. Two of them were light barques, called caravels, not superior to river and coasting craft of more modern days.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ That such long and perilous expeditions into unknown seas, should be undertaken in vessels without decks, and that they should live through the violent tempests by which they were frequently assailed, remain among the singular circumstances of those daring voyages.вҖқвҒ вҖ”History of the Life and Voyages of Christopher Columbus, by Washington Irving, 1831, i. 78.] вҶ©

As Women seldom think by halvesвҒ вҖ”.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

This extraordinary and flourishing German colony in America does not entirely exclude matrimony, as the вҖңShakersвҖқ do; but lays such restrictions upon it as prevents more than a certain quantum of births within a certain number of years; which births (as Mr.В Hulme [perhaps Thomas Hulme, whose Journal is quoted in Hints to Emigrants, 1817, pp. 5вҒ вҖ“вҒ 18] observes) generally arrive вҖңin a little flock like those of a farmerвҖҷs lambs, all within the same month perhaps.вҖқ These Harmonists (so called from the name of their settlement) are represented as a remarkably flourishing, pious, and quiet people. See the various recent writers on America.

[The Harmonists were emigrants from WГјrtemburg, who settled (1803вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1805) under the auspices of George Rapp, in a township 120 miles north of Philadelphia. This they sold, and вҖңtrekkedвҖқ westwards to Indiana. One of their customs was to keep watch by nights and to cry the hours to this tune: вҖңAgain a day is past and a step made nearer to our end. Our time runs away, and the joys of Heaven are our reward.вҖқ (See The Philanthropist, No. xx., 1815, vol. v, pp. 277вҒ вҖ“вҒ 288.)] вҶ©

Which test I leave unto the Lords spiritual.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

Jacob Tonson, according to Mr.В Pope, was accustomed to call his writers вҖңable pens,вҖқ вҖңpersons of honour,вҖқ and, especially, вҖңeminent hands.вҖқ Vide Correspondence, etc., etc.

[вҖңPerhaps I should myself be much better pleased, if I were told you called me your little friend, than if you complimented me with the title of a вҖҳgreat genius,вҖҷ or an eminent hand, as Jacob does all his authors.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Pope to Steele, November 29, 1712, Works of Alexander Pope, 1871, vi. 396.] вҶ©

[See DвҖҷIsraeliвҖҷs Curiosities of Literature, 1841, pp. 450вҒ вҖ“вҒ 452, and the Dissertation prefixed to Francis DouceвҖҷs edition of HolbeinвҖҷs Dance of Death, 1858, pp. 1вҒ вҖ“вҒ 218.] вҶ©

вёәвҒ Miss Allman and Miss Noman.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

вёәвҒ that smooth placid sea
Which did not show and yet concealed a storm.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[Compare Childe Harold, Canto IV. stanza lix. line 3, Poetical Works, 1899, ii. 374, note 2.] вҶ©

[вҖқвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ And, under him,
My Genius is rebuked; as it is said
Mark AntonyвҖҷs was by CГҰsar.вҖқ

Macbeth, act iii, sc. 1, lines 54вҒ вҖ“вҒ 56.]

вҶ©

[WarisonвҒ вҖ”cri-de-guerreвҒ вҖ”note of assault:вҒ вҖ”

вҖңEither receive within these towers
Two hundred of my masterвҖҷs powers,
Or straight they sound their warrison,
And storm and spoil this garrison.вҖқ

Lay of the Last Minstrel, Canto IV. stanza xxiv, lines 17вҒ вҖ“вҒ 20.]

вҶ©

And adds a third to what was late a pair.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[Compare:

вҖңLifeвҖҷs a jest, and all things show it;
I thought so once, and now I know it.вҖқ

GayвҖҷs Epitaph.]

вҶ©

[For вҖңPotage Г  la bonne femme,вҖқ вҖңDindon Г  la PГ©rigueux,вҖқ вҖңSoupe Г  la Beauveau,вҖқ вҖңLe dorey garni dвҖҷГ©perlans frits,вҖқ вҖңLe cuisseau de pore Г  demi sel, garni de choux,вҖқ вҖңLe salmi de perdreaux Г  lвҖҷEspagnole,вҖқ вҖңLes bГ©casses,вҖқ see вҖңBill of Fare for November,вҖқ The French Cook, by Louis Eustache Ude, 1813, p. viii. For вҖңLes poulardes Г  la CondГ©,вҖқ вҖңLe jambon de Westphalie Г  lвҖҷEspagnole,вҖқ вҖңLes petites timballes dвҖҷun salpicon Г  la MonglasвҖқ (?Montglat), вҖңLes filets de perdreaux sautГ©s Г  la Lucullus,вҖқ vide ibid., p. ix., and for вҖңPetits puits dвҖҷamour garnis de confitures,вҖқ vide Plate of Second Course (to face) p. vi.] вҶ©

[Alexander the Great.] вҶ©

A dish вҖңГ  la Lucullus.вҖқ This hero, who conquered the East, has left his more extended celebrity to the transplantation of cherries (which he first brought into Europe), and the nomenclature of some very good dishes;вҒ вҖ”and I am not sure that (barring indigestion) he has not done more service to mankind by his cookery than by his conquests. A cherry tree may weigh against a bloody laurel; besides, he has contrived to earn celebrity from both.

[According to Pliny (Nat, Hist., lib. xv. cap. xxv. ed. 1593, ii. 131), there were no cherry trees in Italy until L. Lucullus brought them home with him from Pontus after the Mithridatic War (B.C. 74), and it was not for another hundred and twenty years that the cherry tree crossed the Channel and was introduced into Britain.] вҶ©

вҖңPetits puits dвҖҷamour garnis de confitures,вҖқвҒ вҖ”a classical and well-known dish for part of the flank of a second course [vide ante, p. 562]. вҶ©

[вҖңTo-day in a palace, to-morrow in a cow-houseвҒ вҖ”this day with a Pacha, the next with a shepherd.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Letter to his mother, July 30, 1810, Letters, 1898, i. 295.] вҶ©

No lady but a dishвҒ вҖ”.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[вҖңThis construction (вҖҳcommenceвҖҷ with the infinitive) has been objected to by stylists,вҖқ says the New English Dictionary (see art. вҖңCommenceвҖқ). Its use is sanctioned by the authority of Pope, Landor, Helps, and Lytton; but even so, it is questionable, if not objectionable.] вҶ©

Sweet Lord! she was so sagely innocent.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

Subauditur вҖңnon;вҖқ omitted for the sake of euphony. вҶ©

[John Scott, Earl of Eldon, Lord Chancellor, 1801 to 1827, sat as judge (November 7, 1822) to hear the petition of Henry Wallop Fellowes, that a commission of inquiry should be issued to ascertain whether his uncle, Lord Portsmouth (who married Mary Anne Hanson, the daughter of ByronвҖҷs solicitor), was of sound mind, вҖңand capable of managing his own person and property.вҖқ The Chancellor gave judgment that a commission be issued, and the jury, February, 1823, returned a verdict that Lord Portsmouth had been a lunatic since 1809. (See Letters, 1898, ii. 393, note 3, et ibid., 1901, vi. 170, note i.)] вҶ©

Hecla is a famous hot-spring in Iceland. [Byron seems to mistake the volcano for the Geysers.] вҶ©

[Hamlet, act iii. sc. 2, line 367.] вҶ©

[вҖңBy the apostle Paul, shadows to-night
Have struck more terror to the soul of Richard
Than can the substance of ten thousand soldiers,вҖқ etc.

Richard III., act v. sc. 3, lines 216вҒ вҖ“вҒ 218.]

вҶ©

Hobbes: who, doubting of his own soul, paid that compliment to the souls of other people as to decline their visits, of which he had some apprehension.

[Bayle (see art. вҖңHobbesвҖқ [Dict. Crit. and Hist., 1736, iii. 471, note N.]) quotes from Vita Hobb., p. 106: вҖңHe was as falsely accused by some of being unwilling to be alone, because he was afraid of spectres and apparitions, vain bugbears of fools, which he had chased away by the light of his Philosophy,вҖқ and proceeds to argue that, perhaps, after all, Hobbes was afraid of the dark. вҖңHe was timorous to the last degree, and consequently he had reason to distrust his imagination when he was alone in a chamber in the night; for in spite of him the memory of what he had read and heard concerning apparitions would revive, though he was not persuaded of the reality of these things.вҖқ See, however, for his own testimony that he was вҖңnot afrayd of sprights,вҖқ Letters and Lives of Eminent Persons, by John Aubrey, 1813, vol. ii. pt. ii. p. 624.] вҶ©

[Hamlet, act iv. sc. 5, lines 41, 42.] вҶ©

End of Canto 15th. Mch. 25, 1823. B.вҒ вҖ”[MS.] вҶ©

March 29, 1823. вҶ©

[Herodotus, Hist., i. 136.] вҶ©

[Hamlet, act ii. sc. 2, line 103.] вҶ©

[The story is told of St.В Thomas Aquinas, that he wrote a work De Omnibus Rebus, which was followed by a second treatise, De Quibusdam Aliis.] вҶ©

[Not St.В Augustine, but Tertullian. See his treatise, De Carne Christi, cap. V. c. (Opera, 1744, p. 310): вҖңCrucifixus est Dei filius: non pudet, quia pudendum est: et mortuus est Dei filius: prorsus credibile est, quia ineptum est: et sepultus resurrexit: certum est quia impossibile est.вҖқ] вҶ©

[вҖңThat the dead are seen no more,вҖқ said Imlac, вҖңI will not undertake to maintain, against the concurrent and unvaried testimony of all ages, and of all nations. There is no people, rude or unlearned, among whom apparitions of the dead are not related and believed. This opinion, which perhaps prevails as far as human nature is diffused, could become universal only by its truth; those that never heard of one another would not have agreed in a tale which nothing but experience can make credible. That it is doubted by single cavillers, can very little weaken the general evidence; and some, who deny it with their tongues, confess it with their fears.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Rasselas, chap. xxx., Works, ed. 1806, iii. 372, 373.] вҶ©

The composition of the old Tyrian purple, whether from a shell-fish, or from cochineal, or from kermes, is still an article of dispute; and even its colourвҒ вҖ”some say purple, others scarlet: I say nothing.

[Kermes is cochineal, the Greek ОәПҢОәОәО№ОҪОҝОҪ. The shell-fish (murex) is the Purpura patula. Both substances were used as dyes.] вҶ©

[See Ovid, Heroid, Epist. ix. line 161.] вҶ©

[Titus used to promise to вҖңbear in mind,вҖқ вҖңto keep on his list,вҖқ the petitions of all his supplicants, and once, at dinner-time, his conscience smote him, that he had let a day go by without a single grant, or pardon, or promotion. Hence his confession. вҖңAmici, diem perdidi!вҖқ Vide Suetonius, De XII. CГҰs., вҖңTitus,вҖқ lib. viii. cap. 8.] вҶ©

[Tuism is not in JohnsonвҖҷs Dictionary. Coleridge has a note dated 1800 (Literary Remains, i. 292), on вҖңegotizing in tuismвҖқ but it was not included in SoutheyвҖҷs Omniana of 1812, and must have been unknown to Byron.] вҶ©

[Sc. toilette, a Gallicism.] вҶ©

[Byron loved to make fact and fancy walk together, but, here, his memory played him false, or his art kept him true. The Black Friar walked and walks in the GuestsвҖҷ Refectory (or Banqueting Hall, or вҖңGalleryвҖқ of this stanza), which adjoins the PriorвҖҷs Parlour, but the room where Byron slept (in a four-post bedвҒ вҖ”a coronet, at each corner, atop) is on the floor above the PriorвҖҷs Parlour, and can only be approached by a spiral staircase. Both rooms look west, and command a view of the вҖңlakeвҖҷs billowвҖқ and the вҖңcascade.вҖқ Moreover, the GuestsвҖҷ Refectory was never hung with вҖңold pictures.вҖқ It would seem that Don Juan (perhaps Byron on an emergency) slept in the PriorвҖҷs Parlour, and that in the visionary Newstead the pictures forsook the Grand Drawing-Room for the Hall. Hence the scene! El Libertado steps out of the Gothic Chamber вҖңforthвҖқ into the вҖңgallery,вҖқ and lo! вҖңa monk in cowl and beads.вҖқ But, Quien sabe? The PsalmistвҖҷs caution with regard to princes is not inapplicable to poets.] вҶ©

[Compare MarinerвҖҷs description of the cave in Hoonga Island (Poetical Works, 1901, v. 629, note 1).] вҶ©

[вҖңThe place,вҖқ wrote Byron to Moore, August 13, 1814, вҖңis worth seeing as a ruin, and I can assure you there was some fun there, even in my time; but that is past. The ghosts, however, and the Gothics, and the waters, and the desolation, make it very lively still.вҖқ вҖңIt was,вҖқ comments Moore (Life, p. 262, note 1), вҖңif I mistake not, during his recent visit to Newstead, that he himself actually fancied he saw the ghost of the Black Friar, which was supposed to have haunted the Abbey from the time of the dissolution of the monasteries, and which he thus describes from the recollection, perhaps, of his own fantasy, in Don Juan.вҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ It is said that the Newstead ghost appeared, also, to Lord ByronвҖҷs cousin, Miss Fanny Parkins, and that she made a sketch of him from memory.вҖқ The legend of the Black Friar may, it is believed at Newstead (et vide post, вҖңSong,вҖқ stanza ii. line 5, p. 583), be traced to the alarm and suspicion of the country-folk, who, on visiting the Abbey, would now and then catch sight of an aged lay-brother, or monkish domestic, who had been retained in the service of the Byrons long after the Canons had been вҖңturned adrift.вҖқ He would naturally keep out of sight of a generation who knew not monks, and, when surprised in the cloisters or ruins of the church, would glide back to his own quarters in the dormitories.] вҶ©

[вҖңShew his eyes, and grieve his heart;
Come like shadows, so depart.вҖқ

Macbeth, act iv. sc. 1, lines 110, 111.]

вҶ©

With that she rose as graceful as a Roe
Slips from the mountain in the month of June,
And opening her Piano вҖҳgan to play
ForthwithвҒ вҖ”вҖңIt was a Friar of Orders Gray.вҖқ

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

By their bed of death he receives their [breath].

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

I think that it was a carpet on which Diogenes trod, withвҒ вҖ”вҖңThus I trample on the pride of Plato!вҖқвҒ вҖ”вҖңWith greater pride,вҖқ as the other replied. But as carpets are meant to be trodden upon, my memory probably misgives me, and it might be a robe, or tapestry, or a table-cloth, or some other expensive and uncynical piece of furniture.

[It was PlatoвҖҷs couch or lounge which Diogenes stamped upon. вҖңSo much for PlatoвҖҷs pride!вҖқ вҖңAnd how much for yours, Diogenes?вҖқ вҖңCalco Platonis fastum!вҖқ вҖңAst fastu alio?вҖқ (Vide Diogenis Laertii De Vita et Sententiis, lib. vi. ed. 1595, p. 321.)

For вҖңAttic Bee,вҖқ vide Cic. I. De Div., xxxvi. В§ 78, вҖңAt Platoni cum in cunis parvulo dormienti apes in labellis consedissent, responsum est, singulari illum suavitate orationis fore.вҖқ] вҶ©

[For two translations of this Portuguese song, see Poetical Works, 1900, iii. 71.] вҶ©

I remember that the mayoress of a provincial town, somewhat surfeited with a similar display from foreign parts, did rather indecorously break through the applauses of an intelligent audienceвҒ вҖ”intelligent, I mean, as to musicвҒ вҖ”for the words, besides being in recondite languages (it was some years before the peace, ere all the world had travelled, and while I was a collegian), were sorely disguised by the performers:вҒ вҖ”this mayoress, I say, broke out with, вҖңRot your Italianos! for my part, I loves a simple ballat!вҖқ Rossini will go a good way to bring most people to the same opinion some day. Who would imagine that he was to be the successor of Mozart? However, I state this with diffidence, as a liege and loyal admirer of Italian music in general, and of much of RossiniвҖҷs; but we may say, as the connoisseur did of painting in The Vicar of Wakefield, that вҖңthe picture would be better painted if the painter had taken more pains.вҖқ

[A little while, and Rossini is being lauded at the expense of a degenerate modern rival. Compare BrowningвҖҷs Bishop BlougramвҖҷs Apology. вҖңWhere sits Rossini patient in his stall.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Poetical Works, ed. 1868, v. 276.] вҶ©

[Compare The Two Foscari, act iii. sc. 1, line 172, Poetical Works, 1901, v. 159, note 1.] вҶ©

[Of Lady Beaumont, who was вҖңweak enoughвҖқ to admire Wordsworth, see The Blues, Ecl. II. line 47, sq., Poetical Works, 1901, iv. 582.] вҶ©

[Christopher Anstey (1724вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1802) published his New Bath Guide in 1766.] вҶ©

[Compare English Bards, etc., lines 309вҒ вҖ“вҒ 318, Poetical Works, 1898, i. 321, note 1.] вҶ©

[For вҖңGynocracy,вҖқ vide ante, p. 473, note 1.] вҶ©

Thrower down of buildingsвҒ вҖ”.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[Byron had, no doubt, inspected the plan of Colonel WildmanвҖҷs elaborate restoration of the Abbey, which was carried out at a cost of one hundred thousand pounds (see stanza lix. lines 1, 2). The kitchen and domestic offices, which extended at right angles to the west front of the Abbey (see вҖңNewstead from a Picture by Peter Tilleman, circ. 1720вҖқ Letters, 1898, i. (to face p.) 216), were pulled down and rebuilt, the massive Sussex Tower (so named in honour of H.R.H. the Duke of Sussex) was erected at the south-west corner of the Abbey, and the south front was, in part, rebuilt and redecorated. Byron had been ready to вҖңleave everythingвҖқ with regard to his beloved Newstead to WildmanвҖҷs вҖңown feelings, present or futureвҖқ (see his letter, November 18, 1818, Letters, 1900, iv. 270); but when the time came, the necessary and, on the whole, judicious alterations of his successor, must have cost the вҖңbanished LordвҖқ many a pang.] вҶ©

вҖңAusu Romano, sere VenetoвҖқ is the inscription (and well inscribed in this instance) on the sea walls between the Adriatic and Venice. The walls were a republican work of the Venetians; the inscription, I believe, Imperial; and inscribed by Napoleon the First. It is time to continue to him that titleвҒ вҖ”there will be a second by and by, вҖңSpes altera mundi,вҖқ if he live; let him not defeat it like his father. But in any case, he will be preferable to вҖңImbГ©ciles.вҖқ There is a glorious field for him, if he know how to cultivate it.

[Francis Charles Joseph Napoleon, Duke of Reichstadt, died at Vienna, July 22, 1832. But, none the less, ByronвҖҷs prophecy was fulfilled.] вҶ©

[Burgage, or tenure in burgage, is where the king or some other person is lord of an ancient borough, in which the tenements are held by a yearly rent certain.] вҶ©

[вҖңI conjure you, by that which you profess,
(HoweвҖҷer you come to know it) answer me:
Though you untie the winds, and let them fight
Against the churches.вҖқ

Macbeth, act iv. sc. 1, lines 50вҒ вҖ“вҒ 53.]

вҶ©

[See the lines вҖңTo my Son,вҖқ Poetical Works, 1898, i. 260, note 1.] вҶ©

[See SpenserвҖҷs FaГ«ry Queen, Book I. Canto IX. stanza 6, line 1.] вҶ©

To name what passes for a puzzle rather,
Although there must be such a thingвҒ вҖ”a father.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[вҖңRather than so, come, Fate, into the list,
And champion me to the utterance.вҖқ

Macbeth, act iii. sc. 1, lines 70, 71.]

вҶ©

[For вҖңSeptemberers (Septembriseurs),вҖқ see CarlyleвҖҷs French Revolution, 1839, iii. 50.] вҶ©

[вҖңQuery, Sydney Smith, author of Peter PlymleyвҖҷs Letters?вҒ вҖ”PrinterвҖҷs Devil.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Ed. 1833. Byron must have met Sydney Smith (1771вҒ вҖ“вҒ 1845) at Holland House. The вҖңfat fen vicarageвҖқ (vide infra, stanza lxxxii. line 8) was Foston-le-Clay (Foston, All Saints), near Barton Hill, Yorkshire, which Lord Chancellor Erskine presented to Sydney Smith in 1806. The вҖңlivingвҖқ consisted of вҖңthree hundred acres of glebe-land of the stiffest clay,вҖқ and there was no parsonage house.вҒ вҖ”See A Memoir of the Rev. Sydney Smith, by Lady Holland, 1855, i. 100вҒ вҖ“вҒ 107.] вҶ©

[вҖңObserve, also, three grotesque figures in the blank arches of the gable which forms the eastern end of St.В HughвҖҷs Chapel,вҖқ and of these, вҖңone is popularly said to represent the вҖҳDevil looking over Lincoln.вҖҷвҖҠвҖқвҒ вҖ”Handbook to the Cathedrals of England, by R.J. King, Eastern Division, p. 394, note x.

The devil looked over Lincoln because the unexampled height of the central tower of the cathedral excited his envy and alarm; or, as Fuller (Worthies: Lincolnshire) has it, вҖңoverlooked this church, when first finished, with a torve and tetrick countenance, as maligning menвҖҷs costly devotions.вҖқ So, at least, the vanity of later ages interpreted the saying; but a time was when the devil вҖңlooked overвҖқ Lincoln to some purpose, for in A.D. 1185 an earthquake clave the Church of Remigius in twain, and in 1235 a great part of the central tower, which had been erected by Bishop Hugh de Wells, fell and injured the rest of the building.] вҶ©

For laughter rarely shakes these aguish folks.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

Took down the gay bon-motвҒ вёә.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

To hammer half a laughвҒ вҖ”.

вҖ”вҒ [MS. erased.]

вҶ©

[вҖңThereвҖҷs a difference to be seen between a beggar and a Queen;
And I вҖҳll tell you the reason why;
A Queen does not swagger, nor get drunk like a beggar,
Nor be half so merry as I,вҖқ etc.

вҖңThereвҖҷs a difference to be seen,вҖҷtwixt a Bishop and a Dean,
And IвҖҷll tell you the reason why;
A Dean can not dish up a dinner like a Bishop,
And thatвҖҷs the reason why!вҖқ]

вҶ©

[вҖңSine Cerere et Libero friget Venus.вҖқ Terentius, Eun., act iv. sc. 5, line 6.] вҶ©

In French вҖңmobilitГ©.вҖқ I am not sure that mobility is English; but it is expressive of a quality which rather belongs to other climates, though it is sometimes seen to a great extent in our own. It may be defined as an excessive susceptibility of immediate impressionsвҒ вҖ”at the same time without losing the past: and is, though sometimes apparently useful to the possessor, a most painful and unhappy attribute.

[вҖңThat he was fully aware not only of the abundance of this quality in his own nature, but of the danger in which it placed consistency and singleness of character, did not require the note on this passage to assure us. The consciousness, indeed, of his own natural tendency to yield thus to every chance impression, and change with every passing impulse, was not only for ever present in his mind, butвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ had the effect of keeping him in that general line of consistency, on certain great subjects, whichвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ he continued to preserve throughout life.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Life, p. 646. вҖңMobilityвҖқ is not the tendency to yield to every impression, to change with every impulse, but the capability of being moved by many and various impressions, of responding to an ever-renewed succession of impulses. Byron is defending the enthusiastic temperament from the charge of inconstancy and insincerity.] вҶ©

[The first edition of CockerвҖҷs Arithmetic was published in 1677. There are many allusions to Cocker in Arthur MurphyвҖҷs Apprentice (1756), whence, perhaps, the saying, вҖңaccording to Cocker.вҖқ] вҶ©

вҖң[Et Horatii] Curiosa felicitas.вҖқвҒ вҖ”Petronius Arbiter, SalyricГҙn, cap. cxviii. вҶ©

[вҖңDamn with faint praise, assent with civil leer,
And without sneering, teach the rest to sneer.вҖқ

Pope on Addison, Prologue to the Satires, lines 201, 202.]

вҶ©

[Bion, Epitaphium Adonidis, line 28.] вҶ©

[вҖқвҒ вҖҠвҒ вҖҰ genetrix hominum, divГҙmque voluptas, Alma Venus!вҖқ Lucret., De Rerum Nat., lib. i. lines 1, 2.] вҶ©

[Job iv. 13.] вҶ©

See the account of the ghost of the uncle of Prince Charles of Saxony, raised by SchroepferвҒ вҖ”вҖңKarlвҒ вҖ”KarlвҒ вҖ”was willst du mit mir?вҖқ

[For Johann Georg Schrepfer (1730(?)-1774), see J.S.B. SchlegelвҖҷs Tagebuch, etc., 1806, and SchwГӨrmer und Schwindler, von Dr.В Eugen Sierke, 1874, pp. 298вҒ вҖ“вҒ 332.] вҶ©

[Inferno, Canto III. line 9.] вҶ©

When once discovered it donвҖҷt like to come near it.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

A beardless chinвҒ вҖ”.

вҖ”вҒ [MS.]

вҶ©

[End of Canto 16. B. My. 6, 1823.вҒ вҖ”MS.] вҶ©

[May 8, 1823.вҒ вҖ”MS. More than one вҖңSeventeenth Canto,вҖқ or so-called continuation of Don Juan, has been published. Some of these вҖңSequelsвҖқ pretend to be genuine, while others are undisguisedly imitations or parodies. For an account of these spurious and altogether worthless continuations, see вҖңBibliography,вҖқ vol. vii. There was, however, a foundation for the myth. Before Byron left Italy he had begun (May 8, 1823) a seventeenth canto, and when he sailed for Greece he took the new stanzas with him. Trelawny found вҖңfifteen stanzas of the seventeenth canto of Don JuanвҖқ in ByronвҖҷs room at Missolonghi (Recollections, etc., 1858, p. 237). The MS., together with other papers, was handed over to John Cam Hobhouse, and is now in the possession of his daughter, the Lady Dorchester. The copyright was purchased by the late John Murray. The fourteen (not fifteen) stanzas are now printed and published for the first time.] вҶ©

The Italians, at least in some parts of Italy, call bastards and foundlings the mulesвҒ вҖ”why, I cannot see, unless they mean to infer that the offspring of matrimony are asses. вҶ©